<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The future state, or, A discourse attempting some display of the souls happiness, in regard to that eternally progressive knowledge, or eternal increase of knowledge, and the consequences of it, which is amongst the blessed in heaven by a country gentleman, a worshipper of God in the way of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J941B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12539468</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12539468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62928</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62928)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 671:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The future state, or, A discourse attempting some display of the souls happiness, in regard to that eternally progressive knowledge, or eternal increase of knowledge, and the consequences of it, which is amongst the blessed in heaven by a country gentleman, a worshipper of God in the way of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Edward.</author>
                  <author>Jones, George, d. 1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>159 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Greenwood ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to George Jones. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62928:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62928:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The FUTURE STATE OR, A DISCOURSE Attempting ſome Diſplay of the <hi>Souls Happineſs,</hi> in regard to that Eternally Progreſſive Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or Eternal Increaſe of Knowledge, and the Conſequences of it, which is amongſt the Bleſſed in Heaven.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Country Gentleman,</hi> a Worſhipper of <hi>God</hi> in the Way of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The Light of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings [in the Kingdom of <hi>God</hi>] will find nothing ſo difficult, dark, and intricate, which they cannot diſ-intangle; and make plain; and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility that we ſhall have in our Ratiocinations, (which will be ſuch, that we ſhall be able to attempt all ſorts of Objects, without any Pain) will cauſe that we ſhall uſe this Contemplation, as with a Succeſs <hi>Eternally Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,</hi> ſo with Content wholly Incomprehenſible.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amyrald.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> himſelf hath <hi>Infinite Goodneſs</hi> in him, which the Creature cannot take in at once; they are taking of it in <hi>Eternally.</hi> The Saints ſee in <hi>God</hi> ſtill <hi>Things Freſh,</hi> which they ſaw not in the <hi>Beginning</hi> of their Bleſſedneſs.</p>
               <bibl>Dr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Greenwood,</hi> at the Crown in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:62928:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62928:2"/>THE Future STATE, <hi>&amp;</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The <hi>Introduction,</hi> and State of the <hi>Probleme.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. I Would not be thought <hi>Peremptory</hi> and <hi>Dogmatical,</hi> in what I ſhall diſcourſe on this Subject: For though the <hi>Reality</hi> of the <hi>Future State</hi> have the Suffrage of all Mankind, and be <hi>Evident</hi> both by Natural and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Light; yet the <hi>Particularities</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are much in the <hi>Dark,</hi> and we know but little <hi>Concerning</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a Caſe ſo <hi>Obſcure,</hi> to be Poſitive and Aſſertory, would ſavour of <hi>Greater</hi> Arrogance, than I am willing to harbour.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62928:3"/>
               <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Suſpicion</hi> in <hi>Things</hi> obſcure, is more <hi>Decorous,</hi> and more <hi>Acceptable,</hi> than <hi>Bold</hi> and <hi>Confident</hi> Aſſertions and Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>Any Thing</hi> ſhould drop from my Pen in the <hi>Progreſs</hi> of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> which may <hi>Seem</hi> too Affirmative, and <hi>Hardly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable with a <hi>Becoming</hi> Modeſty and Jealouſie, I deſire <hi>Thoſe</hi> Luxuriancies of Expreſſions may receive <hi>Some</hi> Abatements, and be made <hi>Fairly</hi> agreeable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For although I may poſſibly be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently <hi>Well</hi> perſwaded of the <hi>Truth</hi> of what I ſhall diſcourſe; yet I am not <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain:</hi> 'Tis not improbable, that I ſhould be <hi>Miſtaken:</hi> I am of <hi>Humane Race,</hi> and have no <hi>Priviledge</hi> of Exemption from <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Infirmities</hi> and <hi>Errours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Therefore what I ſhall ſay on this Point, ſhall be <hi>Problematical</hi> and <hi>Diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> for indeed, by this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> I have as <hi>Much</hi> Inclination to inquire, what <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> think therein, as to deliver my <hi>Own</hi> Apprehenſions concerning it: For although I ſhould not <hi>Demonſtrate</hi> the <hi>Probleme,</hi> (to which I do not indeed pretend) I think it not <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> but that ſome other Perſon may <hi>Do</hi> it.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62928:3"/>
            <p n="6">6. What <hi>Other</hi> Men may have ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready concerning it, I cannot tell; 'tis not impoſſible, but that the <hi>School-Men</hi> may have largely diſcourſed it; for they are a <hi>Bold</hi> and <hi>Daring</hi> ſort of Men, and there is almoſt <hi>Nothing</hi> that eſcapes their <hi>Inquiries</hi> and <hi>Diſquiſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Yet I muſt <hi>Say,</hi> That thoſe <hi>Few</hi> that I have had the Opportunity to <hi>Converſe</hi> in, or <hi>Conſult</hi> withal, ſay <hi>Nothing</hi> at all concerning it: Other Queſtions (in my opinion) of far leſs <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Importance</hi> they debate at large; but of <hi>This</hi> I find nothing, but a <hi>Moſt</hi> deep and <hi>Profound</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Some very <hi>Brief</hi> and <hi>Tranſient</hi> Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages I do nevertheleſs acknowledge to have read of this <hi>Subject,</hi> in ſome other Authors; which were the firſt <hi>Occaſions</hi> of applying my ſelf to the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of it. Had not thoſe Paſſages a little <hi>Moved</hi> and <hi>Ingaged</hi> my Thoughts in the <hi>Contemplation</hi> thereof, I had probably remained <hi>Satisfied</hi> in a general Belief of the <hi>Tranſcendent</hi> Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the <hi>Future Life.</hi> without making any <hi>Particular</hi> Inquiries into the <hi>Nature</hi> of it: Peradventure I might never have <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated,</hi> whether our Knowledge (in which, by the Confeſſion of all <hi>Divines,</hi> it doth much lie, though not wholly conſiſt) be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62928:4"/>Compleat and Perfect <hi>Immediately</hi> upon our Admiſſion into the <hi>Divine Preſence,</hi> or at leaſt at the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the Dead; or whether it be <hi>Eternally</hi> Progreſſive and Increaſing for evermore.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Nevertheleſs it is my <hi>Opinion,</hi> that it may be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful,</hi> to form to our ſelves as <hi>Poſitive, Particular,</hi> and <hi>Determinate</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Future Happineſs,</hi> as we poſſibly can; provided they be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the <hi>Inſpired Writings,</hi> or diſagreeable with the <hi>Revelations</hi> that <hi>God</hi> hath made concerning it.</p>
            <p n="10">10. For <hi>General Accounts</hi> of things are not anear ſo affecting, as a <hi>Plain</hi> and <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Narrative</hi> and <hi>Deſcription</hi> of them. To ſay, That the <hi>Future State</hi> is Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and <hi>Full</hi> of Glory; That thoſe that ſhall be deemed worthy of it, ſhall <hi>See</hi> God, and partake in the <hi>Glory,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> injoyes in the Preſence of his Father, is to ſpeak very <hi>Great</hi> Things, and ſuch as ſhould <hi>Exceedingly</hi> raviſh and affect our <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. But ſuch is the Conſtitution of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Minds,</hi> that <hi>Great</hi> Things do rather amaze, and induce a kind of Stupor upon them, than affect with a <hi>Grateful</hi> pleaſure and Joy. Some <hi>Objects</hi> are too <hi>Big</hi> for our Senſes; our Eye cannot bear the <hi>Light</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62928:4"/>of the <hi>Sun,</hi> in its <hi>Higheſt</hi> Altitude and Splendour. Some <hi>Sounds</hi> are ſo <hi>Great,</hi> that they are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful</hi> and <hi>Offenſive</hi> to our Ears: And there are ſome <hi>Objects</hi> too <hi>Great</hi> for our Minds; and when they are propoſed unto them, they do rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and awaken in them a <hi>Kind</hi> of <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and Admiration, than a <hi>Delightful</hi> Taſt, Savour, and Conſolation.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The <hi>Main</hi> Doctrine of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> is contained in a <hi>Few</hi> Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; 'tis briefly contained in that <hi>Form</hi> of Words, that is uſually called the <hi>Apoſtle's Creed;</hi> and more briefly in the Words u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at our <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> But all know, and muſt confeſs, that till thoſe Things are <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,</hi> and at <hi>Large</hi> explained, they make <hi>Little</hi> Impreſſion upon the <hi>Minds</hi> of Men; they are <hi>Very</hi> little <hi>Moved</hi> or <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected</hi> by them.</p>
            <p n="13">13. It may be therefore <hi>Reaſonably</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that an Explication of the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Future Happineſs</hi> may be acceptable to <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Conſidering</hi> Minds: Thoſe Texts of <hi>Scripture</hi> that deſcribe it, are too <hi>Big</hi> for our Underſtandings. If the Meaning of them can by <hi>Diviſion</hi> be explained, it may be <hi>More</hi> ſuitable to our <hi>Capacities,</hi> and <hi>More</hi> affecting to our <hi>Hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. That the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62928:5"/>in the <hi>Other World</hi> will be <hi>Very</hi> Great, is the Common Confeſſion of all <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> what ever be their Differences in <hi>Other Things,</hi> in <hi>This</hi> they are at <hi>Perfect</hi> Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: They all acknowledge the <hi>Future State,</hi> (called in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven</hi>) <hi>Tranſcendently</hi> Happy and Glorious; and that there is nothing in <hi>This</hi> World, that can be an <hi>Apt</hi> or <hi>Proper</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of it; they are all <hi>Beneath</hi> it, as far as Darkneſs is <hi>Beneath</hi> Light; or the faint Shining of a <hi>Sorry Glow-Worm,</hi> is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Luſtre of the <hi>Sun</hi> in its <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Splendour.</p>
            <p n="15">15. 'Tis alſo confeſſed, that very <hi>Much</hi> of the Happineſs of that <hi>State</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Largeneſs</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> In <hi>This</hi> World, thoſe that know <hi>Moſt,</hi> know very <hi>Little;</hi> thoſe that have the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Reputation for Wiſdom and Underſtanding, are Ignorant and Blind; and what they do ſee, is <hi>Very</hi> darkly, and with much Imperfections: Their <hi>Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are very <hi>Narrow,</hi> their <hi>Faculties</hi> are <hi>Weak;</hi> and can neither Diſcern, nor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend much, by the <hi>Moſt</hi> diligent <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours</hi> and <hi>Applications:</hi> But in the <hi>Other World</hi> their <hi>Capacities</hi> will be enlarged, and their <hi>Faculties</hi> ſtrengthened; and <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> will be <hi>Increaſed,</hi> beyond
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62928:5"/>our preſent <hi>Conceptions</hi> and <hi>Imaginations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. The Knowledge of <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Moſt</hi> excellent Knowledge; He is the <hi>Moſt</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Object; and therefore, the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Him muſt needs be ſo. All Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is valuable according to the <hi>Objects</hi> thereof: Where the One is <hi>Worthy</hi> and <hi>Excellent,</hi> the Other is ſo; where the One is <hi>Mean</hi> and <hi>Worthleſs,</hi> the Other is not <hi>Valuable</hi> or <hi>Regardable.</hi> And hence it is, that even in this World, the Knowledge of <hi>God</hi> ſurpaſſes all other Knowledge, whatſoever it be.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Whatſoever <hi>Conſtitutes</hi> Man happy, muſt be <hi>Analogous,</hi> and ſuitable to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: There muſt be an <hi>Agreeableneſs</hi> between the <hi>Subject,</hi> and the <hi>Object,</hi> or Man cannot be <hi>Happy.</hi> Light, Beauty, and Proportion <hi>Pleaſes</hi> the <hi>Eye;</hi> Muſick, and Harmonious Sounds <hi>Delight</hi> the <hi>Ears;</hi> and Fragrant, and Odoriferous Scents and Perfumes the <hi>Smell:</hi> And the Reaſon is, they are <hi>Congruous</hi> to theſe Faculties; there is a <hi>Proportion</hi> between them.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Man is indued with a <hi>Reaſonable</hi> Soul, and the Knowledge of Things, is very <hi>Suitable</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant</hi> to it: <hi>Muſick</hi> is not more <hi>Pleaſant</hi> to the <hi>Ear,</hi> nor <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Proportion</hi> to the <hi>Eye,</hi> than <hi>Knowledge</hi> to the <hi>Mind</hi> of Man. The Pleaſures of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62928:6"/>and the Delights of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> vaſtly excel all the Pleaſures of <hi>Senſe,</hi> be they never ſo exquiſite or perfect. The Delights of the <hi>Senſual</hi> and <hi>Voluptuous,</hi> are <hi>Mean</hi> and <hi>Brutiſh;</hi> the Delights of <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Knowing</hi> Men, are <hi>Raiſed, Sublime,</hi> and <hi>Angelical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. The <hi>Rational Faculty</hi> is not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in <hi>Knowledge,</hi> but 'tis very much <hi>Perfected</hi> and <hi>Advanced</hi> by it. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any Man's <hi>Knowledge</hi> is, the greater and <hi>More</hi> Perfect is his <hi>Mind;</hi> the leſs any Man is poſſeſſed withal, the leſs and the <hi>More</hi> imperfect and defective is his <hi>Senſe.</hi> Thoſe that have leaſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> have the <hi>Narroweſt</hi> and moſt contracted <hi>Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. Nothing ſo much delights and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the <hi>Minds</hi> of Men, as the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> that's moſt pleaſant, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters greateſt Satisfaction to them: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> quiets, and lays to reſt the Motions, and <hi>Satisfies</hi> the Appetites of them: It alſo perfects, and compleats them. The <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the conſequent Effects thereof, is the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Perfection that they are capable of attaining, poſſeſſing, and injoying either in <hi>This,</hi> or in the <hi>Other World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. In this World, <hi>God</hi> is known by his <hi>Word,</hi> and by his <hi>Works:</hi> All that we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62928:6"/>know of Him, is either by Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Works</hi> of his Hands, or by Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Conſidering the <hi>Revelations</hi> that he hath made of himſelf, in the <hi>Sacred Volums.</hi> From the Effects of his Power, <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> viſible and diſcernable in his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Works,</hi> we come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Thoſe</hi> Perfections, and do form <hi>Thoſe</hi> Notions that we have concerning them.</p>
            <p n="22">22. It ſeems <hi>Probable,</hi> that we ſhall know <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Other State,</hi> after the <hi>Same</hi> manner that we know Him in <hi>This. God</hi> is the ſame <hi>Immutably;</hi> in Him is no <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riableneſs,</hi> nor <hi>Shadow of Turning:</hi> His Nature, Attributes, Excellencies, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, ſuffer no <hi>Alteration.</hi> What He <hi>Is,</hi> He <hi>Was,</hi> and <hi>Will Be</hi> Eternally.</p>
            <p n="23">23. The <hi>Nature</hi> of our Faculties will remain the <hi>Same</hi> There, that they are Here. Gradual <hi>Advantages</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> I do acknowledge they will receive, and thoſe <hi>Very Great</hi> immediately upon their Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thither: But <hi>Gradual Advantages</hi> will not alter the <hi>Specifick</hi> Nature of our Souls. If their <hi>Specifick</hi> Nature were chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, we ſhould ceaſe to be <hi>Men;</hi> and then it would follow, that <hi>Men</hi> obeyed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and another <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> or kind of Creatures will be <hi>Saved</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62928:7"/>and <hi>Damned.</hi> Which ſeems to me very <hi>Abſurd</hi> and <hi>Incongruous.</hi> Whether <hi>God</hi> may awaken any <hi>New</hi> Powers, or Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, after its Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence, I know not; nor will I deny the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of it; for I think it conſiſtent with the Preſervation of our <hi>Specifick Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:</hi> Which is all that I affirm.</p>
            <p n="24">24. If <hi>God</hi> be the <hi>Same</hi> in the <hi>Other State,</hi> and <hi>This,</hi> (as 'tis certain, He is) and if our <hi>Eſſential Faculties</hi> continue the <hi>Same,</hi> I ſee no reaſon, why we may not think it (at leaſt probable) that the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall know <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>Works,</hi> and ſuch other <hi>Revelations,</hi> as he ſhall make of himſelf there.</p>
            <p n="25">25. And indeed, I cannot tell of what Uſe the <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Objects in that <hi>State</hi> will be, unleſs they diſcover to us the <hi>Excellencies</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Of what Uſe will the <hi>Pomp</hi> and <hi>Splendour,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Luſtre</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>God</hi> be, if it learn us nothing of his <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Admirable</hi> Attributes and Perfections? This is the <hi>Great,</hi> though not the <hi>Only,</hi> Uſe of all things in <hi>This World;</hi> and ſuch I conceive will be the Uſe of them, in <hi>That</hi> which is to come.</p>
            <p n="26">26. VVhether <hi>God</hi> will make Uſe of any <hi>Second Cauſes,</hi> for the <hi>Maintenance</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62928:7"/>and <hi>Support</hi> of our <hi>Beings,</hi> (though it ſeem to me probable) yet I will not affirm, but if that ſhould be granted, yet it cannot with any <hi>Reaſon</hi> be imagined, that <hi>That</hi> is the <hi>Only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of them: 'Tis not the <hi>Only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of them Here; nor is it in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure probable, 'twill be the <hi>Only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of them There. <hi>The Heavens declare the Glory of God;</hi> and ſo do all the Beings that are contained in it, and encompaſſed by it: And I make no doubt, the <hi>Heaven of Heavens,</hi> and all the <hi>Illustrious Objects</hi> there, are of the <hi>Same <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> and deſigned to the <hi>Same</hi> Intent and Purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="27">27. That the <hi>Objects</hi> in the <hi>Other World</hi> will contribute towards the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the Bleſſed, I ſhall affirm: But yet 'tis (I conceive) by acquainting us with the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating the <hi>Tranſcendency,</hi> and <hi>Riches</hi> of his <hi>Love,</hi> his <hi>Bounty,</hi> and his <hi>Grace.</hi> 'Tis <hi>God</hi> is the great <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Humane Happineſs;</hi> and in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of Him, and the conſequent Fruits and Effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is the <hi>Supreme Felicity</hi> of Men. <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Beings</hi> promote our Happineſs only by revealing the <hi>Excellencies</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us a <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Perception</hi> of them.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62928:8"/>
            <p n="28">28. Some School-men (I do eaſily grant) do aſſert an <hi>Immediate Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>World to come:</hi> But I am not ſatisfied in the <hi>Proofs</hi> and <hi>Evidences,</hi> that they bring in favour of it; and <hi>many</hi> (if not <hi>most</hi>) <hi>Proteſtants</hi> reject the Opinion; and with very <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable</hi> Reaſons, <hi>Confute</hi> what they <hi>Affirm,</hi> and lay down for the Support of it. <hi>Vid. Voet. diſput. ſelect.</hi> Pag. 1193. Vol. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Cum multis aliis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">29. But though it be granted, That the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will conſiſt very <hi>Much</hi> in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, it may be doubted, whether <hi>This Knowledge</hi> be <hi>Perpetually</hi> Increaſing, or whether it be <hi>Inſtantaneous,</hi> and preſent it ſelf to the Eye of the <hi>Mind,</hi> as Light to the <hi>Bodily</hi> Eye, which no ſooner appears above the Horizon, than all Eyes are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned thereby in a moment.</p>
            <p n="30">30. I am prone to think <hi>This Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> Progreſſive and Increaſing; and that <hi>Mary Ages</hi> ſpent in the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> will furniſh the Bleſſed with <hi>More</hi> of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Him, than they were endowed withal upon their firſt <hi>Admiſſion</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance</hi> there. I cannot think, that the <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> of Ages (pardon the Expreſſion) that do compound an <hi>Everlasting Duration,</hi> will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62928:8"/>make no <hi>Increaſe</hi> in the Knowledge of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> nor add no <hi>Perfection</hi> to their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">31. VVhether the <hi>Proofs</hi> that I ſhall make of this <hi>Probleme</hi> be <hi>Valid</hi> or <hi>Invalid,</hi> the <hi>Reader</hi> muſt determine, when he hath <hi>Weighed</hi> and <hi>Conſidered</hi> them. I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that they be eſteemed as they are. 'Tis no part of our <hi>Creed,</hi> that I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending. If my <hi>Arguments</hi> be thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid, and my <hi>Opinion</hi> rejected, 'twill be no matter of Provocation to me: If <hi>They</hi> be thought cogent, and my <hi>Opinion</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Acceptation with <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Men, perchance I may be a little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therein: But if it may advance the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and make <hi>Heaven</hi> any whit the more acceptable to the Thoughts and Meditations of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> I am ſure I ſhall greatly rejoyce.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Theſe Things being premiſed, 'twill be adviſeable to propoſe the <hi>Probleme, [Knowledge Eternally Progreſſive]</hi> and give the Senſe wherein I underſtand it.</p>
            <p n="33">33. The word <hi>Knowledge</hi> I take in the largeſt Meaning and Signification; I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it not in the <hi>Strict</hi> Senſe of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> for the Knowledge of Things by their proper <hi>Efficient,</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutive Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> but in a <hi>General</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited</hi> Senſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62928:9"/>for <hi>All Kinds</hi> of Knowledge, by whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever means, or after whatſoever manner it be obtained.</p>
            <p n="34">34. By <hi>Eternally Progreſſive,</hi> I mean <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtingly Increaſing;</hi> it will Advance for <hi>Ever;</hi> it will never arrive at that <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> beyond which it can proceed no further. The <hi>Viſible</hi> World is <hi>Finite,</hi> the Extenſion thereof is <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi> The <hi>Waves</hi> of the Sea have their Bounds prefixed, and ſet unto them: Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, ſays <hi>God, ſhall they come,</hi> and no farther; and here ſhall their Rage <hi>be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped:</hi> But Humane Knowledge hath <hi>No Bounds</hi> affixed unto it; it may Increaſe to all Durations.</p>
            <p n="35">35. By the <hi>Future State,</hi> I mean the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> after their Departure hence. There is <hi>Another World</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> Conſequent and Future to <hi>This. Humane Souls</hi> do not periſh, when they leave their <hi>Bodies;</hi> they ſubſiſt in <hi>Another</hi> State, and do <hi>Advance</hi> in Knowledge <hi>There,</hi> as well as <hi>Here: Here</hi> 'tis obviouſly <hi>Progreſſive;</hi> and I ſee no reaſon, why it may not be ſo <hi>There. Here</hi> we proceed gradually in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of Things; and ſuch is the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of our Faculties, that 'tis in my Apprehenſion <hi>Impoſſible</hi> it ſhould be otherwiſe: And I cannot imagine,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62928:9"/>that <hi>Death</hi> ſhould make ſo great an <hi>Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> in them, that what was before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> ſhould become not only <hi>Poſſible,</hi> but <hi>Neceſſary</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>navoidable;</hi> for ſuch muſt our Knowledge be, if it be Perfect, <hi>Immediately</hi> upon our Diſſolution and Departure hence.</p>
            <p n="36">36. By the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> I mean ſuch as <hi>God</hi> ſhall deem <hi>Worthy</hi> and <hi>Meet</hi> to be Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Inheritance of the <hi>Saints in Light;</hi> ſuch as having done his <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and performed the Terms of the <hi>Goſpel-Covenant,</hi> have Right to the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> and Admiſſion <hi>Through the Gates into the City.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62928:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The <hi>Probability</hi> of the <hi>Queſtion</hi> argued from the Conſideration of the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and Man.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Queſtion</hi> being thus briefly ſtated, I ſhall lay down ſuch <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> as ſhall render it fairly <hi>Probable</hi> to Perſons of <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprejudiced</hi> Minds, and will give themſelves Liberty to conſider Things, without <hi>Byaſs</hi> and <hi>Partiality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God</hi>'s Perfections are <hi>Infinite;</hi> his Power hath <hi>No Limits</hi> of Extenſion: He can effect all things, that are the <hi>Effects</hi> of Power. There is nothing <hi>Impoſſible</hi> unto Him: His Wiſdom is of <hi>Vaſt</hi> Extent, and reaches all things. There is nothing can eſcape the Cognizance of his <hi>Infinite</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: His Goodneſs is of <hi>Equal</hi> Extent with his Power and Wiſdom; it touches all things that are the <hi>Proper</hi> and <hi>Congruous</hi> Objects thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though Man receive <hi>Great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62928:10"/>immediately upon his Admiſſion into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Heaven; yet he ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains a <hi>Finite Creature:</hi> His removal from this <hi>Howling Wilderneſs,</hi> doth not make him a <hi>God,</hi> nor endow him with <hi>Divine Perfections:</hi> He remains <hi>There</hi> a <hi>Finite Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> and of <hi>Limited Powers.</hi> Though he be <hi>Mightily Advanced,</hi> and his Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities <hi>Enlarged</hi> beyond our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions; yet he is ſtill a <hi>Creature,</hi> and his Nature remains the <hi>Same</hi> invariably.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Finite</hi> Creature can never compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend an <hi>Infinite</hi> Creator: The Globe of the Earth cannot be contained in a <hi>Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell,</hi> nor the Waters of the Ocean in a <hi>Bottle</hi> or <hi>Tankard:</hi> The Hills cannot be crowded into a <hi>Cottage,</hi> nor the Mountains into a <hi>Shepherds Tent.</hi> There is no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous Proportion between the <hi>One,</hi> and the <hi>Other;</hi> And there is far leſs Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between the Underſtanding of <hi>Man,</hi> and the Perfections of <hi>God:</hi> The One is <hi>Finite,</hi> the Other is <hi>Infinite;</hi> and between them there can be no <hi>Analogy:</hi> Whereas there is ſome betwixt all <hi>Created</hi> Beings, (though ſometimes very ſmall) foraſmuch as they are all <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Man muſt <hi>Know</hi> (though not <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi>) the Excellencies and Perfections of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62928:11"/>
               <hi>God,</hi> or he cannot be <hi>Happy.</hi> All Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites have their <hi>Proper</hi> Objects, and in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Fruition</hi> of them, they find their <hi>Content</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> and in the <hi>Abſence</hi> of them, they find <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> This we find true, in the <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of every Day. Men have Appetite and Inclination to a <hi>Sociable</hi> Life; and therefore, in the Company and Society of Seconds, they find <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Repoſe;</hi> and Solitude is <hi>Irkſome</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful</hi> to them. They have <hi>Appetites</hi> and <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to <hi>Eat,</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> and <hi>Reſt;</hi> and in the Enjoyment of the <hi>Objects</hi> of thoſe <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites,</hi> they are <hi>Pleaſed</hi> and <hi>Satisfied;</hi> and if they be deprived of them in their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> Seaſons, they are <hi>Troubled</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Man hath an <hi>Inclination</hi> and <hi>Deſire</hi> to know God: 'Tis <hi>Natural</hi> to him, to proceed from the <hi>Effect</hi> to the <hi>Neareſt</hi> Cauſe, and from <hi>That</hi> to the <hi>Next;</hi> and ſo in an <hi>Orderly</hi> and <hi>Regular</hi> Gradation, till it aſcend to <hi>God,</hi> the Prime <hi>Cauſe</hi> of all Things; and there it <hi>Rests,</hi> and is <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> That's the <hi>Proper</hi> and <hi>Terminating</hi> Object of all <hi>Humane Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition:</hi> When we have purſued things thither, were we ſit down in <hi>Complacency,</hi> and ſolace our ſelves in our <hi>Acquſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62928:11"/>
            <p n="6">6. What the <hi>Mind</hi> of Man cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the <hi>Divine</hi> Perfections at <hi>Once,</hi> it may receive at <hi>Many</hi> times, and by Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: The Soul being a <hi>Limited</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, it cannot receive or know much of the <hi>Excellencies</hi> of God, at one <hi>Single</hi> Graſp or Fathome; but at ſeveral times, and <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively,</hi> it may know much; and how <hi>much,</hi> is not ſafe to ſay or determine. <hi>Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> Men cannot paſs the <hi>Gates</hi> of a City at once; but in ſucceſſion of Time, <hi>Many Millions</hi> may do it. All the Water in the Ocean could not paſs the Mouth of the Streights of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> at one Point of Time; but in a <hi>Continued</hi> ſpace of Time, it might certainly do it, ſuppoſing nothing elſe did hinder it. There is no <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician,</hi> that at one view of his Mind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds all the Propoſitions in <hi>Euclid, Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius,</hi> and <hi>Archimedes,</hi> with their ſeveral Demonſtrations; but many have done it <hi>Succeſſively;</hi> and indeed all that are <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> in that Pleaſant and Ingenious Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Infinite</hi> Perfections (and ſuch are thoſe of <hi>God</hi>) can never be exhauſted: As <hi>Infinite</hi> Duration cannot be meaſured, ſo <hi>Infinite</hi> Perfections cannot be drained: Whatſoever is exhauſtible, is <hi>Finite;</hi> whatſoever may be ſathomed by <hi>Humane</hi> Underſtandings,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62928:12"/>is of <hi>Limited</hi> Nature and Perfection: That which is <hi>Infinite,</hi> contains thoſe Depths that can <hi>Never</hi> be ſounded. And ſuch are the <hi>Properties</hi> and <hi>Excellencies</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> The Days of <hi>Eternity</hi> will never <hi>Fully</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly</hi> reveal and expoſe them. After all our <hi>Search</hi> into them, we ſhall never <hi>Find</hi> them out unto Perfection.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Therefore they may furniſh Matter and Subject for <hi>Eternal</hi> Contemplation: They may <hi>Perpetually</hi> exerciſe our <hi>Minds,</hi> and miniſter new <hi>Occaſion</hi> for our Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. There will be no defect of <hi>Matter</hi> for our Thoughts, nor Subject for our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.</hi> An Object of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> may well afford <hi>Reaſon, Occaſion,</hi> and <hi>Foundation,</hi> for everlaſting <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Conſiderations.</hi> Where the Object is <hi>Inexhauſtible</hi> in its Virtues, the Thoughts may be <hi>Eternal</hi> in their Inquiries and Search concerning them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whatſoever is known of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Future State,</hi> will be either by <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Supernatural</hi> Revelation. God will be known by the <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Works of his Hands. The Objects that adorn the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> will declare the <hi>Glorious</hi> Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of their Maker; every thing <hi>There,</hi> will ſpeak forth his Praiſe, unveile his <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and render it <hi>Conſpicuous</hi> to thoſe that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62928:12"/>ſhall be admitted to behold it <hi>There:</hi> And peradventure, there may be ſome <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> Ways of Revelation, which may uncover ſomething of the <hi>Divine</hi> Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies even <hi>There,</hi> as well as <hi>Here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. The <hi>Objects</hi> or <hi>Works</hi> that reveal and diſcover the <hi>Attributes</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of God to the Bleſſed, in the World to come, will be <hi>Very</hi> great and <hi>Many;</hi> and how great and <hi>Many</hi> they may be, can neither be determined, nor imagined. Thoſe that reveal him <hi>Here,</hi> are <hi>Many,</hi> and ſome of them <hi>Very</hi> great and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. And ſurely, it cannot be juſtly thought, but that the <hi>Things</hi> that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal God in the <hi>Other State,</hi> will be as nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and much <hi>More great</hi> and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; it being deſigned to illuſtrate and ſet forth the <hi>Glory</hi> of God in a moſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent</hi> manner. He will there be <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his Saints, and admired in thoſe that believe.</hi> And he cannot attain this <hi>Glory,</hi> unleſs there be ſomething <hi>Very great</hi> to reveal, and lay him open before us.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The Mind of Man is <hi>Fitted</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted</hi> to the Uſe of <hi>Knowing;</hi> and 'tis pleaſed therein. This is true in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of <hi>Moſt,</hi> if not of <hi>All</hi> Men. There are very <hi>Few,</hi> if <hi>Any,</hi> that are not delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62928:13"/>in <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> Some <hi>Brutiſh</hi> Senſualiſts, and <hi>Covetous</hi> Earth-Worms, may be ſo <hi>ſwallowed</hi> up among <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>Senſual</hi> Things, that they may have loſt almoſt <hi>All</hi> Deſire of Knowledge, and all <hi>Taste</hi> and <hi>Senſe</hi> of Pleaſure in it: But 'tis <hi>Apparently</hi> otherwiſe in Multitudes of others, and in all of <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>Ingenuous</hi> Minds; and in the moſt Profligate and Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh at <hi>ſometimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. God imploys all things to their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> Ends and Uſes in <hi>This</hi> World; and I ſee no cauſe to doubt, but he will do ſo in the <hi>Other.</hi> He <hi>Made</hi> the Sun to heat, warm, and enlighten the <hi>World;</hi> and ſo he <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> and <hi>Imploys</hi> it. He <hi>Made</hi> the Earth, that it might bring forth Graſs, and Trees, and Fruits, for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of Man and Beaſt: And to that end, he <hi>Hath</hi> and <hi>Doth</hi> imploy it. And the like may be ſaid, and is <hi>Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly</hi> viſible in <hi>All</hi> the Works of his Hands; they <hi>All</hi> ſerve the Ends and Purpoſes, to which by their <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> they are fitted and prepared.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The <hi>Humane</hi> Soul is not only adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Knowing,</hi> but it hath a very <hi>Vigorous</hi> and <hi>Paſſionate</hi> Deſire after it; and that Deſire is <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Eſſential</hi> to it. Hunger and Thirſt are not <hi>More Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> to our <hi>Bodies,</hi> in their preſent State
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62928:13"/>and Conſtitution, than the Deſire of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is unto our <hi>Minds;</hi> and they can no more put off the <hi>One,</hi> than the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. This Deſire will not only be <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,</hi> but <hi>Perfected, Enlarged,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed</hi> in the <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of God. It will receive no <hi>Abatement,</hi> much leſs an <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation There;</hi> but it will become much more eager, ſharp, and earneſt. 'Tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much dead in all Men (though not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually) here <hi>Below:</hi> But it proceeds from the <hi>Sinful Depravations</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of the Soul, when it ſhall return to <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Soundneſs,</hi> that Dſiere will <hi>Revive,</hi> and become <hi>Vigorous, Brisk,</hi> and <hi>Active.</hi> In Bodily <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> the Appetites of Hunger and Thirſt do ſometimes <hi>Languiſh,</hi> and almoſt <hi>Dye;</hi> but when <hi>Health</hi> returns, thoſe Appetites return with it, and become as <hi>Quick</hi> and <hi>Preſſing</hi> as ever.</p>
            <p n="15">15. This Inclination muſt have <hi>Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> or elſe Heaven will be Mans <hi>Torment,</hi> not his <hi>Happineſs. Eager</hi> Appetites, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Suitable</hi> Objects for their Satisfaction, are an <hi>Inſupportable</hi> Miſery; and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, they may be much of the <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Damned:</hi> Whether that be ſo, yea or no, I will not determine: But ſure I am, and the Experience of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind confirms it, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſatisfied Deſires</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62928:14"/>are a great Vexation and Anguiſh: They are like <hi>Hunger</hi> and <hi>Thirſt,</hi> where there is no <hi>Bread</hi> or <hi>Water,</hi> or any Congruous Object to <hi>Quiet,</hi> or take off their <hi>Fury,</hi> and their <hi>Rage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. Nothing can ſatisfie <hi>This</hi> Appetite and Deſire, but ſuch things as are <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> unto it. Deſires of <hi>Knowledge</hi> muſt be ſatisfied by <hi>Intelligible</hi> Objects; as that of <hi>Seeing</hi> is quieted with things <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Congruous</hi> to the <hi>Viſive</hi> Faculty; and that of <hi>Hearing,</hi> with things <hi>Audible</hi> and <hi>Analogous</hi> to that Senſe: So that of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is appeaſed by Objects <hi>Agreeable</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The Soul of Man is an <hi>Active</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: We find it ſo <hi>Here;</hi> and 'tis more than probable, 'twill be ſo <hi>Hereafter:</hi> When 'tis looſened from this groſs and heavy Body, 'twill be <hi>More</hi> active, and and not <hi>Leſs:</hi> And yet even <hi>Here,</hi> ſome think 'tis <hi>Never</hi> Idle; when the <hi>Body</hi> Reſts, the <hi>Mind</hi> is Imployed; as is <hi>Obvious</hi> in our Dreams: And though we have no <hi>Memory</hi> of them, yet it may well be thought, that we never ſleep without them.</p>
            <p n="18">18. An <hi>Active</hi> Eſſence, without <hi>Objects</hi> whereon to imploy its Faculties and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, muſt needs be a very <hi>Great</hi> Burthen to it ſelf. Hence it is, that <hi>Here</hi> below,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62928:14"/>we are ſo <hi>Impatient</hi> of Idleneſs, and that 'tis ſo burdenſom to Men, to have <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> to do; nothing almoſt being more <hi>Irkſome</hi> and <hi>Intolerable.</hi> And thence Men. that are not preſſed by <hi>Neceſſity</hi> to uſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Labours, nor have no great Taſte or Savour in <hi>Reading</hi> and <hi>Meditation,</hi> have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Play and Divertiſements, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the <hi>Active</hi> Powers of their Souls, and to avoid the <hi>Inſupportable</hi> Burthen of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. New <hi>Objects,</hi> and New <hi>Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> do moſt affect our Minds, and make the moſt <hi>Grateful</hi> Impreſſions on them in <hi>Time:</hi> And 'tis not unlikely, but they will do ſo in <hi>Eternity.</hi> Thoſe that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in <hi>Books,</hi> and Contemplate and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the <hi>Nature</hi> of Things, do find themſelves <hi>Senſibly</hi> affected with new things. Thence 'tis ſaid, That <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a <hi>Hecatomb</hi> to the Gods, upon his finding out the Demonſtration of the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-ſeventh Propoſition</hi> of the Firſt Book of <hi>Euclid.</hi> He was ſo raviſhed with that <hi>New Diſcovery,</hi> that he knew not how <hi>Sufficiently</hi> to teſtify his Gratitude unto them. 'Tis not to be doubted, but that he knew many things in <hi>Geometry,</hi> and had skill in <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi> before he found the Artifice of <hi>Demonſtrating</hi> that Propoſition: But this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62928:15"/>was <hi>New,</hi> and made more <hi>Pleaſant</hi> Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon him, than all his <hi>Other</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p n="20">20. As in Numbers, there is, nor can be none ſo great, to which ſome <hi>Increaſe</hi> may not be made by Addition; and yet <hi>Number</hi> will never be <hi>Infinite:</hi> So in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, I conceive, they neither are, nor can be ſo <hi>Many,</hi> to which no Addition can be made by an <hi>Infinite</hi> Power; and yet they will ſtill remain <hi>Finite:</hi> For <hi>Infinity</hi> is an <hi>Incommunicable</hi> Attribute and Property of <hi>God,</hi> and nothing is capable of it beſides Him.</p>
            <p n="21">21. If <hi>Beings</hi> may <hi>Everlaſtingly</hi> increaſe, there is no reaſon to doubt, but <hi>Knowledge</hi> may increaſe in <hi>Proportion</hi> with them: If the <hi>One</hi> may receive Advantage, and be multiplied, the <hi>Other</hi> may do ſo likewiſe. For <hi>Beings,</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Properties</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> of them, are the <hi>Objects</hi> of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Underſtanding; and Men's Science is <hi>Greater</hi> or <hi>Leſs,</hi> according to the <hi>Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> or <hi>Leſs</hi> variety of <hi>Objects</hi> that they are acquainted withal.</p>
            <p n="22">22. But of the <hi>Variety</hi> of Objects, that will be propoſed to the Contemplation of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>God,</hi> and of the <hi>Probability</hi> or <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of an <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Increaſe of Knowledge thence, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62928:15"/>to diſcourſe in the <hi>Next Chapter;</hi> and therefore, I'le here Conclude <hi>This.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the <hi>Objective Evidences</hi> and <hi>Probabilities</hi> of the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. HAving ſaid ſomething in the <hi>Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chapter,</hi> from the <hi>Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> compared with the <hi>Nature, Faculties,</hi> and <hi>Inclinations</hi> of Man, to <hi>Prove,</hi> or at leaſt make <hi>Probable</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> that I have aſſerted; I ſhall now proceed to propoſe ſome <hi>Objective</hi> Reaſons and Evidences for the farther Eſtabliſhment and Proof of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Viſible World is of very <hi>Vaſt</hi> Extent; and no Man can determine the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits</hi> of it. Who can with any Certainty ſay, This is the <hi>Compaſs,</hi> and Theſe are the <hi>Extenſions</hi> of the Earth and Heaven? Who can tell me the <hi>Diameter</hi> of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Fabrick, that preſents it ſelf to our Eyes? Where is the <hi>Mathematician,</hi> that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62928:16"/>will deſcribe the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of its Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? They have pretended to give us the <hi>Diameter</hi> and <hi>Circumference</hi> of the Earth, the <hi>Diſtance</hi> of the <hi>Planetary</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from it, and from each other; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their <hi>Peripheries</hi> and <hi>Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes:</hi> But none ever dared to determine the Magnitude of the <hi>Whole</hi> World, or ſo much as to gueſs at its Extenſions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Earth on which we dwell (and which, in compariſon with the <hi>Whole World,</hi> is but a Point, by the Confeſſion of the greateſt <hi>Mathematicians</hi>) furniſhes an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Infinite</hi> Number of <hi>Objects</hi> to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation. How numerous are the <hi>Kinds</hi> of <hi>Beings</hi> on the Earth, and in the Sea? What Naturaliſt hath ever pretended to give us an <hi>Exact</hi> Hiſtory of them? The Kinds of Birds, and Beaſts, and Fiſhes, and Inſects, are to us <hi>Incomputable;</hi> and ſo are the <hi>Kinds</hi> of <hi>Herbs,</hi> and Flowers, and Earths, and Minerals, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What <hi>Kinds</hi> of Beings, and how <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous</hi> they may be in the Superiour Parts of <hi>This World,</hi> we cannot ſay; but 'tis not <hi>Improbable,</hi> but they may be Repleniſhed with Beings <hi>Suitable</hi> to their Quality and Condition. The higher Parts of this <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious</hi> Fabrick are much more Pure,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62928:16"/>Clean, and Splendid, than this <hi>Howling Wilderneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Caliginous</hi> Air that doth encompaſs, and ſurround it; and it may be, the <hi>Beings</hi> that inhabit them, may as much <hi>Tranſcend</hi> thoſe <hi>Here,</hi> as the Place of the <hi>One</hi> doth <hi>Tranſcend</hi> that of the <hi>Other.</hi> This Earth ſeems to be one of the meaneſt <hi>Parts</hi> of the Univerſe; and perhaps, the Beings in it, may be the <hi>Meaneſt</hi> in their Kinds of all the Works of <hi>God</hi>'s Hands.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There may be <hi>Other</hi> Worlds now Exiſting, beſides that which falls under our Knowledge and Obſervation. Some <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers</hi> have diſcourſed of an <hi>Infinity</hi> of Worlds; and thought ſuch an Opinion <hi>Worthy</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Power is <hi>Infinite,</hi> and Goodneſs <hi>Inexhauſtible.</hi> I like not the Notion of <hi>Infinite Worlds;</hi> but I think it not impoſſible, but that there may be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Others,</hi> beſides <hi>This,</hi> of which we are a Part, and which is offered to our <hi>View</hi> and <hi>Contemplation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. There may have been <hi>Other Worlds</hi> Pre-exiſtent to <hi>This.</hi> The <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> do aſſure us, that <hi>This World</hi> was made <hi>Five Thouſand,</hi> and <hi>Some Hundreds</hi> of Years ſince: But it no where ſays, That there never was <hi>Any World</hi> before it; it no where affirms, That <hi>God Never</hi> produced any <hi>Created</hi> Being, or Syſteme of Beings, till
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62928:17"/>he gave Exiſtence to the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> and all the <hi>Hoſt</hi> of them: Of which <hi>Moſes</hi> diſcourſes in the Firſt and Second Chapters of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And truly, he that conſiders the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivity, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Fecundity</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, will hardly be able to think, that <hi>God Never</hi> gave Being to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, will a <hi>Few</hi> Years ſince; a <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> with Him, are but as <hi>One Day:</hi> And is it imaginable, that he ſhould purpoſe to have ſuch <hi>Eſſences,</hi> as ſhould partake with Him in his Happineſs, and Glory, to all <hi>Eternity, a Parte poſt;</hi> and yet <hi>a Parte ante,</hi> ſhould never produce <hi>Any,</hi> till about <hi>Five</hi> or <hi>Six</hi> Days ago? This will ſeem very <hi>Improbable</hi> to a Conſidering or Inquiring Man.</p>
            <p n="8">8. There may be a <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of Worlds, after the Conflagration of <hi>This;</hi> and to how long Continuance this <hi>Succeſſion</hi> may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, I will not pretend to judge. 'Twere great Temerity and Preſumption, for any Mortal to ſay, <hi>Hitherunto</hi> will it proceed, and no <hi>Farther;</hi> and here will <hi>God</hi> reſt, and put a Period to the Exerciſe of his <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Power and Virtue.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In thoſe <hi>Other</hi> Worlds paſt, preſent, and to come, there may have been, and there may be <hi>Various</hi> Kinds of Beings; of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62928:17"/>which we have no Knowledge or Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance in <hi>This.</hi> The Kinds of Beings here Below, are exceeding <hi>Numerous,</hi> as I have obſerved already; and differing <hi>Countreys</hi> do produce differing Species and Kinds of <hi>Creatures: America</hi> will furniſh us with <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Trees, Fruits</hi> and <hi>Minerals,</hi> with <hi>Fiſh</hi> and <hi>Fowls</hi> of <hi>Other</hi> Natures and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, than any that are found in <hi>Europe. Africa,</hi> and the <hi>Southern Iſlands</hi> do abound with many things, that <hi>Aſia</hi> and the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Countreys</hi> are utter Strangers unto.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And if <hi>Several Countreys,</hi> on the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the ſame <hi>Earth,</hi> do furniſh to us <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Differing</hi> Beings; we may reaſonably judge, that <hi>Several Worlds</hi> in the ſame <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> or <hi>Creation,</hi> will ſupply us with very great <hi>Variety</hi> and <hi>Difference</hi> of Creatures.</p>
            <p n="11">11. There may be <hi>Sundry</hi> Gradual Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences among the <hi>Same</hi> Kinds of Beings: Thus 'tis on <hi>Earth;</hi> and ſo it may be in <hi>Other Parts</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Creation, amongſt <hi>Men</hi> that are of the ſame <hi>Specifick</hi> Nature. Gradual <hi>Varieties</hi> are almoſt <hi>Infinite;</hi> ſome have the Perfections of <hi>Angels</hi> almoſt, and others are raiſed but little above the Craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier ſort of <hi>Brutes:</hi> And the <hi>Intermediate</hi> Differences between theſe <hi>Extreams,</hi> are innumerable. And the ſame may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62928:18"/>in other <hi>Kinds</hi> of Beings. And this <hi>Variety,</hi> together with the ſeveral <hi>Cauſes, Reaſons,</hi> and <hi>Ends</hi> thereof, will afford <hi>Great</hi> Subject and Matter for Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The Supreme Heavens (there is no doubt) will afford and miniſter great <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety</hi> of <hi>Wonders</hi> to our Meditation. 'Tis the <hi>Palace</hi> of the <hi>Great King;</hi> 'tis the <hi>Houſe of God;</hi> the Place wherein he gives the greateſt Demonſtrations of his <hi>Glorious Perfections,</hi> and eſpecially of his <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> and remunerating <hi>Bounty</hi> and <hi>Grate:</hi> And certainly, ſuch a Place muſt needs be very <hi>Illuſtrious;</hi> it muſt be adorned with things <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Wonderful;</hi> it muſt be embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with what will create <hi>Extaſie</hi> and <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> Nothing <hi>Mean</hi> is ſeen in the <hi>Courts</hi> of Great <hi>Kings;</hi> all things <hi>There</hi> are full of <hi>Splendour, Stately, Magnificenct,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>Their Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs:</hi> And it cannot be ſuppoſed, but that the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> will be as <hi>Worthy</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and as <hi>Suitable</hi> to his <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> as are the <hi>Courts</hi> of Mortal <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. The Diſtance betwixt <hi>God,</hi> and the Greateſt <hi>Monarchs</hi> upon Earth, is <hi>Infinite;</hi> there is no <hi>Analogy</hi> or <hi>Proportion</hi> between their Greatneſs. What Proportion is there between the <hi>Waters</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62928:18"/>
               <hi>Hollow</hi> of a Man's <hi>Hands?</hi> What Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is there between the <hi>Duſt</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and a <hi>Meaſure?</hi> Some Proportion there is between them, becauſe they are all <hi>Finite:</hi> But between <hi>God,</hi> and his Creatures, even the Greateſt and moſt Sublime amongſt them, there is no Proportion: <hi>God</hi> being of <hi>Boundleſs</hi> and <hi>Infinite</hi> Perfections; and they being all of <hi>Limited</hi> Nature and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
            <p n="14">14. If we may gueſs at the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> by the <hi>Tranſcendent</hi> Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Eſſence and Perfections, (and I know not by what elſe we may make our Conjectures concerning it) we muſt ſay, That the <hi>Splendour</hi> of it, ſurpaſſes that of the <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Mortal Kings,</hi> almoſt as much as <hi>God</hi> ſurpaſſes Them. The Fabrick of <hi>Heaven,</hi> that <hi>Houſe not made with Hands,</hi> tranſcends the moſt <hi>Pompous Palaces</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> almoſt as much as <hi>God Tranſcends</hi> Them in Power, State, and Glory.</p>
            <p n="15">15. In the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> (at leaſt, after the <hi>Reſurrection</hi>) Man will be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of a Body and a Soul: And this <hi>Glorious Fabrick</hi> will contribute much to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of both. 'Twill be an Object, and a State ſuitable to the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Appetites of the <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Bodies,</hi> where-withal they will be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62928:19"/>endowed. What thoſe <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites</hi> will be, I cannot define; nor how <hi>Great</hi> the Changes and Advantages will be, that they will receive with the <hi>Change</hi> and <hi>Alteration</hi> of the Body, on that <hi>Great Day:</hi> But all confeſs, (and there is no doubt of it) That the <hi>One</hi> will be the <hi>Rule,</hi> and the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of the <hi>Other;</hi> the Change of the <hi>Body</hi> will give <hi>Law</hi> (as it were) to the Change of the <hi>Senſes,</hi> and <hi>Bodily Appetites</hi> that ſhall be continued unto it.</p>
            <p n="16">16. But 'tis the <hi>Soul,</hi> that will receive the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Advantage, and Happineſs, by the Injoyment and Poſſeſſion of this <hi>Houſe of God:</hi> Thereby it will learn much of the <hi>Divine Excellencies</hi> and <hi>Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> much of his <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> much of his <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs;</hi> much of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfathomable Riches</hi> of his <hi>Grace.</hi> And 'tis therein, that the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Man</hi> doth conſiſt; that I conceive, is the <hi>Viſion of God,</hi> in which almoſt all <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> do place the <hi>Supreme</hi> Felicity and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Yet either <hi>Voluntarily,</hi> or by <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> the Bleſſed Inhabitants of <hi>Heaven</hi> may leave thoſe Happy Manſions, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and view the <hi>Whole</hi> Creation of <hi>God</hi> Here we may obſerve Men travelling from <hi>One</hi> Kingdom to <hi>Another,</hi> to obſerve the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62928:19"/>
               <hi>Manners,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> the <hi>Laws, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> by which they are Governed, and under which they Live; as alſo, to take Knowledge of whatſoever is <hi>Rare</hi> and <hi>Peculiar, Stupendious</hi> and <hi>Worthy</hi> of Obſervation. And I do not know, but the Bleſſed may paſs from <hi>One Part</hi> of the World to <hi>Another,</hi> and behold what-ever is <hi>Curious</hi> and <hi>Admirable</hi> in them: And what <hi>Wonders</hi> of Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs may be found in every of them, who can imagine? And how much of the <hi>Glory</hi> of the Divine Attributes may be <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated</hi> by them, who can determine?</p>
            <p n="18">18. The <hi>Scriptures</hi> do aſſure us, That the <hi>Holy Angels</hi> do ſometimes converſe, and are imployed here <hi>Below.</hi> 'Though <hi>Heaven</hi> be their <hi>Home</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and they be therefore called the <hi>Angels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> yet ſometimes they ſpend a little time on Earth; and many things do they obſerve and learn <hi>Here.</hi> What they know of the <hi>Redemption</hi> of the World by a <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> and of the Warfare that is betwixt the <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> and the <hi>Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> they know by the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Revelations</hi> that are made unto it; together with the Experience that they have of the Conduct and Succeſs thereof. And if the <hi>Holy Angels of Heaven</hi> learn many things
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62928:20"/>from <hi>This Earth,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may learn ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things from <hi>This</hi> and <hi>Other Worlds,</hi> and Parts of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. For ſomething may be known of <hi>God,</hi> which the <hi>Heaven of Heavens</hi> doth not reveal or diſcover; though they be a moſt <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Glaſs, in which the Face of <hi>God</hi> may be ſeen; yet I am not ſure, that they do reveal all that the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of <hi>Knowing</hi> concerning him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may learn in <hi>Other Parts</hi> of the Univerſe, which they cannot learn in the <hi>Paradiſe of God:</hi> Not that <hi>God</hi> could not make it known unto them <hi>There;</hi> but he chuſes <hi>Several</hi> Creatures, and <hi>Several</hi> Parts of the <hi>Creation;</hi> upon which to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Footſteps</hi> of his Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by them to propoſe them to the <hi>View</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Rational</hi> Beings; for 'tis they alone, that are capable of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beholding them.</p>
            <p n="20">20. All <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Works</hi> do manifeſt, and ſhew forth his <hi>Glorious Attributes</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: The Firmament ſheweth his handy Work:</hi> The Sun, Moon, and Stars, in their <hi>Eſſence, Regular Motions, Influences,</hi> and <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi> do declare his <hi>Infinite</hi> Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Goodneſs. There is not a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in the Heavens, or in the Earth, which doth not teach and reveal ſomething of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62928:20"/>
               <hi>Admirable</hi> Excellency of their Maker. And if <hi>This World,</hi> and all the <hi>Beings</hi> in it, do ſpeak forth the Glory and Perfections of the <hi>Great God,</hi> it cannot be doubted, but that whatever <hi>Other Worlds</hi> there be, have been, or may be, will ſpeak the <hi>Same</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. <hi>God</hi> makes all things for <hi>Himſelf;</hi> that is, for the Diſcovery of <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and Illuſtration of his <hi>Boundleſs Perfections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>God</hi> knows his <hi>Own Excellencies,</hi> and needs no <hi>Effects</hi> for the Diſcovery of them: He needs not <hi>This,</hi> or any <hi>Other World,</hi> to acquaint himſelf with the <hi>Extent</hi> of his Power, his Wiſdom, or his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Theſe, and all his other Attributes, are <hi>Perfectly</hi> underſtood by him. He <hi>Doth not,</hi> nor <hi>Cannot</hi> learn any thing concerning them, from the <hi>Works</hi> of his Hands. His <hi>Creatures</hi> do not teach him <hi>Knowledge,</hi> nor doth he gain any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> by the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his <hi>Creative</hi> Power and Virtue.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Therefore <hi>Reaſonable Creatures</hi> muſt contemplate, and behold them; or 'twill be <hi>Very hard,</hi> in my Apprehenſion, to give any fair <hi>Account</hi> of them. Of what Uſe were the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>Sea,</hi> and the <hi>Dry Ground,</hi> with thoſe various, and almoſt innumerable ſorts and kinds of Beings, that are in it, if there were no <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent</hi> Beings, to <hi>Behold, View,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62928:21"/>them? Why were they Made? and why did <hi>God</hi> engrave his <hi>Own</hi> Image, and impreſs the Characters of his <hi>Own</hi> Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on them, if there were no <hi>Intellectual</hi> Eſſences to obſerve them? And if this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick that our <hi>Eyes</hi> behold, were made to be a <hi>Glaſs,</hi> in which Men and <hi>Angels</hi> might ſee, and contemplate the Glory of its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; ſuch will be the Uſe of all <hi>Other Worlds,</hi> that have been, are, or may be: They will be alſo <hi>Mirrors,</hi> in which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and intelligent Beings will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and among them the <hi>Bleſſed-Inhabitants</hi> of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="23">23. 'Tis true, in the <hi>Preſent State,</hi> and by reaſon of the Darkneſs and Impotence that Sin hath introduced upon the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, this <hi>World</hi> is in great degree uſeleſs, with regard to the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Main</hi> end of it: 'Twas Built, Framed, and Faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to <hi>Reveal God</hi> unto them; and it bears very <hi>Apparent</hi> Characters of a <hi>Deity</hi> upon it. But Man is <hi>Blind,</hi> and cannot <hi>See</hi> them; or <hi>Lazy</hi> and <hi>Negligent,</hi> and will not obſerve them; or ingaged in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of <hi>Pleaſures, Profits,</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> and cannot attend to conſider them. But, in my Opinion, this only proves, That there are other <hi>Intellectual Beings,</hi> that do contemplate <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Several</hi> Creatures,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62928:21"/>and Sorts of Eſſences, that are here below: And that though the World were made chiefly to reveal <hi>God</hi> to Man, yet that was not the <hi>Only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it; but that <hi>Angels</hi> might therein ſee and behold the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And if <hi>This World</hi> were made partly for the Uſe and Contemplation of <hi>Angels;</hi> 'tis not improbable, but that <hi>This,</hi> and <hi>Other Worlds,</hi> may be alſo made, partly for the Uſe and Contemplation of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> and <hi>Glorified</hi> Saints of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Yet I muſt add, That <hi>This World</hi> is of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> to Mankind. Some among them do <hi>See</hi> and <hi>Diſcern</hi> a <hi>God</hi> If <hi>Infinite</hi> Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Perfection therein; and <hi>More might do ſo,</hi> if they would apply themſelves to Conſider it. Thought <hi>Sin</hi> hath darkned the <hi>Eye</hi> of the <hi>Mind,</hi> it hath not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterly</hi> extinguiſhed, and put it out. Something it may ſtill <hi>See</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in the Creation, if it would put it ſelf on the <hi>Meditation</hi> of them. But if it were granted, That <hi>Mankind</hi> were utterly diſabled from <hi>Seeing</hi> or <hi>Learning</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of <hi>God,</hi> from the <hi>Things</hi> that are ſeen; yet it would not follow, that it were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſs</hi> to him. Things may be in their own Nature <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful,</hi> to certain Ends and Purpoſes; though Men may have <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily</hi> made themſelves incapable of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> them. Wholſom Meat and Drink may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62928:22"/>be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful</hi> for the nouriſhing of Humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; though <hi>Some</hi> Perſons may have ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured their <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and deſtroyed their <hi>Stomachs</hi> and <hi>Digeſtive</hi> Faculties by Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, that they are uncapable of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it. And 'tis certain, that the <hi>World</hi> were of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> to teach Men <hi>God,</hi> though Man were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterly</hi> diſabled ſo to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Imploy</hi> it.</p>
            <p n="25">25. The Sum of what I have ſaid in this <hi>Chapter,</hi> is this: The <hi>World</hi> in which we Live, and do Behold, is of very <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> Extent; the <hi>Species,</hi> and <hi>Kinds</hi> of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> in it, are <hi>Very greatly Numerous.</hi> There may have been <hi>Other Worlds</hi> Pre-exiſtent to <hi>This;</hi> there may be <hi>Others</hi> Co-exiſtent with it, and <hi>Others</hi> may Succeed it, to an <hi>Indefinite</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited</hi> Period. All <hi>God</hi>'s Works <hi>Shew</hi> forth his <hi>Glory;</hi> they are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> to their main End and Intention, if there be no <hi>Intelligent Natures</hi> to Behold and Conſider them. <hi>Angels</hi> do Behold and Conſider the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>This Subluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry World:</hi> And 'tis not improbable, in my Judgment, that the <hi>Glorious Saints</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> may ſee and behold the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Works</hi> that he hath made and done in <hi>This,</hi> and many <hi>Other Worlds:</hi> And ſo <hi>Great,</hi> and almoſt <hi>Infinitely</hi> various may they be, as to miniſter <hi>Eternal</hi> Matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62928:22"/>and an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of Knowledge for evermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Several Ways and Means of obtaining <hi>Knowledge;</hi> and, firſt, of <hi>Knowledge</hi> by <hi>Intui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THe <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Means</hi> of Obtaining and Increaſing <hi>Knowledge,</hi> are <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious:</hi> I ſhall reduce them to theſe Heads; 1. <hi>Intuition.</hi> 2. <hi>Hiſtorical Narration.</hi> 3. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſcurſive Argumentation.</hi> That I be not miſunderſtood, I ſhall here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, That I do not <hi>Poſitively</hi> affirm, that the Knowledge of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will increaſe by all <hi>Theſe</hi> Ways in the <hi>World to come,</hi> nor that there are no <hi>Other</hi> Ways of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Addition to it. All that I ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, is, That 'tis <hi>Poſſible,</hi> yea, and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,</hi> that it may be augmented by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Intuition,</hi> I mean a preſent <hi>Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Things; or a <hi>View</hi> of them, as they are preſented to us, and ſet before us. Knowledge of things by preſent <hi>Intui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62928:23"/>is diſtinguiſhed from that <hi>Knowledge</hi> of things that we have by conſidering the <hi>Signs, Images,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentations</hi> of them. The <hi>Knowledge</hi> that I have of <hi>Perſons, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Villages,</hi> and <hi>Countreys,</hi> by ocular and preſent Inſpection, differs from the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> that I have of them by viewing their <hi>Pictures</hi> and <hi>Statues,</hi> or inſpecting the <hi>Maps</hi> and <hi>Delineations</hi> of them. The <hi>Knowledge</hi> that we have of the Glory of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God,</hi> and the Perſon of our <hi>Saviour</hi> in it, differs much from that which the <hi>Bleſſed Saints and Angels</hi> have concerning them. Theirs is <hi>Preſent</hi> and <hi>Intuitive,</hi> Ours is <hi>Abſent</hi> and <hi>Abſtractive.</hi> We obtain it by conſidering the <hi>Reports</hi> that are made, and the <hi>Deſcriptions</hi> that are given of them in the <hi>Book of God:</hi> Whereas Theirs is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the <hi>Viſion, Preſence,</hi> and <hi>Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of thoſe things themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In this World, 'tis but very little that we know by <hi>Intuition;</hi> and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are, our Preſence is <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined:</hi> We are fixed to a <hi>Little</hi> Spot of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Creation;</hi> and can <hi>View,</hi> at once, but few of the <hi>Creatures</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And though by <hi>Local Motion,</hi> we are able to remove our ſelves from <hi>Place</hi> to <hi>Place,</hi> and view <hi>Many</hi> things <hi>Succeſſively,</hi> by preſent <hi>Intui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which <hi>at Once</hi> we cannot do; yet the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62928:23"/>Sphere of our <hi>Activity</hi> is ſmall; and 'tis with <hi>Difficulty</hi> and <hi>Slow Motions,</hi> that we do paſs through it. It takes up a <hi>Great</hi> deal of time, to inſpect the <hi>Beings</hi> that may be ſeen in a <hi>Circumference</hi> of a few Miles <hi>Diameter;</hi> and 'tis not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome <hi>Toyl</hi> and <hi>Labour:</hi> And much more muſt be imployed to view a <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> or <hi>Space,</hi> whoſe <hi>Diameter</hi> is <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Miles, and of <hi>Large</hi> Extenſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Two things will very much augment and increaſe the <hi>Intuitive Knowledge</hi> of the Bleſſed; and thoſe are the <hi>Extenſion</hi> of their Preſence, and a <hi>Facility</hi> of moving from Place to Place: Theſe, I do humbly, conceive, will be very <hi>Great</hi> Advantages unto them therein. Peradventure, their Preſence may be ſo <hi>Extenſive,</hi> that by Means thereof they may inſpect and behold more things at <hi>One View,</hi> than we can <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively,</hi> and one after another, in <hi>Many</hi> Years: And, it may be, their <hi>Motion</hi> may be almoſt as quick, as the <hi>Beams</hi> of Light; and they may paſs the <hi>Immenſe</hi> Spaces of the Univerſe, in the <hi>Twinkling</hi> of an Eye, or at leaſt with <hi>Incredible</hi> Swiftneſs, and in a <hi>Very Small</hi> Space of time. But theſe things muſt be ſpoken to ſomething <hi>More</hi> at large, and ſomething <hi>More</hi> particularly, that they may appear a <hi>Little</hi> Probable, if not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubtedly</hi> Certain.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:62928:24"/>
            <p n="5">5. Tho' the <hi>Preſence</hi> of the Bleſſed in the <hi>Future World,</hi> will be certainly <hi>Definite</hi> and <hi>Limited;</hi> for their Advancement to <hi>Bliſs</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> will not make them ſo <hi>Many</hi> Gods; their proper Natures will ſtill remain: They will be Men in <hi>Heaven,</hi> as truly as they were on <hi>Earth.</hi> But tho' they continue Men, yet I do (with Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) conceive, that their <hi>Preſence</hi> will be much more <hi>Extenſive,</hi> and <hi>Large,</hi> than now it is: And in all likelihood, the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion</hi> of their Preſence may be <hi>Varied</hi> There, according to the <hi>Variety</hi> of their <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Virtues,</hi> their Faith and their Obedience, Here.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> remains a <hi>True</hi> Man in his <hi>Glorified Eſtate;</hi> and yet, certainly, his <hi>Preſence</hi> is much <hi>More</hi> Extenſive, than when he dwelt upon <hi>Earth:</hi> When he was upon <hi>Earth,</hi> 'twas as much <hi>Limited,</hi> and <hi>Confined,</hi> as that of Other Men: But it ſeems to me utterly <hi>Improbable,</hi> that it ſhould continue or remain ſo, now he is in <hi>Heaven.</hi> Then he was able to inſpect, and view by <hi>Intuition,</hi> no more than others that were of <hi>Humane Race;</hi> for <hi>He was in all things made like unto them, Sin only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted:</hi> But now, perhaps, he may as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſpect the <hi>Whole Globe</hi> of this Earth, and the <hi>Heavens</hi> that <hi>Encompaſs</hi> and <hi>Surround</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62928:24"/>it, as any of us can view a <hi>Globe</hi> or <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference</hi> of an Inch <hi>Diameter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. For he is the <hi>Soveraign</hi> of Mankind: He is the <hi>Prince of the Kings of the Earth:</hi> He is the Governour of the World: The <hi>Laws</hi> by which they ought to <hi>Live,</hi> and by which they muſt be <hi>Judged,</hi> are his <hi>Laws.</hi> Sentence will paſs upon all Men, at the <hi>Great Day</hi> of <hi>Accounts,</hi> according to their <hi>Obedience</hi> or <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Beſides, He is our <hi>Great Interceſſor</hi> with <hi>God</hi> Almighty: But how can he <hi>Hear our Prayers,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand our Needs</hi> and <hi>Wants,</hi> unleſs he be <hi>Preſent</hi> with us, and do <hi>Inſpect</hi> and <hi>Obſerve</hi> them? Can he <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede</hi> for what he <hi>Knows</hi> not? Or can he <hi>Know</hi> what he doth not <hi>Hear?</hi> Or can he <hi>Hear</hi> where he is not <hi>Preſent?</hi> Or can he be <hi>Preſent</hi> with all thoſe that call upon him, unleſs his <hi>Preſence</hi> be of <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> Nature? Is not his <hi>Name</hi> called upon, from the <hi>Riſing of the Sun, to the Going down of the ſame?</hi> And can all thoſe Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers come before him, unleſs his <hi>Preſence</hi> be very <hi>Diffuſive,</hi> and extended with the <hi>Fabrick</hi> of Earth and Heaven?</p>
            <p n="9">9. In the mean time, I am not about to affirm the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Bodily Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nor to determine the <hi>Manner</hi> of it. I ſuppoſe his <hi>Preſence</hi> of no greater <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62928:25"/>than his Government; and his <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> no larger than the Extent of his <hi>Redemption;</hi> and what elſe may be <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> for the Protection and Preſervation of his <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>People.</hi> And as to what concerns the <hi>Manner</hi> of his Preſence, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine nothing: 'Tis but little that we know of the <hi>Nature</hi> of our <hi>Own Souls,</hi> whil'ſt they are in the <hi>Body;</hi> and therefore, can pretend to know little of the <hi>Soul</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſince it is cloathed with a <hi>Glorious Body</hi> What is the <hi>Nature</hi> of that Body, and what are its <hi>Extenſions,</hi> how the Soul is <hi>Joyned</hi> to it, and doth <hi>Actuate</hi> and <hi>Enliven</hi> it, and by what <hi>Tubes</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> it doth <hi>View</hi> and take <hi>Cognizance</hi> of the <hi>Affairs</hi> of Men, I cannot tell, but that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> even in his <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> hath ſome <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them, I think can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be doubted.</p>
            <p n="10">10. To ſay of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do of the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> to whom they addreſs their <hi>Prayers,</hi> gives me no Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: They tell us, That <hi>God Hears</hi> the <hi>Prayers</hi> that they preſent unto them, and acquaints them with them, that they may <hi>Again Offer</hi> and <hi>Preſent</hi> them to him. This, and ſome other <hi>Improbable</hi> Accounts do they give of their <hi>Praying to Saints and Angels,</hi> when <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do tell them, That they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62928:25"/>cannot poſſibly take <hi>Cognizance</hi> of them, by reaſon that their Preſence is of <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Determinate</hi> Nature.</p>
            <p n="11">11. For what is the Advantage of the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> above <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> if he Poſſeſs and enjoy no <hi>Greater Perfections,</hi> than they do? It cannot be doubted, but that <hi>They</hi> may underſtand the <hi>Needs</hi> and <hi>Wants</hi> of Men, if <hi>God</hi> will <hi>Reveal</hi> them unto them: And if <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> come no otherwiſe by the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them, what is his <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency,</hi> and what are his <hi>Advantages</hi> (at leaſt, in that <hi>Kind</hi>) greater than Theirs? And how hath he a <hi>Name above every Name,</hi> not only in <hi>This World,</hi> but alſo in <hi>That</hi> which is <hi>To come?</hi> And how hath <hi>He in all things the Preheminence?</hi> Surely, theſe <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> do import <hi>Some</hi> Excellencies and Advantages <hi>Peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Human Nature</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> which <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> are uncapable of.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Moreover, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the Head of his <hi>Church,</hi> even in his <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> and from Him the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, by the Means of his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> to all the Members of it: But how can this be, without Knowledge? Or how can he know the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of it to the <hi>Several</hi> and <hi>Single</hi> Members of <hi>His Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62928:26"/>without Largeneſs of Preſence? The Reaſon of the <hi>Divine</hi> Omniſcience, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from his <hi>Omnipreſence. God</hi> knows all things, becauſe he is Preſent <hi>Every Where:</hi> And I do humbly think, that the <hi>Extenſiveneſs</hi> of our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Knowledge, bears proportion with the <hi>Extent</hi> of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p n="13">13. In brief, <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> conſidered as <hi>Man,</hi> and as <hi>Mediator,</hi> is the great and general <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> of all the Affairs of this Humane World. Whatſoever is done in it, he does it; for all Power in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> is given to him: and <hi>God</hi> hath given him Power <hi>Over all Fleſh;</hi> all things are made <hi>Subject to Him;</hi> and he is the <hi>Head over all things to the Church.</hi> Theſe things, with many more of like importance, the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> do aſſert concerning Him: But how the Power thus given to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> can be exerciſed without <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the Affairs of the World, and of the Church, (I mean, an <hi>Intuitive Knowledge</hi> of them) nor how he can have any <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of them, without great <hi>Extenſion</hi> of Preſence, is beyond all Imagination, or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Conception.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Great is the <hi>Myſtery of Godlineſs;</hi> and certainly, even the Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> is a far more Glorious Perſon, than the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62928:26"/>moſt of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yea, or of <hi>Chriſtian Divines,</hi> do conceive or apprehend. He is called the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>Light;</hi> snd doth <hi>Enlighten</hi> all the Intellectual World. He is the <hi>Expreſs Image of his Father's Perſon:</hi> That is, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the moſt Lively <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> of the <hi>Deity,</hi> that is among Created Beings. He is <hi>Sat down on the Right Hand of the Majeſty on High:</hi> That is, He is next the <hi>Pure Godhead,</hi> the moſt <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eſſence</hi> in the World. His Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodneſs, Preſence, and other Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, are far <hi>Superiour</hi> to thoſe of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures; and they approach ſo near thoſe of <hi>God</hi> himſelf, as to be an <hi>Apt</hi> and <hi>Fair Reſemblance</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Let no Man miſunderſtand me in what I have ſaid concerning the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> I do not aſſert the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity</hi> of it; nor do I deny his <hi>Divine;</hi> or the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> thereof to the <hi>Humane.</hi> I <hi>Extend</hi> the Preſence of his <hi>Humane Nature</hi> no farther, than the Nature of his <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Office</hi> doth require it. He is the Great Prophet, Prieſt, and King of <hi>Humane Race:</hi> And as far as the Exerciſe of theſe ſeveral Offices do require his Preſence, ſo far I <hi>Extend</hi> it, and no farther: Though I will not determine, that theſe are the <hi>Bounds</hi> or
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62928:27"/>
               <hi>Limits</hi> of it. And touching the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mon of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Word</hi> with the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it the <hi>Great Eſſential,</hi> as well as the <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> and do very heartily believe it.</p>
            <p n="16">16. If any Man ſhall doubt the Truth of what I have ſaid, concerning the <hi>Preſence</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> becauſe he is not able to comprehend or imagine the Manner of it: I anſwer; The <hi>Exiſtence</hi> of Multitudes of things, is <hi>Certain;</hi> though the manner thereof may be <hi>Incomprehenſible:</hi> The <hi>Exiſtence</hi> of the <hi>Humane Soul</hi> in the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> is <hi>Certain,</hi> and that it gives Life and Motion to it; but how 'tis <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited,</hi> and by what <hi>Ties</hi> and <hi>Ligaments</hi> 'tis faſtened there, and how it gives <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> to it, no Man can tell. That <hi>Children</hi> are Formed in their <hi>Mother</hi>'s <hi>Wombs,</hi> and that <hi>Birds</hi> and <hi>Fouls</hi> are Formed of <hi>Eggs,</hi> is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;</hi> but how theſe things are done, no Man is able to inform us.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Beſides, we are ignorant of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of <hi>Humane Minds,</hi> and what <hi>Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> they are capable of being advanced unto, aſter they are freed from their <hi>Groſs</hi> and <hi>Heavy Bodies:</hi> And we know as little of the Nature of thoſe <hi>Spiritual Bodies,</hi> where-withal we ſhall be inveſted at the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62928:27"/>
               <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and which <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is already cloathed withal in the <hi>Heavens.</hi> Peradventure, the Soul of our <hi>Saviour</hi> may be ſo far advanced and perfected, as to be able to actuate a <hi>Spiritual Body</hi> of very vaſt <hi>Dimenſions:</hi> And this Body may penetrate all Groſs and Material Bodies, even as <hi>Light</hi> doth the <hi>Pureſt Chriſtal.</hi> So that, to deny the Preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> becauſe we cannot comprehend the manner of it, (eſpecially ſince we know ſo little of the Capacity of a <hi>Humane Mind,</hi> and ſuch was that of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi>) or of the Nature of that <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Glorious Body,</hi> which is the Tabernacle and Habitation of it) is I think, Unreaſonable.</p>
            <p n="18">18. But, after all that I have ſaid on this Subject, I ſhall add thus much. I do not confidently affirm it; I only propoſe it to the Conſideration of <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprejudiced Minds;</hi> and leave them fully the Liberty to Embrace or Reject it, as they ſee ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe: Only I would deſire them well to conſider, how many and great things the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks of the Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> In Him <hi>Dwells al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Fulneſs of the Godbead:</hi> He is filled with the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> that he may be a Head of <hi>Vital Influence</hi> to all his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. He is the Univerſal <hi>Law-giver,</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> of all Men; and will be the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62928:28"/>
               <hi>Judge</hi> of all the World: Which doth imply great Largeneſs of <hi>Knowledge, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> and by conſequence, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Extenſive Preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. But what means all this long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe? Why this? If <hi>Extenſion</hi> of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> be Reconcileable, and Conſiſtent with the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> in his Glorified Eſtate; it may be Reconcileable with it in the Bleſſed. If he be a <hi>True Man,</hi> notwithſtanding, his Preſence is <hi>Extended</hi> to very vaſt Diſtances: The <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may be ſo, though their <hi>Preſence</hi> be <hi>Extended</hi> in ſome <hi>Good</hi> Degree and Meaſure. And if the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> in the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> be capable of theſe <hi>Extenſions,</hi> and this <hi>Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> the ſame <hi>Nature</hi> is capable of it in the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in their <hi>Degree</hi> and <hi>Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. And this <hi>Extenſion</hi> of <hi>Preſence</hi> will very much increaſe their <hi>Intuitive Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> they will be able to ſee and obſerve, <hi>at one View,</hi> much of the Works of <hi>God,</hi> and many of the Productions of his <hi>Infinite Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> By it they will be able to obſerve the <hi>Connexion</hi> and <hi>Dependance</hi> of things on each other; and conſequently, the <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Harmony</hi> of them, which will very much <hi>Affect</hi> &amp; <hi>Delight</hi> them. He that beholds one Piece, or Part
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62928:28"/>of a <hi>Curious Picture</hi> or <hi>Statue,</hi> is not <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> or <hi>Delighted</hi> by it; but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds it altogether, and obſerves the <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Symmetry</hi> of its Parts to, and with each other, is even tranſported with the <hi>Admiration</hi> of it. He that <hi>Views</hi> only one Part of a <hi>Landskip,</hi> finds peradventure but little <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in the Proſpect of it; but he that <hi>Sees</hi> it altogether, and in its whole Extent and Dimenſions, finds a <hi>Marvellous Complaiſance</hi> therein.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Though this <hi>Extenſion</hi> of Preſence in the <hi>Future State</hi> ſhould be doubted, and conſequently, the Increaſe of <hi>Intuitive Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> thereby; yet it may be very much increaſed, by Facility of <hi>Motion,</hi> from Place to Place; which almoſt all <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do acknowledge a Power of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty <hi>Inherent</hi> in the Bleſſed. All confeſs a Power of removing themſelves from one determinate Spot of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with <hi>Incredible</hi> Swiftneſs. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Properties of the <hi>Glorious Bodies,</hi> where-with they will be inveſted at the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> they reckon <hi>Quickneſs</hi> and <hi>Agility</hi> for Motion and Action. And ſurely, <hi>Spiritual Bodies</hi> are, in their own Nature, more <hi>Agile,</hi> and <hi>Fit</hi> for Motion, than theſe <hi>Groſs</hi> and <hi>Earthly Bodies,</hi> that we now bear about with us.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:62928:29"/>
            <p n="22">22. The Bleſſed being thus <hi>Agile,</hi> and <hi>Fit</hi> for Motion, they may as eaſily paſs from <hi>World</hi> to <hi>World,</hi> or from One part of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> to Another; as we do from <hi>Village</hi> to <hi>Village</hi> in the Country, or from <hi>Street</hi> to <hi>Street</hi> in a vaſt and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous City. Some <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Planetary Bodies,</hi> to be ſo many <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable Worlds;</hi> and the Learned <hi>Hevelius</hi> hath lately given us a Map of the <hi>Moon,</hi> in which he hath deſcribed and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſeveral <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>Countreys</hi> in it.</p>
            <p n="23">23. And if the <hi>Moon</hi> be an <hi>Habitable World,</hi> (as it is not altogether Improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) I ſee no reaſon, why we may not think the ſame of all the other <hi>Luminous Bodies,</hi> that are placed in the Expanded <hi>Heavens:</hi> If that <hi>Planet</hi> be a World much like our <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> may be a <hi>World</hi> ſomething advanced above it, in <hi>Luſtre,</hi> and in <hi>Glory:</hi> And the Inhabitants thereof may be <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious</hi> in proportion to their Countrey, and excel Us who live upon <hi>This Earth,</hi> as much as the <hi>Luſtre</hi> and <hi>Brightneſs</hi> of the One, ſurmounts the <hi>Shadows</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> of the Other.</p>
            <p n="24">24. And the Bleſſed being of a <hi>Very A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Nature,</hi> and capable of moving with <hi>Velocity</hi> and <hi>Swiftneſs,</hi> may ſtep from <hi>Star</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62928:29"/>to <hi>Star,</hi> and Intuitively obſerve what-ever is <hi>Wonderful,</hi> and <hi>Worthy</hi> of Obſervation there. They may obſerve what-ever in them is fit to Exalt the <hi>Honour,</hi> and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the <hi>Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ens</hi> of their Great <hi>Creatour:</hi> And it needs not to be doubted, but they will find <hi>Sufficient</hi> Reaſons and Occaſions for it. There is ſomething <hi>Great</hi> in all the Works of <hi>God</hi> upon the <hi>Surface</hi> of this <hi>Earth,</hi> and in the <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>Rivers,</hi> that run within the Banks and Shores thereof. And ſurely, the more <hi>Illuſtrious Worlds,</hi> and Parts of the <hi>Creation,</hi> will produce things vaſtly Greater than any that are found Here below, and more <hi>Worthy</hi> of Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="25">25. But no Part of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> will produce things ſo Great, as will the <hi>Court of Heaven:</hi> There ſhall we ſee and behold the <hi>Braveſt,</hi> the moſt <hi>Stately,</hi> and moſt <hi>Magnificent</hi> Effects of the <hi>Divine</hi> Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs. And how Great is the Extent of that <hi>Glorious</hi> Palace, and what great Variety of Beings may be found There, who can determine? If the <hi>Earth,</hi> compared with the <hi>Heavens,</hi> be but a <hi>Point;</hi> the <hi>Heavens,</hi> compared with the <hi>Heaven of Heavens,</hi> may be much more ſo; the Extent thereof, may be almoſt <hi>Infinite.</hi> And though there ſhould be no <hi>Other Worlds,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62928:30"/>either Paſt, Preſent, or to Come; yet even <hi>That</hi> alone might employ <hi>Eternal</hi> Ages, to view and behold the <hi>Wonders,</hi> and the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="26">26. There may be various Kinds of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> and <hi>Intellectual</hi> Eſſences or Beings. There may be <hi>Pure Minds,</hi> and ſuch as are utterly <hi>Immaterial;</hi> and there may be <hi>Several Gradual</hi> Differences amongſt them. There may be <hi>Angels Incorporate,</hi> and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with <hi>Material</hi> Organs; much of the ſame Nature with thoſe, where-with the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will be endued at the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> And among theſe, there may be very many <hi>Gradations,</hi> and Modal Differences and Diſtinctions; and among the <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Gradual</hi> Differences may be very great and many; and ſo may be the Reaſons of them. And all theſe will lie open to our View and Meditation.</p>
            <p n="27">27. What <hi>Kinds</hi> of Beings may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned and prepared for the Ornament of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> that <hi>City</hi> of the <hi>Living God,</hi> I cannot ſay or determine: But for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as there are many things Here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which (beſides the Illuſtration of the <hi>Divine</hi> Perfections) ſeem to be of little or no uſe, unleſs it be to <hi>Embelliſh</hi> and <hi>Adorn</hi> the World, and render it <hi>Pleaſant</hi> to our View; ſo 'tis probable, that in the <hi>Houſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62928:30"/>and Kingdom of God,</hi> many things may be placed There, to make it <hi>Beautiful</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant</hi> to thoſe that ſhall be thought <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> of Admiſſion Thither. And theſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings may be of <hi>Several</hi> Kinds and Natures, and may miniſter Matter to our <hi>Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as well as Pleaſure to the <hi>Bodily Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> where-withall we ſhall be endued There.</p>
            <p n="28">28. But the moſt <hi>Amazing</hi> Wonder, that will be propoſed to the <hi>Intuition</hi> and <hi>Contemplation</hi> of the Bleſſed, will be our <hi>Lord Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> He that was ſometimes the moſt <hi>Deſpiſed</hi> of Mortal Men, is There the <hi>Prince of the Kings of the Earth:</hi> He that was the <hi>Contempt</hi> of Men, is the <hi>Object</hi> even of <hi>Angel</hi>'s <hi>Admiration:</hi> He that ſometimes ſtood before the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate,</hi> is already <hi>Appointed</hi> Judge of the <hi>Living,</hi> and the <hi>Dead;</hi> and all muſt come before his <hi>Judgment-Seat,</hi> and receive their Sentence from Him. And how great the <hi>Excellencies</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of this <hi>Jeſus</hi> are, who will undertake to Characterize or Deſcribe?</p>
            <p n="29">29. A <hi>God</hi> indeed, in the <hi>Humane</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, He cannot be; but certainly, He is, and will remain, the moſt <hi>Glorious and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent Image</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Whole</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He had never been <hi>Exalted</hi> far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62928:31"/>all <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers; Angels</hi> and <hi>Authorities</hi> had never been made Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Him, if He had not greatly ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them in his <hi>Perſonal</hi> and Eſſential Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and <hi>Advantages.</hi> His Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Goodneſs, his Preſence, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, his Government, and Empire, is much more <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Perfect,</hi> than that of any other <hi>Created</hi> Eſſence: And therefore, He hath obtained a more <hi>Excellent Name, than any of them;</hi> and is advanced, and ſet before them</p>
            <p n="30">30. Of this <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Bleſſed will have a preſent <hi>Intuition;</hi> not only in his <hi>Perſonal,</hi> but <hi>Politick</hi> Capacity: They will behold him as Head of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> the Captain-General of all the <hi>Hoſts</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> the moſt <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Being that preſides over them; and under the <hi>Pure Deity,</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects and Governs them, and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates <hi>Vital</hi> Influences unto them: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth aſſure us, That (the Work of <hi>Man</hi>'s <hi>Reſtauration</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> beign accompliſhed) He ſhall <hi>Give up the Kingdom to</hi> God <hi>the Father,</hi> yet I do conceive, that He will always retain the Honour and Title of the <hi>Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of Men;</hi> and that as the <hi>Sun</hi> doth <hi>Illuſtrate</hi> this <hi>Inferiour World,</hi> ſo that <hi>Son of Righteouſneſs</hi> will <hi>Illuſtrate</hi> the <hi>Supreme</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62928:31"/>and <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem; The Lamb is the Light of it:</hi> And the Bleſſed ſhall <hi>Eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Behold and Dwell in his <hi>Light,</hi> to their incredible <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> But of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncreaſe of <hi>Knowledge</hi> by <hi>Intuition,</hi> I have ſaid enough; and therefore, here I'le put a Period to <hi>This Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62928:32"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Increaſe of <hi>Knowledge</hi> by <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. WHen <hi>God</hi> made Man, he endued him with <hi>Reaſonable Faculties,</hi> and made him capable of <hi>Moral</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: He was able to underſtand his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and by the Proſpect of <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments,</hi> he could chuſe the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,</hi> and refuſe the <hi>Neglect</hi> and <hi>Contempt</hi> thereof. He was able to <hi>See</hi> and <hi>Diſcern</hi> the Meaning and Importance of the <hi>Divine Commandments;</hi> and he could, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of its <hi>Advantages,</hi> chuſe <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> and on the Previſion of its <hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> refuſe <hi>Diſobedience</hi> and <hi>Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Laws,</hi> by which <hi>God</hi> intended to Govern <hi>Mankind,</hi> were written in the <hi>Nature</hi> of Things; and from thence they were to derive the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them. The ſeveral <hi>Beings</hi> in the World, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with <hi>Relation</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and one <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> are the Signs of the <hi>Divine</hi> Will; and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62928:32"/>Divine <hi>Laws</hi> are nothing elſe, but the <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Will, concerning Man's <hi>Duty, Reward,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> and the <hi>Whole Creation</hi> (at leaſt, as far as Man is capable of obſerving it) are the <hi>Revealing Signs</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>God</hi> did not Reveal all his <hi>Will</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Man's Duty, (even whil'ſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent) in the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Things,</hi> but ſome Part of it: He made known even then, by <hi>Supernatural Revelation.</hi> Such was the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of Eating of the Fruit of the <hi>Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil:</hi> And ſuch (according to the Opinion of <hi>Some Divines</hi>) was the Precept of <hi>Sacrificing Beasts:</hi> For that Sacrifices of that Kind were offered to <hi>God,</hi> whil'ſt Man continued <hi>Incocent,</hi> they think probable; becauſe <hi>God</hi> cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Firſt Parents with <hi>Skins</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the <hi>Fall;</hi> which (they think) were the Skins of thoſe <hi>Beaſts</hi> that had been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> Of the Firſt of theſe Precepts, there is no doubt, but that it was made known by <hi>Supernatural Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation:</hi> But whether Beaſts were offered in Sacrifice before the <hi>Fall,</hi> ſeems very <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain,</hi> if not <hi>Improbable;</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether there were any Precept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, till afterwards. For the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>This Opinion,</hi> I conceive, is not Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62928:33"/>and other Accounts are given of the <hi>Skins,</hi> where-with our Firſt Parents were cloathed, by Learned <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Since the <hi>Fall</hi> of Man, 'tis <hi>Apparent,</hi> that much of <hi>God</hi>'s Will hath been made known to them by <hi>Revelation.</hi> This no Man doth, or can doubt, that Reads and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> That the <hi>Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpent's Head,</hi> was made known to <hi>Adam</hi> by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi> and, peradventure, ſome other things, not Recorded in the <hi>Book of God.</hi> That the World was to periſh by a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge,</hi> if they continued in their <hi>Impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> That <hi>God</hi> would no more Drown the World for its Wickedneſs, was <hi>Revealed</hi> to <hi>Noah</hi> after the ſame manner. Many things were ſo made known to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the other <hi>Patriarchs;</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> in ſucceeding Generations; and after them to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of <hi>Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Hiſtory of the <hi>Creation</hi> was known to <hi>Moſes,</hi> either by <hi>Immediate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> or by <hi>Tradition</hi> from thoſe that at firſt received it by <hi>Revelation:</hi> For though the <hi>Creation</hi> of the World might be Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and Gathered from the Things that do appear; yet the manner of it could not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62928:33"/>poſſibly be Collected thence. How could it be known, that <hi>God</hi> Created the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> and the <hi>Earth;</hi> and that the <hi>Earth</hi> was without <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Void;</hi> and that he ſaid, <hi>Let there be Light, and there was Light;</hi> and that he <hi>Divided the Light from the Darkneſs;</hi> and called the One <hi>Day,</hi> and the Other <hi>Night;</hi> and that <hi>The Evening, and the Morning were the Firſt Day?</hi> And ſo on, according to the Hiſtory and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that <hi>Moſes</hi> gives of it. This could not be known otherwiſe, than by <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> There is nothing in the <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>Fabrick</hi> of Heaven and Earth, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Creatures</hi> in them, that give us any notice of the <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of their Creation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To paſs by many other things; The <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> both <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> was Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by <hi>Immediate Revelation</hi> from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove: All their <hi>Laws</hi> were appointed by <hi>God</hi> himſelf: He was their <hi>Legiſlator.</hi> Their Government was a <hi>Theocracy. God</hi> was their Supreme Prince, and Ruled over them. Whatever he required of them as a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or a <hi>Church</hi> ſeparate from all the Nations upon Earth, to his peculiar <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> was made known to them by <hi>Inſpiration.</hi> Their <hi>Laws,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62928:34"/>and Methods of <hi>Government,</hi> were not the Products and Effects of <hi>Reaſon</hi> upon the Conſideration of the <hi>Nature of Things;</hi> but of <hi>Divine,</hi> and (in many things) of <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> Will, by Revelation.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church is alſo thus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed: The great Author and Founder of it came out of the <hi>Boſom of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and appointed the Laws by which 'tis <hi>Conſtituted, Ruled,</hi> and <hi>Governed.</hi> Tho' many of thoſe Laws be of <hi>Natural Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> yet even they were anew <hi>Revealed</hi> from Heaven; and other Laws, both for its Conſtitution and Adminiſtration, were purely of <hi>Supernatural</hi> Appointment and Inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The <hi>Angelical Hoſt</hi> know much of the Will, Nature, Attributes, and Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Supernatural</hi> Revelation. Thus they underſtand the Will of <hi>God,</hi> concerning Man's Salvation; thus they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come acquainted with the Grace, Mercy, Pity, and Compaſſion of <hi>God</hi> to wards <hi>Faln Man.</hi> All that they know of theſe things, is by the <hi>Revelations</hi> that <hi>God</hi> hath made to the <hi>Church,</hi> and World, concerning it. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereof was, or could be learned from the Book of <hi>Nature:</hi> All the Knowledge they have concerning it, is by <hi>Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Methods of Diſcovery.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:62928:34"/>
            <p n="9">9. That <hi>God</hi> was <hi>Placable,</hi> they might perhaps inferre from the Conſideration of his <hi>Nature,</hi> and his <hi>Works;</hi> but that he would be <hi>Reconciled</hi> unto them, they could not know, till he Himſelf had declared it by <hi>Revelation.</hi> The Will of <hi>God</hi> is ſecret; and no Man or <hi>Angel</hi> can know, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, till he hath by ſome <hi>Overt-Act</hi> diſcovered and revealed it. That <hi>God</hi> would be reconciled to Sinful, Lapſed, and Faln <hi>Man,</hi> was not diſcovered by <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Revelation:</hi> Therefore, all that <hi>Angels</hi> know about it, is from <hi>God,</hi> and that by <hi>Supernatural</hi> Manifeſtation.</p>
            <p n="10">10. If Man, whil'ſt Innocent, knew at leaſt ſome Part of <hi>God</hi>'s Will, by <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary Revelations;</hi> if after the Fall, <hi>God</hi> hath continued to make known his Will to the <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> after the ſame manner; yea, if the <hi>Angels</hi> know much by the ſame <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> and <hi>Means</hi> of Diſcovery; I ſee no reaſon, why it may not be at leaſt <hi>Probable,</hi> that the Bleſſed may Increaſe and Advance their <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the <hi>Future State,</hi> by the ſame <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Method.</hi> Though I doubt not, but that very much of the <hi>Nature, Will,</hi> and <hi>Attributes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> will be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and laid before their <hi>Eyes,</hi> in the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Works of his Hands; yet I am not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62928:35"/>ſure, that <hi>Supernatural Revelation</hi> will be of <hi>No <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> There. 'Tis not <hi>Improbable;</hi> but ſomething, that may and ſhall be known of <hi>God,</hi> may be <hi>Excepted</hi> from <hi>Natural,</hi> and <hi>Reſerved</hi> for <hi>Supernatural</hi> Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As the Hiſtory of <hi>This Worlds Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> was made known to Man by <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Revelation,</hi> as I have obſerved al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; ſo 'tis poſſible, the Hiſtory of the <hi>Generation</hi> of many <hi>Other Worlds</hi> may, by the ſame Means, be made known to the Bleſſed: For although it will be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obvious, by <hi>Natural</hi> Evidence and Light, that all <hi>Beings</hi> do proceed from the <hi>Firſt Being,</hi> and all <hi>Effects</hi> from the <hi>Firſt Cauſe;</hi> yet the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of their <hi>Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> is not obvious thereby. If it may be ſuppoſed, that there are <hi>Angels,</hi> or <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences,</hi> Younger than this World; I think it may be ſaid, That they could not know the <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi> of its <hi>Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> unleſs it be by <hi>Revelation,</hi> or the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſuch <hi>Intelligent Beings,</hi> as were Pre-exiſtent to it. There is no Evidence in the <hi>Nature</hi> of Things, that <hi>This World</hi> was made between <hi>Five</hi> and <hi>Six thouſand</hi> Years ago; nor that <hi>Light</hi> was one of the <hi>Firſt</hi> Things that was made; and other Things in that order, in which they are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62928:35"/>deſcribed in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. As many of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and much of the <hi>Policy</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church of God</hi> in <hi>This World,</hi> is known both to Men and <hi>Angels</hi> by <hi>Revelation;</hi> ſo 'tis not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but ſome part of the <hi>Laws, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> of <hi>Other Worlds,</hi> may be known to the Bleſſed after the <hi>Same</hi> manner. They may obtain the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of it, juſt as the <hi>Angels</hi> obtain the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of <hi>Our Laws</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: And 'tis affirmed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That 'tis by the <hi>Church</hi> that they attain it: That is, as I conceive, by the <hi>Revelations</hi> made to the <hi>Church,</hi> and by the Experience that they have of the <hi>Obedience</hi> that they pay unto them, and the <hi>Rewards</hi> that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent thereunto; together with the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments</hi> that attend the Neglect and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of them; in which, many times, they are the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and <hi>Executioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. And who knows, whether many of the Obſcure <hi>Prophecies</hi> in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> and ſome other Difficulties in the <hi>Inſpired Writings,</hi> may not be Explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Opened, and Unfolded, after the <hi>Same Manner</hi> that they were delivered to Men? They were ſpoken by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they were thereunto moved by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and perchance, the <hi>Same</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:62928:36"/>
               <hi>Spirit</hi> that was the <hi>Author</hi> of them, may be the <hi>Interpreter</hi> and <hi>Explainer</hi> of them: The ſame <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> that revealed the <hi>Matter</hi> of them to the <hi>Prophets,</hi> may open and unfold the <hi>Meaning</hi> of them to the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The Holy <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> obſerves ſome <hi>Analogies</hi> and <hi>Similitudes</hi> between the Firſt and Second <hi>Creation,</hi> as is apparent in his <hi>Second Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> As in the Old <hi>Creation, God</hi> commanded <hi>Light</hi> to ſhine out of <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> ſo in the New <hi>Creation,</hi> he cauſes <hi>Light</hi> to ariſe upon thoſe that ſit in <hi>Darkneſs, and in the Valley and Shadow of Death.</hi> As a <hi>Dark</hi> and <hi>Confuſed Chaos</hi> did precede <hi>Light,</hi> and a <hi>Well-ordered</hi> World, and State of things, in the <hi>Firſt Creation;</hi> ſo a State of <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> doth precede a State of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Knowledge, Rectitude</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> in the <hi>Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. The <hi>Analogies, Likeneſſes,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions,</hi> that are obſerved between theſe <hi>Two Creations,</hi> by the <hi>Sacred Writers,</hi> are but few: But 'tis not improbable, in my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, but that there may be <hi>Very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more,</hi> than thoſe obſerved by them; and perhaps, there may be almoſt nothing in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Firſt Creation</hi> of things, which hath not its <hi>Likeneſs, Shadow,</hi> and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62928:36"/>
               <hi>Reſemblance</hi> in the <hi>Second.</hi> And who dares to deny, that they may be diſcovered to the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> by Extraordinary <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. The Frame and Fabrick of the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> and the ſeveral Veſſels and Uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils thereof, had certainly their <hi>Meaning</hi> and <hi>Signification:</hi> The <hi>Epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> puts that paſt all doubt and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; yet, I think, that there is very little of the <hi>Import</hi> and <hi>Signification</hi> of them expounded unto us, and ſet before us in the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> What is meant by the <hi>Shew-Bread,</hi> and by the <hi>Candleſtick</hi> with its ſeveral <hi>Lamps,</hi> by the <hi>Cherubims</hi> covering the <hi>Mercy-Seat</hi> with their <hi>Wings;</hi> who is able to determine. Something the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> hath ſaid for the Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Some</hi> of them, and ſomething other <hi>Authors</hi> have ſaid to unriddle the <hi>Meaning</hi> of them: But beſides what the <hi>Scripture</hi> hath ſaid thereof, we have no ſecurity of its Truth. All Accounts of the <hi>Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of thoſe things, unleſs ſuch as we find in the <hi>Bible,</hi> are but <hi>Conjectures;</hi> and as they may be True, ſo they may be Falſe; for we have no <hi>Certain</hi> Aſſurance of their Verity: And 'tis not impoſſible, but that the <hi>Full</hi> and <hi>Certain</hi> Knowledge of them may be reſerved for <hi>Another World;</hi> and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62928:37"/>that the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may know them by <hi>Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> and <hi>Special</hi> Revelation.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Beſides what I have ſaid, there were many <hi>Typical Perſons, Things,</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> under the <hi>Old-Teſtament;</hi> and I do believe, that no <hi>Meer</hi> Man, either did, doth, or ſhall, in <hi>This World,</hi> underſtand them. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> was a <hi>Typical</hi> Perſon; and very many of thoſe Actions, which (as a <hi>Prieſt</hi>) he did perform, were alſo <hi>Typical:</hi> And ſo I think of many things, of which we read in the <hi>Old-Teſtament;</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, the <hi>Holy of Holies,</hi> and the <hi>Vail</hi> that ſeparated it from the <hi>Holy Place. David</hi> alſo, and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> were <hi>Typical</hi> Perſons; and ſomething of the <hi>Antitypes</hi> of them, the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> doth inform us of; but, I think, <hi>Very little,</hi> and that <hi>Darkly</hi> and <hi>Imperfectly</hi> too. And, perhaps, the full Knowledge of them may be kept in <hi>Reſerve</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> ſhall There know it by <hi>Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. To which I may add the Meaning and Importance of many of the <hi>Ceremonial Laws,</hi> of which we read in the Books of <hi>Moſes.</hi> What is the Meaning and Reaſon of their <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> is not eaſie to tell: It may be reaſonably ſuppoſed, that the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> for whom thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> were appointed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62928:37"/>the Meaning and Reaſons of them, better than we do at <hi>This Diſtance</hi> of <hi>Years;</hi> eſpecially if we <hi>Remember,</hi> and <hi>Conſider,</hi> that we are under no Obligation to <hi>Obſerve</hi> them. Yet I am much inclined to think, that even they themſelves never fully underſtood either the <hi>Meaning, Ends,</hi> or <hi>Reaſons</hi> of their Inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Who knows the Meaning or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their ſeveral <hi>Sorts</hi> and <hi>Kinds</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices;</hi> or can give us any Evidence, that the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves underſtood them? Why were ſome of them <hi>Wholly</hi> conſumed upon the Altar, others only <hi>in Part?</hi> Why was <hi>Some Part</hi> of ſome of them eaten by the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Others</hi> by the <hi>People</hi> themſelves that made the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and <hi>Oblation?</hi> There were many <hi>Particularities</hi> in the moſt of their <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> which can hardly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for; and I do much believe, that the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves never well underſtood them. And what I have ſaid of their <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,</hi> is applicable to <hi>Many</hi> other of their <hi>Laws.</hi> Some <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the Nature and Reaſon of them, was to be found among the more <hi>Enlightned</hi> of them; but a full and perfect <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they were <hi>Strangers</hi> to; and poſſibly, may be known by no Means, but that of <hi>Revelation;</hi> no in no Place, but in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62928:38"/>
               <hi>Future State;</hi> and by the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> There.</p>
            <p n="20">20. In moſt Ages, ſince the Creation of <hi>This</hi> World, <hi>God</hi> hath on <hi>Sundry</hi> Reaſons, and at <hi>Sundry</hi> Times, made known his Will and Purpoſe concerning <hi>Future</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents. Thus he made known to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Servitude and Bondage of his Poſterity, in a Strange Country, for the ſpace of <hi>Four Hundred Years,</hi> and their <hi>After</hi> Deliverance and Proſperity. Thus he made known to the <hi>Jews</hi> their Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>Seventy</hi> Years; and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and Reſtauration to their <hi>Own</hi> Country. And many other things, which thoſe that read the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> cannot be ignorant of.</p>
            <p n="21">21. It may reaſonably be conjectured, that the <hi>Bleſſed Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> had the Knowledge of all theſe <hi>Future</hi> Events, by the <hi>Revelations</hi> that <hi>God</hi> made concerning them: And I ſee no reaſon, why many things may not be known by the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in the <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem,</hi> after the <hi>Same Manner,</hi> and that in a Succeſſion of Times and Ages, <hi>Without End,</hi> or <hi>Period</hi> of Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="22">22. For whether there may not be a <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Worlds,</hi> to an <hi>Indefinite Period</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> &amp; whether <hi>God</hi> may not govern them <hi>Much after the Manner of This,</hi> partly by
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62928:38"/>
               <hi>Natural,</hi> and partly by <hi>Supernatural Laws,</hi> who can define? I know nothing in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, that forbids ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or Apprehenſions: Though it <hi>Teaches</hi> no ſuch Doctrine, (nor do I affirm it <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly</hi> True or Neceſſary) yet I find not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in the Contents thereof, which is <hi>Oppoſite</hi> unto it, or <hi>Inconſiſtent</hi> with it. I do not affirm, There ſhall be a <hi>Succeſſion of Worlds equally Wicked with This,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſuch as ſhall need a <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Redeemer:</hi> But what hinders, that there may not be a <hi>World,</hi> yea, <hi>Many Worlds,</hi> that may retain <hi>Their Primitive Integrity and State,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> may Govern them by <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Revealed Laws,</hi> (ſince <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> whil'ſt Innocent, was ſo Governed) and after ſuch a Part of Time, as ſhall ſeem good to the <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of his Will, remove the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> thereof, to <hi>Better</hi> and more <hi>Glorious Habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. Yea, let me add, That I am not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſure, that <hi>God</hi> Governs the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> in Heaven, by no other but <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Laws.</hi> The Service the they do to <hi>God</hi> Almighty, either in the Protecting of <hi>Kingdoms, Churches,</hi> and <hi>Particular Perſons,</hi> or in Puniſhing his <hi>Enemies,</hi> may (in my Apprehenſion) by performed in <hi>Obedience</hi> to ſome <hi>Poſitive</hi> and <hi>Particular Commands</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:62928:39"/>and <hi>Revelations.</hi> For although <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments</hi> be of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> yet the <hi>Time</hi> and of <hi>Meaſure</hi> them is not ſo. What <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> doth determine, when, and in what <hi>Degree</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> the Enemies of <hi>God,</hi> and of his <hi>People,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Puniſhed</hi> and <hi>Chaſtiſed?</hi> What <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> doth appoint, when <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> ſhall be protected, or delivered out of the Hands of their <hi>Oppreſſors,</hi> and ſuch as ſeek their Ruine? Theſe things ſeem to me to depend on the Wiſdom and Will of <hi>God;</hi> and that there is no Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of coming to the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them, but by <hi>Immediate Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. And if in <hi>Particular</hi> Inſtantaneous Caſes, they are Governed by <hi>Revealed Laws,</hi> what hinders, but that in ſome other Caſes they may be Governed by them, through the vaſt Durations of Eternity? Who knows, but that there may be ſome <hi>Poſitive Inſtitutions,</hi> by which they may worſhip <hi>God,</hi> and exalt his Praiſe? And who ean tell, how <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> may be the Number of them? Or whether ſome of them may not be <hi>Temporary,</hi> and <hi>Expire,</hi> and others <hi>Succeed</hi> them of new <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment</hi> and <hi>Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. If <hi>Innocent Adam</hi> were Governed by both Natural and Revealed <hi>Laws;</hi> if
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62928:39"/>it be not altogether improbable, that the Bleſſed <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> are ſo Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; it cannot fairly be doubted, but that the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Other Worlds</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from <hi>God, Both ſorts of Laws</hi> for their Direction and Conduct; and that the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them that are <hi>Supernatural,</hi> may Increaſe and Advance the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed:</hi> It being altogether as poſſible, that they may arrive at the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of them, as it is that the <hi>Angels</hi> of Heaven ſhould partake in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Myſteries</hi> and <hi>Laws;</hi> of which we are aſſured from the <hi>Sacred Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. Whether all that I have ſaid on this Subject, will render it probable, that the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the Bleſſed may <hi>Increaſe</hi> Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by <hi>Revelation,</hi> I leave to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Reader.</hi> I have ſuggeſted ſuch <hi>Probabilities,</hi> as occurred to my Thoughts. Thoſe that ſhall peruſe them, may <hi>Accept</hi> or <hi>Refuſe</hi> them, as they ſhall judge conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, or as they pleaſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:62928:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Increaſe of <hi>Knowledge</hi> by <hi>Hiſtorical Narration,</hi> or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat the Holy <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> are capable of Communicating their Thoughts and Sentiments to each other, is not doubted by <hi>Divines;</hi> nor is there any reaſon for it. Man is a <hi>Sociable Creature:</hi> 'Tis a Property that ſeems to be <hi>Eſſential</hi> unto him: And we have reaſon to think the like of the <hi>Holy Angels.</hi> They are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Beings,</hi> as well as <hi>Men;</hi> and, I believe, they are endowed with the ſame <hi>Eſſential Properties</hi> with them. And that <hi>Sociableneſs</hi> is as agreeable to the <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> as to the <hi>Humane</hi> Nature; and from both <hi>Equally</hi> inſeparable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How they do <hi>Communicate</hi> with each other, <hi>I</hi> do not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand,</hi> nor peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Any Man</hi> living on the Face of this Earth. He that will tell you how they do it, muſt intimately underſtand the <hi>Nature</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:62928:40"/>of <hi>Spirits,</hi> and whether they be <hi>Imbodied,</hi> yea or no, and what is the Nature of thoſe <hi>Bodies,</hi> and <hi>Vehicles,</hi> in which they lodge or dwell. But theſe are ſuch things, that no Man of <hi>Sound Senſe</hi> can pretend unto: And, by certain Conſequence, no Man doth know the <hi>Manner</hi> how <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> do mutually Converſe together, and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain each other. For whil'ſt we are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the <hi>Nature</hi> of things, we muſt needs be ignorant <hi>How</hi> they produce their Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. We are very much ignorant of the <hi>Nature</hi> of our <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Phyſick;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, can't tell how they do perform their <hi>Operations</hi> on our <hi>Bodies. Phyſicians</hi> are not yet agreed, whether <hi>Purgatives</hi> do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate by <hi>Pulſion</hi> or <hi>Traction,</hi> or meerly by <hi>Provoking</hi> Nature; and they are as little agreed how our <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, Diſtributed, and Turned into <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Humours,</hi> and alſo into <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Bones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Though we know not <hi>How</hi> very many things are done; yet we are much aſſured, that they <hi>Are.</hi> We know not <hi>How</hi> a <hi>Tree</hi> grows from a <hi>Seed,</hi> nor a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Variegated Flower</hi> from a <hi>Slip,</hi> that ſeems <hi>Simple,</hi> and without any <hi>Diverſity.</hi> We can't tell <hi>How</hi> Beaſts and Fiſhes are Formed, nor how <hi>Vermine</hi> are Bred in a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62928:41"/>
               <hi>Carkaſs,</hi> nor how <hi>Froggs</hi> are made of <hi>Spawn,</hi> or the <hi>Mudd</hi> and <hi>Slime</hi> of the River <hi>Nile.</hi> The Truth and Exiſtence of theſe things, is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeniable;</hi> but <hi>How</hi> they are Made and Generated, no Man is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If many things be <hi>Really</hi> Exiſtent, the <hi>Manner</hi> of whoſe Exiſtence we can give no <hi>Fair</hi> Account of. I ſee nothing that can reaſonably hinder us from granting, that <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> do <hi>Converſe</hi> together and <hi>Communicate</hi> their <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to each other. 'This certain, that <hi>They</hi> do many other things, which we cannot <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> or <hi>Comprehend.</hi> They do, or at leaſt have, often <hi>Appeared</hi> in <hi>Humane Shape,</hi> and <hi>Converſed</hi> with Men. Whether they have become Viſible, by forming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves <hi>Extemporate Bodies,</hi> of the Matter of the <hi>Air,</hi> and other <hi>Elements;</hi> or whether they have condenſed their <hi>Own Proper Bodies,</hi> and made them Viſible by <hi>Conſpiſſating</hi> the <hi>Matter</hi> of them, who can inform us? Granting either of theſe <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> who can teach us how they do effect it? Theſe are Inquiries, that the <hi>Wiſeſt</hi> cannot Anſwer; theſe are <hi>Problems,</hi> that they cannot reach or fathome.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Suppoſing then that <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> can Communicate their <hi>Knowledge,</hi> I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62928:41"/>do affirm, That the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> may be very greatly Increaſed thereby. For if there be, or have been, <hi>Other Worlds</hi> Exiſtent beſides <hi>This</hi> in which we live, the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may receive <hi>Information</hi> concerning them, by and from the <hi>Angels</hi> of Heaven, that have ſuperintended them, and by the Appointment of <hi>God,</hi> taken <hi>Cognizance</hi> of their Affairs: For it muſt not be doubted, but that <hi>God</hi> exerciſes a particular Care, and Providence over all the Works of his Hands; and 'tis as likely, that he ſhould make the <hi>Holy Angels</hi> the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtrators</hi> of it, in thoſe <hi>Other Worlds,</hi> as well as in <hi>This;</hi> of which there is no doubt, or the leaſt ſcruple or peradventure, among thoſe that bear the Name of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. By this means, the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may be informed of the Nature of the ſeveral <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> Exiſtent there; and what was the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> the <hi>Virtue,</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of them; and eſpecially, what <hi>Reaſonable Creatures</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit There; as alſo, what was the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> that <hi>God</hi> preſcribed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and impoſed upon them; and what the <hi>Obedience</hi> they gave unto them: To which I might add many other things; as, what was the <hi>Period</hi> of their <hi>Exiſtence,</hi> and by what <hi>Subordinat Means</hi> and <hi>Cauſes</hi> their <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:62928:42"/>were preſerved and continued; what and where they do receive <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Thus alſo they may be informed of all the great <hi>Emergencies</hi> that happened to them, and what were the <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions</hi> of them; as alſo, what <hi>Laws,</hi> what <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> was obſerved among them; and into what <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Different</hi> ſorts theſe Reaſonable <hi>Beings</hi> were diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; and how they employed and ſpent their Time: For Reaſonable Souls muſt have ſomething, upon which they may <hi>Exerciſe</hi> their Powers either by <hi>Action, Contemplation,</hi> or both; elſe their Powers are of <hi>No <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> but are made in <hi>Vain;</hi> which cannot be imagined, it being beneath the Wiſdom of a <hi>Prudent Man,</hi> and much beneath that of the <hi>All-Wiſe God,</hi> to give Being to <hi>Rational Creatures</hi> to no End or Purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. How many and numerous the <hi>Notices</hi> may be, that the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may receive after this <hi>manner</hi> is neither ſafe nor poſſible to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; for ſhould they deſcend to things minute and particular, (and who knows how low they may deſcend) how almoſt <hi>Infinite,</hi> and beyond all Computation would they be? Should there have been many Worlds <hi>Pre-exiſtent</hi> to <hi>This,</hi> or <hi>Co-exiſtent</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:62928:42"/>with it, what <hi>Infinite</hi> Matter of <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> would their Affairs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to the <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> or other <hi>Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Agents,</hi> that had Knowledge and Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of them? And how much of <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> would be <hi>Employed</hi> in theſe kind of <hi>Hiſtories</hi> and <hi>Narrations?</hi> And if we may judge any thing of the Agreeableneſs of things <hi>Then,</hi> to the Temper of our Minds, by what we may find <hi>Here</hi> below, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve concerning them, we muſt ſay, That ſuch things will be very <hi>Pleaſant</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful;</hi> not barely as <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> but as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi> and <hi>Evidences</hi> of the <hi>Infinite</hi> Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs of <hi>God;</hi> not as bare <hi>Narrations</hi> of ſuch and ſuch <hi>Events,</hi> but as <hi>Effects</hi> of the <hi>Infinite Power, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſearchable</hi> Wiſdom, and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe</hi> Goodneſs of the <hi>Creator</hi> of all things.</p>
            <p n="9">9. After the <hi>Same Manner</hi> the Bleſſed will obtain the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the Affairs of <hi>This World,</hi> ſince the Creation of it: The <hi>Holy Angels</hi> will certainly give them a large Account of the <hi>World,</hi> before the <hi>Flood;</hi> how, and by what <hi>Gradations</hi> they corrupted themſelves, departed from <hi>God,</hi> and abandoned themſelves to <hi>Senſuality</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs.</hi> What <hi>Moſes</hi> hath very briefly reported, they will diſcourſe more at large, and give to the Bleſſed a <hi>Full, Clear,</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62928:43"/>and <hi>Satisfactory Knowledge</hi> of them. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things that are <hi>Dark</hi> and <hi>Obſcure</hi> to us, will be ſet in <hi>Open Light,</hi> by their more <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Ample Diſcourſes:</hi> That which now miniſters Matter for <hi>Many,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Inſuperable Objections,</hi> will be totally freed from them, by their <hi>Larger Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries</hi> and <hi>Explications</hi> concerning them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The <hi>Holy Men</hi> of that Age, may alſo contribute ſomething towards the Increaſe of the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed. Adam,</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> and <hi>Seth,</hi> and <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> knew very much of the Affairs of the World, from the <hi>Creation</hi> to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge;</hi> and ſince their Removal to <hi>Heaven,</hi> there is no queſtion, but that they have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much improved it: And ſurely, they will <hi>Communicate</hi> their <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the <hi>New-Come Saints</hi> with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and Narratives of it.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The <hi>Holy Angels</hi> alſo will acquaint them with the <hi>Hiſtory of the World,</hi> after the <hi>Flood,</hi> till the Days of <hi>Abraham;</hi> they will give them Account of the Re-peopling of it by the Poſterity of <hi>Noah,</hi> of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Babel</hi> that they began to build, of the <hi>Confuſion</hi> of their <hi>Language,</hi> and of their <hi>Diſperſion</hi> into ſeveral Parts of the <hi>World</hi> thereupon: Of theſe things, I make no queſtion, they will give very large and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62928:43"/>particular <hi>Accounts:</hi> Of thoſe things, of which we now know almoſt nothing, then and there (I mean in the Society of the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi>) we ſhall have a <hi>Clear, Full,</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> Knowledge.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Noah</hi> himſelf lived four hundred and fifty Years after the <hi>Flood;</hi> and there is no doubt <hi>Saw</hi> and <hi>Knew</hi> much of the Affairs of the <hi>World:</hi> And there is as <hi>Little Doubt,</hi> in my Opinion, that he doth and will <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> the <hi>Knowledge</hi> thereof among the <hi>Bleſſed:</hi> And ſo will other of the <hi>Pious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> and <hi>Good Men</hi> of that Age. They will all contribute to the Increaſe of the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of thoſe, that in ſucceſſion of Times, are admitted into the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. And ſurely, the Hiſtory of the <hi>Church of God,</hi> in all Ages of the World, by the <hi>Narrations</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> will be moſt perfectly delivered to the <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> They will acquaint them with the ſeveral <hi>Accidents</hi> that have happened to it; how it hath ſuffered <hi>Many</hi> and <hi>Great Calamities</hi> from its Enemies, and ſometimes hath <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt</hi> periſhed from among Men; and then how, and by what <hi>Means</hi> it hath riſen as from the Aſhes, and become <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the World.</p>
            <p n="14">14. They will declare, and propoſe to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62928:44"/>their <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Conſideration,</hi> by what <hi>Improbable</hi> Means <hi>God</hi> hath raiſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it: In the Firſt Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity, God</hi> raiſed and increaſed <hi>His Church,</hi> by the Preaching and Diſcourſes of a few <hi>Poor Fiſher-men,</hi> in deſpight to all the Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that was made againſt it, by all the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Learning, Power,</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> of the World; yea, thoſe very Means, by which the Enemies of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Church</hi> thought to deſtroy it, were by the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> made inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of advancing it. They perſecuted all that were called by the <hi>Chriſtian Name;</hi> they deſpoyled them of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> their <hi>Friends,</hi> their <hi>Liberties,</hi> and their <hi>Honours;</hi> they treated them as the <hi>Vileſt</hi> Miſcreants; they killed and murthered them by <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands;</hi> they invented the moſt <hi>Cruel, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering,</hi> and <hi>Painful</hi> Deaths, that they could imagine: And yet all this would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Church of God;</hi> the <hi>Blood of the Martyrs was the Seed thereof;</hi> and the <hi>More</hi> they mowed, and cut them down, the <hi>More</hi> they increaſed.</p>
            <p n="15">15. As <hi>God</hi> raiſed his <hi>Church</hi> at firſt (I mean the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi>) by very <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Means;</hi> ſo hath he recovered it from a Lapſed and Corrupted Eſtate, by <hi>Means altogether as unlikely.</hi> After it had lain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62928:44"/>
               <hi>Hundreds</hi> of Years under the <hi>Papal</hi> Yoke; after it had long ſat in <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and been accuſtomed to <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and all the Kings of the Earth were ingaged in the Defence thereof; was it likely, that <hi>Luther,</hi> a poor mean <hi>Monk,</hi> ſhould ſo <hi>Leaven</hi> the World by his Doctrine, as to cauſe a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Falſhoods and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, and to recover a great part of the <hi>Chriſtian World</hi> to the true Worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> according to the <hi>Simplicity</hi> pf the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel:</hi> This was a thing <hi>Totally</hi> improbable; there was no appearance or likelihood of <hi>Succeſs</hi> therein.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Of theſe things, we have <hi>Some Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and in Antient and Modern <hi>Hiſtories:</hi> The <hi>Scriptures</hi> give us ſome brief Reports of the Raiſing of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> and by what Means 'twas done: The <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of the Antique <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Writers</hi> report the Increaſe and Enlargement of it; and by what <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> 'twas accompliſhed, and with what <hi>Oppoſition:</hi> And ſo do our latter <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> make Report of the <hi>Late Reformation,</hi> and by what <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Second Cauſes</hi> it became ſucceſsful. But I do not doubt, but that the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> do and will give more <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> Accounts of theſe things.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:62928:45"/>
            <p n="17">17. And how particular they may be in it, who is able to determine: But 'tis my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that they will be very <hi>Exact</hi> and <hi>Particular.</hi> Heaven is deſigned for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of the <hi>Divine</hi> Praiſe, and for the Celebration of the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; which cannot be done without <hi>Knowledge;</hi> and the moſt <hi>Exact</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> Knowledge, gives the <hi>Greateſt</hi> and <hi>Beſt</hi> Capacities for it. None are ſo fit to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, Praiſe, and adore the Attributes and Perfections of <hi>God,</hi> as thoſe that have the <hi>Largest</hi> and <hi>Compleatest</hi> Knowledge of the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Stupendious Effects</hi> of them. He is beſt able to commend a <hi>Learned Man,</hi> that hath read his <hi>Books,</hi> and hath the moſt <hi>Intimate</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> Underſtanding of his <hi>Accompliſhments.</hi> He is beſt able to ſpeak forth the <hi>Praiſes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that hath the <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>Extenſive</hi> Knowledge of his <hi>Providence,</hi> and his <hi>Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. How can any Man <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adore</hi> the Wiſdom of <hi>God,</hi> in the Raiſing, Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and Defending his <hi>Church,</hi> in deſpight to all the Craft, Subtilty, and Malice of the Enemies thereof, without the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Divine Conduct,</hi> in all its Affairs and Concernments? How can the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> praiſe the <hi>Power,</hi> the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Government</hi> of the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62928:45"/>
               <hi>Church,</hi> without an <hi>Exact</hi> Knowledge of <hi>God</hi>'s Dealings with it? And how can they have any Cognizance of them, but by the Tradition and Diſcourſes of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels?</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>God</hi> may give them the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them by <hi>Revelation;</hi> and I will not deny, but that ſome of the <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi> of <hi>God</hi> towards his <hi>Church</hi> may be ſo <hi>Made known</hi> unto them. But 'tis not <hi>God</hi>'s uſual Method, in <hi>This</hi> World, to do thoſe things by <hi>Supernatural Ways</hi> and <hi>Means,</hi> which may be done by thoſe that are <hi>Natural;</hi> nor do I believe, that it will be his <hi>Ordinary Way,</hi> in <hi>That</hi> which is to come. Some <hi>Peculiarities</hi> of Diſpenſations, perhaps, he may make known by <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but the <hi>Ordinary Way</hi> of imparting to the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> the Series of his <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> towards the <hi>Church,</hi> will be by <hi>Hiſtorical Narration,</hi> and Tradition.</p>
            <p n="19">19. There hath been a perpetual War between the <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> and the <hi>Seed of the Serpent,</hi> or (which is all alone) between the <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>People</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Vaſſals</hi> of the Devil. And as the viſible Conteſts and Battels that have been managed by theſe two Kingdoms, under their Heads and Chieftains, will be diſcourſed and related among the Bleſſed; ſo I do not doubt, but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62928:46"/>that the <hi>Inviſible Wars</hi> that have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by <hi>Michael,</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Church,</hi> againſt the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> in prejudice unto it, will be very largely laid open there: And how <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Extenſive</hi> the <hi>Knowledge</hi> thereof may be, who can ſay? And if the <hi>Sevenal Smaller</hi> Inſtances and Particulars thereof be made known, (as 'tis probable they will) how <hi>Numerous,</hi> and almoſt <hi>Infinite</hi> will they be? And how many <hi>Ages</hi> may be ſpent in the <hi>Communication</hi> of the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them?</p>
            <p n="20">20. Multitudes of very ſtrange Events do happen and occur to <hi>Kingdoms, Nations,</hi> and <hi>Churches,</hi> and particular <hi>Families</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> of which we are able to give no Account, becauſe we have <hi>No Knowledge</hi> (or at leaſt, very <hi>Little</hi>) of them, or their Affairs: We know not what their <hi>Mercies</hi> have been, nor what are their <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations.</hi> We know not what are their <hi>Qualities</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſitions,</hi> nor what are their <hi>Temptations;</hi> and therefore can't rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon for the <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Strange Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that do betide them. But in the <hi>Other World,</hi> when we ſhall have an <hi>Hiſtorical Narrative</hi> of all thoſe things, 'twill be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to give a reaſon of all the <hi>Strange E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents</hi> that did betide them. If a Perſon ſhould be taken out of a <hi>Cave,</hi> or ſome
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62928:46"/>Place of <hi>Secreſie</hi> and <hi>Silence,</hi> after many Years <hi>Retirement</hi> and <hi>Abode</hi> there, and brought to a <hi>Place</hi> where Publick <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are done, and there ſee Men <hi>Hung by the Neck, cut down ere they were Dead, their Bowels taken out, their Members cut off, and burnt before their Faces, and their Bodies cut into Quarters after the manner of Beaſts;</hi> 'tis not to be doubted, but that he would be <hi>Strangely Amazed</hi> at ſuch a Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure: But when he ſhould afterward be acquainted with their <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> their <hi>Actions</hi> and their <hi>Deſigns,</hi> and receive a full <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Narrative</hi> of them, he would be able to give himſelf a <hi>Reaſon</hi> of all theſe Severities, and be abundantly <hi>Satisfied</hi> in the Wiſdome and Equity of them.</p>
            <p n="21">21. The Affairs of the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> are ſo much <hi>Mingled</hi> and <hi>Confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> that the One cannot be known with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Other: The Victories and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of the <hi>Church,</hi> can't be mentioned, or propoſed to <hi>Conſideration,</hi> without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the Attempts and Aſſaults that were made upon them by the <hi>Men</hi> of the World. The Triumphs of the <hi>Church</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Judaiſme</hi> and <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> can't be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, without mention of the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Furious Oppoſition</hi> that was made by the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62928:47"/>
               <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi> The Succeſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of the <hi>True Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> upon the <hi>Apoſtate Romiſh Synagogue,</hi> cannot be called to mind, without a Rehearſal of its <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Enraged</hi> Oppoſition unto it.</p>
            <p n="22">22. And truly, <hi>This World</hi> being a <hi>Stage</hi> or <hi>Theater,</hi> and the ſeveral Revolutions and Changes in it, being only ſo many <hi>Scenes</hi> and <hi>Parts</hi> of the <hi>Comedy,</hi> or rather of the <hi>Tragedy;</hi> and the Glorious <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> being the <hi>Spectators,</hi> and they all being to give to <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Praiſe</hi> after the great Cataſtrophe and Concluſion of all things; It ſeems to me very probable, that they ſhall have a <hi>Very Perfect</hi> Knowledge of all the Affairs of it. No Man can judge of the Skill and Contrivance, the Wit and Ingeny of a <hi>Comedian,</hi> that hath not a full and clear <hi>Knowledge</hi> of all the Parts of the <hi>Comedy.</hi> And ſure it is, that no Man can reaſonably, and as it becomes a Man, judge of the <hi>Infinite</hi> Wiſdom, and <hi>Curious</hi> Skill of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Various</hi> Changes and Mutations that are ſeen in the World, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he hath a <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſive Knowledge</hi> of them. No Man can give that Applauſe to the Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Goodneſs of <hi>God,</hi> as is <hi>Suitable</hi> to thoſe Attributes, that hath not a <hi>Very Great</hi> and <hi>Perſpicuous Knowledge</hi> of the ſeveral <hi>Events</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:62928:47"/>and <hi>Contingencies,</hi> that have happened in the World.</p>
            <p n="23">23. And foraſmuch as the meaneſt <hi>Saints</hi> that formerly lived on Earth, had a Part to act upon the <hi>Stage</hi> of <hi>This World,</hi> and did perform it; perhaps, even <hi>Each of Them,</hi> as well as the <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> may contribute ſomething to the mutual <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> amongſt the <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> The <hi>Leaſt of all Saints</hi> will be able to ſay <hi>Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> of the Attributes and Perfections of <hi>God.</hi> Some of the Effects of his <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> they have obſerved, and will be able to mention to his Praiſe.</p>
            <p n="24">24. How many of the Days of <hi>Eternity</hi> may be ſpent in learning the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in it, I muſt not pretend to <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> much leſs <hi>Define.</hi> But ſurely, it being ſo <hi>Exceeding</hi> large, and the <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Inſtances</hi> of it being ſo <hi>Numerous,</hi> it may <hi>Justly</hi> be thought, that a very <hi>Conſiderable</hi> Part thereof, will be therein imployed. 'Tis certain, that in the <hi>Future State,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will retain their own proper <hi>Eſſences;</hi> which being <hi>Finite,</hi> I am not able to conceive, how they can receive the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of things any other way, but <hi>Succeſſively;</hi> and what is received <hi>Succeſſively,</hi> doth exhauſt more or leſs of Time; according as that <hi>Knowledge,</hi> or thoſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62928:48"/>
               <hi>Notices</hi> of things are more or leſs numerous and increaſed.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Let no Man hence infer, that the Days of <hi>Eternity</hi> will be ſpent in <hi>Ineffective Diſcourſes, Hiſtories,</hi> and <hi>Narrations:</hi> To entertain <hi>Such</hi> Thoughts of it, were to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame</hi> and <hi>Blaſpheme</hi> it. The <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> will not be <hi>Ineffective, Idle,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable;</hi> they will <hi>Affect</hi> the Hearts both of thoſe that <hi>Speak,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>Hear;</hi> they will produce <hi>Affections</hi> ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their <hi>Nature.</hi> Some of the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> that will be reported There, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Amazements</hi> and <hi>Wonder;</hi> others will awaken, and actuate <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> others <hi>Joy, Delight,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in Him: And all of them <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Confeſſions</hi> to the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of his <hi>Tranſcendent</hi> Excellencies, and <hi>Glorious</hi> Attributes and Virtues. The Minds of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will be ſo <hi>Set</hi> and <hi>Tuned,</hi> that every mention of the Works and Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>God,</hi> will make Impreſſions on them <hi>Acceptable</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>Advantage</hi> of their own <hi>Felicity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. And certainly, <hi>such Diſcourſes</hi> are an Imployment worthy of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> and very ſuitable to the <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> to which they are advanced. They are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to a <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Happy</hi> State; and what is more comely and decorous, than to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62928:48"/>ſpeak of the <hi>Wonders</hi> of his Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Goodneſs, that hath <hi>Raiſed</hi> them to it; and thereby excite and actuate their own <hi>Love, Thanks,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe?</hi> Nothing can be more <hi>Congruous</hi> and <hi>Agreeable</hi> to <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Natures, in their <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> and under their <hi>Obligations,</hi> than ſuch kind of Exerciſes: Nothing can be more worthy of <hi>God,</hi> nor nothing more agreeable to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Beings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. We may obſerve, that the Holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> very frequently calls to mind, and reports the <hi>Mighty</hi> Works, and <hi>Stupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Providences of <hi>God</hi> towards the <hi>Jewiſh Nation:</hi> He remembers <hi>God</hi>'s Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> their Captivity in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and miraculous Deliverance thence: He reports their many Provocations in the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs;</hi> the Judgments that he executed upon them; their <hi>Feigned Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Flattering</hi> him with <hi>Their Lips,</hi> when <hi>Their Hearts were not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright with him.</hi> And why did he remember theſe things? 'Twas to exalt the Honour of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Kindneſs, Grace,</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> towards the <hi>Jews,</hi> and his <hi>Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs</hi> in his <hi>Covenant.</hi> He had ſworn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to give the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> for an Inheritance to his Seed; and he would not fail to <hi>Verify his Oath,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their <hi>Provocations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62928:49"/>
            <p n="28">28. And truly, I ſee no reaſon, why the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> may not report the <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Providences</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and make mention of them to <hi>His Praiſe.</hi> If <hi>Praiſe</hi> be comely for the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in this World,</hi> it will be altogether as comely for them in the <hi>Other:</hi> And if the making mention of the <hi>Mighty Acts of the Lord,</hi> be a proper means of exciting and awakening it in <hi>This,</hi> it may be ſo alſo in <hi>That</hi> which is to come. If it be a <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant Duty</hi> on Earth, 'tis <hi>Much more</hi> ſo in Heaven. Though Pious Men on Earth have received <hi>Many</hi> and <hi>Great Bleſſings</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and ſuch as do very much oblige them to <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Praiſe Him;</hi> yet ſure it is, that thoſe that are in Heaven, have received <hi>Many More,</hi> and thoſe that are of <hi>More Raiſed,</hi> and <hi>Excellent Nature;</hi> and therefore, are under <hi>Greater Obligations</hi> thereunto. And if we may conjecture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of the Nature and Conſtitution of <hi>Humane Minds There,</hi> by what we have experience of <hi>Here,</hi> nothing will more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and excite their <hi>Gratitude,</hi> and their <hi>Praiſe,</hi> than the Reports of his kind <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences,</hi> and <hi>Mighty Works</hi> done in the World.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Some more things I might ſuggeſt, to make the <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62928:49"/>
               <hi>Probable,</hi> and that Eternally; as the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the Kingdom of Darkneſs, the <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> the <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,</hi> that are obſerved and found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. For without ſome <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> they cannot manage their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and his <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and without <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Laws are <hi>Inſignificant,</hi> and <hi>Toothleſs</hi> things. Theſe things (I doubt not) are well known by the <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> and by Them communicated to the <hi>Bleſſed:</hi> As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, what are the <hi>Puniſhments</hi> that <hi>God</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts upon <hi>Them,</hi> and <hi>Condemned Souls,</hi> for their Wickedneſs; and the ſeveral <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> and <hi>Gradual Differences</hi> of them; with other things of like nature. But, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the <hi>Reader</hi> may think, I have been too <hi>Prolix</hi> already; therefore, this <hi>Chapter</hi> ſhall here receive its Concluſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:62928:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Increaſe of <hi>Knowledge</hi> by <hi>Ratiocination.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>RAtiocination</hi> is an <hi>Inferring</hi> of One thing from Another, or a <hi>Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> from <hi>Things Known,</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown;</hi> and a <hi>Concluding</hi> of One from the Other. Thus we conclude, that the <hi>Sun</hi> is near the <hi>Summer-Solſtice,</hi> becauſe the Days are at their <hi>Greateſt</hi> Length; and that it is near the <hi>Winter-Solſtice,</hi> becauſe they are of the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Shortneſs. Thus we conclude, that the <hi>Sun</hi> approaches the <hi>Equator,</hi> when we ſee the <hi>Graſs</hi> grow <hi>Green</hi> and <hi>Flouriſhing,</hi> and the <hi>Trees</hi> put forth their <hi>Buds</hi> and <hi>Leaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The reaſoning <hi>Power,</hi> and diſcurſive <hi>Faculty,</hi> will be of uſe in the <hi>World to come.</hi> From the Conſideration of what <hi>God is,</hi> from the Memory of what <hi>He hath done,</hi> and from the Knowledge of what <hi>He doth do,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will <hi>Certainly conclude,</hi> the Neceſſity of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to Him.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62928:50"/>When they conſider, that He is the <hi>Firſt Cauſe,</hi> and giveth Being to all <hi>Creatures,</hi> and to Men <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Breath,</hi> and <hi>All Things:</hi> When they remember, that He <hi>Made</hi> them after his <hi>Own Image;</hi> and when they had loſt it by ſinning againſt Him, He ſent his <hi>Son into the World,</hi> to <hi>Take away their Guilt,</hi> to <hi>Renew</hi> and <hi>Sanctifie</hi> their <hi>Natures,</hi> and to <hi>Reſtore</hi> his <hi>Image</hi> to them again: When they call to mind, that He <hi>Supports</hi> their <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>Faculties,</hi> and <hi>Furniſhes</hi> them with <hi>Suitable Objects,</hi> for their Imployment and Delight; They do <hi>Immediately</hi> infer, the great Neceſſity of <hi>Loving</hi> and <hi>Serving</hi> this <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Good God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings</hi> of the Bleſſed were <hi>Infinite,</hi> I think they would have no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Ratiocination:</hi> But foraſmuch as they are certainly of <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Definite</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I cannot underſtand, how they will be able to perform that <hi>Duty,</hi> and exerciſe thoſe <hi>Affections</hi> upon <hi>God,</hi> without it; which all Men confeſs, are the <hi>Imployment</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the Bleſſed. Can they <hi>Love God,</hi> without Conſideration of his <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Excellencies,</hi> and <hi>Amiable Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions?</hi> Can they <hi>Obey</hi> Him, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his <hi>Rightful Soveraignty,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and <hi>Great Benefactions?</hi> Or is not this <hi>Conſideration,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62928:51"/>ſequent thereunto, a manifeſt <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> and Uſe of their <hi>Diſcurſive</hi> Faculty and Power?</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſome things in <hi>This World,</hi> are more <hi>Obvious,</hi> and better <hi>Known</hi> than others, cannot be denyed; and, I believe, were ſo to <hi>Adam,</hi> whil'ſt he remained <hi>Innocent.</hi> I doubt not, but that the <hi>Firſt Principles</hi> of <hi>Things</hi> were more plain to his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> than the numerous <hi>Concluſions</hi> dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from them, as well as they are to <hi>Ours.</hi> 'Twas more obvious to him, that the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Lines</hi> drawn from the Center of a <hi>Circle,</hi> were equal among themſelves; than that all the Sides of an <hi>Aequilateral Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle,</hi> are the <hi>Radii</hi> of <hi>Equal Circles;</hi> with many others, that might be mentioned, if the thing were not plain, beyond all <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> Doubt or Scruple. And if it be thus on <hi>Earth,</hi> and were ſo even <hi>Before</hi> the <hi>Fall,</hi> why may it not be ſo in <hi>Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. If from <hi>Moral</hi> Principles the Bleſſed do infer <hi>Morael</hi> Concluſions, (which I think, cannot be denyed) why may they not do the like from <hi>Natural?</hi> If from the <hi>Being, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> they do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Love, Fear,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> why may they not infer from ſuch things as are <hi>Natural,</hi> and <hi>Well Known,</hi> thoſe things that are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known,</hi> yet <hi>Naturally</hi> conſequent unto them?
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62928:51"/>And indeed, (as I ſee no reaſon to deny it) ſo I am much <hi>Paſt Doubt</hi> of the Truth of it. I cannot but <hi>believe,</hi> that the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will <hi>Conclude,</hi> that they are able to <hi>Move To</hi> and <hi>Fro,</hi> with <hi>Incredible Swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Bodies</hi> are <hi>Spiritual;</hi> and many other <hi>Concluſions</hi> of like Nature, will they infer from like <hi>Premiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Concluſions</hi> that (in this weak and imperfect State) have been made from ſome few <hi>Principles,</hi> in every <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> are almoſt <hi>Infinite:</hi> Who can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>Concluſions</hi> that have been made from the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Natural Philoſophy, Metaphyſick,</hi> and <hi>Geometry?</hi> How many vaſt, and almoſt numberleſs <hi>Volumes,</hi> have been written concerning them? And when will they make an end? 'Thoſe <hi>Sciences</hi> have been ſtudied and poliſhed by <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Chritians,</hi> for well night two <hi>Thouſand</hi> Years; and yet every <hi>New Writer</hi> pretends to ſay ſomething, that was not ſaid before; and to add to the <hi>Advancement,</hi> Increaſe and Perfection of them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Some think, the <hi>Inferences</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions,</hi> that are made from the Principles of <hi>Geometry</hi> alone, may be capable of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Increaſe</hi> and <hi>Augmentation;</hi> and truly, he that conſiders the <hi>Numberleſs</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> that are in the ſeveral
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62928:52"/>
               <hi>Branches</hi> and <hi>Dependencies</hi> of that <hi>Science,</hi> will find no great difficulty in <hi>believing</hi> it. How numerous are the <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> that are to be ſound in <hi>Geometry,</hi> properly and ſtrictly taken, in <hi>Aſtronomy, Algebra, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, Opticks, Dialling,</hi> and the Art of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation?</hi> And how <hi>Few</hi> and <hi>Simple</hi> are the <hi>Principles,</hi> from which they have been <hi>Inferred</hi> and <hi>Deduced?</hi> What daily <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Increaſes,</hi> are made to them by <hi>Learned Men?</hi> Every day, almoſt, Books are Publiſhed and Printed, in which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is added towards the <hi>Perfection</hi> of thoſe <hi>Sciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. And as <hi>Numbers</hi> may be perpetually, and to all Durations <hi>Increaſed</hi> by <hi>Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> ſo I am very much inclined to believe, that the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> in <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are, or ever will be ſo <hi>Numerous,</hi> but that they may be <hi>Increaſed:</hi> And thoſe that are <hi>Skilled</hi> in them, and do obſerve how they <hi>Generate</hi> each other, will (I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded) think as I do; and <hi>Modeſtly</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That it may be continued to <hi>Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. In the mean time, I will not affirm, That the Study of <hi>Geometry</hi> will be any part of the Imployment of the <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> Perhaps, there will be <hi>NO <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it, or <hi>Occaſion</hi> for it There. Some <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62928:52"/>with our <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> becauſe the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of them will then determine. All the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Artifices,</hi> by which Men ſupport <hi>Themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>Families,</hi> will receive their <hi>Period</hi> with our <hi>Lives:</hi> The Arts of <hi>Plowing</hi> and <hi>Sowing,</hi> of <hi>Building</hi> and <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> of Paſſing the <hi>Seas,</hi> and <hi>Navigating</hi> into <hi>Forreign Countries,</hi> will end with <hi>This Life,</hi> becauſe there will be <hi>No <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of them in the <hi>Other.</hi> And, perhaps, ſo it may be with all <hi>Mathematical</hi> Learning and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But if the Principles of one <hi>Single Science,</hi> may be Productive of almoſt <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Concluſions,</hi> much more may the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all <hi>Sciences:</hi> And that ſome <hi>Science</hi> will be of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> in the <hi>Other State,</hi> few doubt or deny. The <hi>Science</hi> of <hi>Natural Philoſophy</hi> will remain There: The Bleſſed ſhall underſtand the <hi>Nature</hi> of their <hi>Own Bodies,</hi> and all <hi>Others,</hi> that they <hi>Converſe</hi> withal, and are <hi>Preſented</hi> to their View. How can they give <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Praiſe</hi> of them, if they do not <hi>Know</hi> them, nor cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate the <hi>Abyſſes</hi> of them? And how far this <hi>Knowledge</hi> may extend, who is able to divine?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Beſides, it is not improbable, that the <hi>Future World</hi> may furniſh many <hi>Species,</hi> and Kinds of <hi>Bodies,</hi> to our Contemplation.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62928:53"/>The <hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>Sea,</hi> and <hi>Air,</hi> have their peculiar Kinds of <hi>Corporeal Eſſences;</hi> yea, every <hi>Climate,</hi> almoſt, hath ſomething <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> to it ſelf: And what hinders, but that the <hi>Higheſt Heavens</hi> may have multitudes of <hi>Peculiarities;</hi> the like whereunto, our Eyes have never <hi>Seen,</hi> nor our Ears <hi>Heard?</hi> Yea, give me leave to ſay, That I am much paſt doubt of it. Surely, that <hi>Bleſſed State</hi> will preſent many <hi>Glorious Objects,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Beings</hi> to our View; and our <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> will be much <hi>Increaſed</hi> and <hi>Enlarged</hi> thereby.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Moreover, we cannot doubt, but the <hi>Science</hi> of <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> will alſo be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued There. The moſt <hi>Glorious</hi> of all Reaſonable <hi>Creatures,</hi> are of <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> Nature: Such are all the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed Saints.</hi> Whether there be any thing <hi>Material</hi> in their <hi>Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> whether they be <hi>Imbodied</hi> in <hi>Pure,</hi> and <hi>AEtherial Vehicles,</hi> I will not here diſpute; but all do grant, that there is ſomething in their <hi>Eſſence,</hi> that is <hi>Spiritual;</hi> and, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will have ſome <hi>Knowledge</hi> of it. They will not remain ſo ignorant of the <hi>Nature, Powers,</hi> and <hi>Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of <hi>Spirits,</hi> as now they are. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what they will <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> of them, and the <hi>Manner</hi> of their <hi>Operations;</hi> as alſo, what
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62928:53"/>
               <hi>Gradual Differences</hi> there are among them, and what <hi>Diverſity</hi> in their Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Perfections: For as there are very <hi>Many</hi> Differences (I mean, Gradual) <hi>among Bodies,</hi> ſo there may be <hi>among Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> for ought that I know. And from this <hi>Diverſity,</hi> may proceed very great Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in their <hi>Powers, Capacities,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections;</hi> the <hi>Knowledge</hi> whereof, may <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,</hi> perhaps, to all Durations.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The <hi>Science</hi> of <hi>Theology</hi> will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Continue, but be very much Inlarged. Much more of <hi>God</hi> will be <hi>Revealed</hi> in the <hi>Future State,</hi> than ever was <hi>Revealed</hi> in <hi>This;</hi> and our Faculties will be much more <hi>Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> of conſidering and underſtanding thoſe <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> and <hi>Revelations.</hi> I do not doubt, but that <hi>Heaven</hi> will preſent to the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> far more <hi>Illuſtrious Demonſtrations</hi> of the <hi>Divine Perfections,</hi> than any that have been made here below. The <hi>Creation, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and <hi>Word of God,</hi> I do acknowledge, have unfolded much of <hi>God;</hi> yet I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <hi>Heaven</hi> will diſcover <hi>Much more:</hi> For Here we <hi>See through a Glaſs darkly, but there Face to Face.</hi> Here we ſee Him very <hi>Obſcurely</hi> and <hi>Imperfectly;</hi> but There we ſhall ſee Him as He is. And as the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Him will be more <hi>Clear</hi> and <hi>Full,</hi> ſo will our Minds
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62928:54"/>be <hi>More Capable</hi> of receiving and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</p>
            <p n="14">14. And who can gueſs, what <hi>Abyſſes</hi> there may be in the <hi>Theology</hi> of the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</hi> Who can imagine, what may be the <hi>Treaſures</hi> thereof? And what Time may be ſpent to <hi>Exhauſt</hi> them? And whether, after <hi>Millions</hi> of Ages, there may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main much <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexhauſted?</hi> The Inquiries that <hi>Job</hi> makes, (<hi>Canst thou by ſearching find out</hi> God? <hi>Canſt thou find out the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to Perfection? It is as high as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; What canſt thou do? Deeper than Hell; What canst thou know? The Meaſure thereof, is longer than the Earth, and broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than the Sea</hi>) may be as truly made in the <hi>Other World,</hi> as in <hi>This:</hi> And, in my Apprehenſion, the Perfections of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Theology</hi> of them, are truly <hi>Inexhauſtible</hi> in both.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the <hi>Sacred Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> may afford Subject and Matter for <hi>Eternal Contemplations;</hi> and, it may be, there may be thoſe Depths in them, which the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may never be able to <hi>Fathome</hi> or <hi>Comprehend.</hi> They are ſuch things, as in <hi>This World,</hi> we cannot <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand;</hi> our Reaſon draws back at the <hi>Contemplation</hi> of them: And had we not ſome Reverence for the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:62928:54"/>that do <hi>Reveal</hi> and <hi>Propoſe</hi> them, we ſhould utterly refuſe <hi>All Aſſent</hi> unto them. They are <hi>Too Bigg</hi> for our Minds, in the <hi>Preſent State;</hi> and therefore, we live under ſome <hi>Temptation</hi> to reject them; and were we not awed by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we ſhould certainly do it. In the <hi>Other World,</hi> theſe things will be more <hi>Clearly</hi> revealed, and more fully <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtood:</hi> But whether there be not ſomething, which after all <hi>Search</hi> and <hi>Inquiry,</hi> will remain <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown</hi> even to the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> themſelves, I think very <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> if not abſolutely <hi>Certain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. The Perfections of the <hi>Perſon</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> (I mean, of his <hi>Humane Nature</hi>) are without all ſcruple, exceeding <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Large;</hi> and there is not an <hi>Eſſence</hi> (unleſs <hi>God</hi> himſelf) <hi>Equal</hi> with it, much leſs <hi>Superiour</hi> to it, in the whole <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> of Beings. The ſhining <hi>Luſtre</hi> of his <hi>Body,</hi> with the ſeveral <hi>Perfections</hi> of it, will be exceeding <hi>Great;</hi> but the <hi>Powers, Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies,</hi> and <hi>Capacities</hi> of his <hi>Soul</hi> will be much more <hi>Stupendious, Admirable,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing.</hi> And I ſee no reaſon, why the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may not obtain the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them, and other things before-mentioned by <hi>Ratiocina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> Why may not much of the <hi>Knowledge</hi> that they have there, both of <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> be gotten by <hi>Inference</hi> and <hi>Deduction?</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:62928:55"/>Why may they not argue from thoſe things that are <hi>Plain,</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>Dark?</hi> Why may they not argue from <hi>Cauſes</hi> to their <hi>Effects,</hi> and from <hi>Effects</hi> to their <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> too?</p>
            <p n="17">17. Here 'tis the ordinary <hi>Method</hi> of proceeding: Men argue from the Fabrick of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> in it, the Certainty of a <hi>First Cauſe,</hi> of <hi>Infin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> and from the <hi>Immateriality</hi> of the <hi>Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> its <hi>Incorruptibility;</hi> and from its <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality,</hi> its <hi>Simplicity;</hi> with ſundry other <hi>Inferences</hi> of like <hi>Nature.</hi> And why the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may not do the <hi>Same,</hi> I cannot <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand:</hi> if their Reaſonable Faculties <hi>Continue,</hi> (as <hi>Surely</hi> they do) the Uſe of them may <hi>Continue.</hi> If it be conſiſtent with the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy</hi> them, I ſee no <hi>Valid</hi> Reaſon, why the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of them may not conſiſt with it.</p>
            <p n="18">18. What hinders, but that there may be ſuch <hi>Effects</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> of a <hi>Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and of an <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> as may much <hi>Reveal</hi> the Nature of thoſe <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries;</hi> and make the <hi>Inference</hi> as <hi>Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and <hi>Eaſie,</hi> as from an <hi>Effect</hi> to a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or from a <hi>Copy</hi> to an <hi>Original.</hi> Some <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of them we do obſerve here. In the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62928:55"/>Mind,</hi> there is a <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Eſſential Principles,</hi> and yet but <hi>One</hi> Soul. In Man, the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> do conſtitute but <hi>One Perſon:</hi> But 'tis not improbable, but there may be more <hi>Perſpicuous Images</hi> of them there; and that thoſe that here we do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, will be <hi>More</hi> fully underſtood. And in conſequence thereunto, theſe <hi>Myſteries</hi> may be as <hi>Evident</hi> to the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> as that the <hi>Whole</hi> is bigger than any <hi>Part</hi> and that all the <hi>Parts</hi> taken together, are equal to the <hi>Whole.</hi> I do not mean, they ſhall <hi>Fully</hi> underſtand them; but they ſhall <hi>Clearly</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, and to the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> of their Souls.</p>
            <p n="19">19. The Reconcileableneſs of the <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Will, with the <hi>Liberty</hi> of Man's, is an <hi>Inſuperable</hi> Difficulty <hi>Now;</hi> but perchance, it may be none <hi>Then.</hi> The <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may poſſibly ſee and underſtand thoſe <hi>Principles, Premiſes,</hi> and <hi>Suppoſitions;</hi> from whence they may be eaſily deduced, without any <hi>Inconſiſtency</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition.</hi> The Difficulty of reconciling theſe things, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from our <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the Nature of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and the <hi>Influence</hi> that the One, and the Other hath upon <hi>Humane</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Did we know, what <hi>God,</hi> and what Man is, and what are the Operations <hi>Peculiar</hi> to One, and the Other, in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62928:56"/>producing thoſe <hi>Effects</hi> that are aſcribed to Men, probably much, or all of this Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty would <hi>Diſappear.</hi> Now 'tis not queſtioned, but that the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will very much <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> all theſe; and from them will argue, and infer an eaſie and obvious <hi>Agreement</hi> between them.</p>
            <p n="20">20. The <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God</hi> are <hi>Infinite;</hi> they are <hi>Oceans,</hi> without either Bank or Bottom, if I may ſo expreſs it. His <hi>Power</hi> is Omnipotent. <hi>God</hi> can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh whatſoever he pleaſes. No Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition can be made to his Mighty Arm. If he will work, none can hinder it. His <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is unſearchable; the Depths there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are unfathomable; no Created Being can find them out unto Perfection. His <hi>Goodneſs</hi> is of very vaſt Extenſion: Who can take the juſt Meaſures of it? <hi>'Tis wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than the Earth, larger than the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſs;</hi> yea, more extenſive than the <hi>Poles</hi> of <hi>Heaven.</hi> And what vaſt Numbers of <hi>Inferences</hi> and <hi>Concluſions</hi> may be made from the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of them? How far may they be <hi>Propagated?</hi> and where will they determine?</p>
            <p n="21">21. From the <hi>Knowledg</hi> of the <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>Attributes,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may, 'tis like, infer and deduce the manner of the Divine <hi>Agency</hi> upon the Minds of Men. That <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:62928:56"/>doth move and act upon the <hi>Souls</hi> of Men Here, is certain both in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and in <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience;</hi> and there is no doubt, but he will do ſo Hereafter: But how he doth it, is an <hi>Inſuperable</hi> Difficulty. <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>Pure Act,</hi> of <hi>Infinite</hi> and <hi>Immenſe</hi> Preſence; without any <hi>Accidents,</hi> properly ſo called. His <hi>Attributes</hi> being his <hi>Eſſence,</hi> according to the general Opinion of <hi>Divines;</hi> I ſay, how <hi>God</hi> doth influence the Minds of Men, and what that Influence is <hi>Ex parte Dei,</hi> is paſt the reach of Mortals to determine. 'Tis commonly ſaid, That 'tis nothing but <hi>God</hi> himſelf; by <hi>God,</hi> meaning his <hi>Act;</hi> and thereby underſtanding his <hi>Eſſence</hi> as in <hi>Act:</hi> But how an <hi>Eſſence Equally,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally Active,</hi> can produce thoſe <hi>Various</hi> Impreſſions upon <hi>Various</hi> Minds, and on the <hi>Same</hi> Minds, at <hi>Sundry</hi> times, is paſt our preſent <hi>Imagination.</hi> And ſo it is alſo how they can receive the <hi>Divine</hi> Influx, if it be nothing but his <hi>Active</hi> Eſſence. But it may be, that the Bleſſed may have <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of thoſe <hi>Praecognita,</hi> from whence the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of theſe things may be inferred by <hi>Plain</hi> and <hi>Eaſie Ratiocination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. That there is a <hi>Creative</hi> Power in <hi>God,</hi> is confeſſed by all <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and ſome ſober <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have ſaid ſome things in favour of it. By <hi>Creative Power,</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:62928:57"/>I mean a Power of giving <hi>Being</hi> to things, without any <hi>Pre-exiſtent</hi> Matter. This is ſuch a <hi>Perfection,</hi> as we cannot <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend;</hi> but the <hi>Other State</hi> may furniſh us with ſuch <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Divine Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence</hi> and <hi>Fecundity,</hi> that the giving <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to Things by <hi>Creation,</hi> will be an <hi>Eaſie</hi> and <hi>Obvious</hi> Effect of it: And the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will as eaſily infer it thence, as we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Growth and Fructification of <hi>Herbs,</hi> and <hi>Trees,</hi> and <hi>Fruits,</hi> from a <hi>Fruitful</hi> Soyl, the <hi>Warmth</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the <hi>Dew</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. The Doctrine of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> is a thing that we believe, out of <hi>Reverence</hi> to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> who is the <hi>Author</hi> of them: But how <hi>Dead</hi> Bones, and Scattered <hi>Duſt</hi> can live; how thoſe-Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that have been eaten by <hi>Wild Beasts</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> or burnt to <hi>Aſhes,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Aſhes</hi> caſt into the <hi>Sea,</hi> can be <hi>Recollected,</hi> and become an <hi>Habitation</hi> for the <hi>Soul,</hi> we are not able to underſtand. But 'tis not improbable, but that the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> may from the <hi>Knowledge</hi> that they have of the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Subordinate</hi> Cauſes thereof, infer and conclude it, with no more <hi>Difficulty,</hi> than we infer the <hi>Building</hi> of a City, or Houſe again, after its ruined and laid in Rubbiſh; from the Knowledge that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62928:57"/>we have of the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Skill</hi> of Men, the Advantages of the <hi>Place</hi> where it was ſcituate, and the Plenty of <hi>Materials</hi> for the Re-edification of it.</p>
            <p n="24">24. The Nature of that <hi>Influence,</hi> and <hi>Support,</hi> by which we <hi>Live, and Move, and have our Being,</hi> is a thing that we are <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally</hi> ignorant of. That there is ſuch a thing, is generally confeſſed by all <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering</hi> Men; for Creatures do not become <hi>Independent,</hi> as ſoon as they do ſubſiſt. They depend on <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Facto eſſe,</hi> as well as in <hi>Fieri:</hi> They need the <hi>Divine Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> as well when they are <hi>Made,</hi> as when they are <hi>Making.</hi> But what this <hi>Divine Influence</hi> and <hi>Cauſation</hi> is, we do not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand;</hi> but 'tis not unlikely, but that the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> may by ſearching, <hi>Find</hi> it out. They may have the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of thoſe <hi>Premiſes,</hi> from which the <hi>Nature</hi> of it may be eaſily deduced. In thoſe <hi>Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> that we imploy <hi>Our ſelves</hi> in, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our <hi>Contemplations</hi> on here, there are many <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> that in themſelves, and <hi>Irreſpectively</hi> conſidered, are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintelligible,</hi> and paſt our Comprehenſion; which, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, are <hi>Plainly</hi> deducible from their <hi>Premiſes,</hi> and <hi>Evident</hi> enough to him that is <hi>Prepared</hi> for the underſtanding of them, by neceſſary <hi>Antecedent</hi> Knowledge. Thus
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62928:58"/>'tis in thouſands of <hi>Mathematical</hi> Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. That in all plain, right-angled <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles,</hi> the Square of the <hi>Hypotenuſe</hi> ſhould be equal to the <hi>Squares</hi> of the other two Sides, is a thing that no Man underſtands <hi>Abſolutely</hi> and <hi>Irreſpectively:</hi> But if he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the <hi>Neceſſary</hi> Premiſes and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, 'tis plain enough, and the <hi>Deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> thereof is not <hi>Difficult.</hi> And if things dark and obſcure, may be inferred from things more <hi>Plain</hi> and <hi>Obvious</hi> in this <hi>World,</hi> I know not why it may not be ſo in the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. I have argued a <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Knowledge,</hi> by <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> in the <hi>Future State;</hi> and I have mentioned ſeveral Inſtances, in which an <hi>Increaſe</hi> thereof may be ſo <hi>Made:</hi> But they are but a <hi>Few</hi> of thoſe very <hi>Many</hi> that I might have <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</hi> And what <hi>Thouſands</hi> of Inſtances the <hi>Other World</hi> may preſent unto the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> for the <hi>Augmentation</hi> of it, in that manner, who can aſſure us? What Bodies of Science may be raiſed from them, who can divine? Perhaps each ſingle Inſtance, and Particular, may miniſter Subject for a large and ample <hi>Science.</hi> And where thoſe Inſtances are innumerable, who can fix Bounds to the Increaſe of <hi>Knowledge</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; or ſay, Thus far may it proceed, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:62928:58"/>no farther? Or, what Improbability is there in the Eternal <hi>Progreſs</hi> of it?</p>
            <p n="26">26. 'Tis certain, the <hi>Mind</hi> of Man was made for the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> is known by his <hi>Works;</hi> and 'tis as certain, that the ſeveral <hi>Virtues, Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of thoſe <hi>Works,</hi> are not equally <hi>Obvious:</hi> ſome are more <hi>Evident</hi> and <hi>Apparent;</hi> others lie more in the <hi>Dark,</hi> and are more ſecret from Obſervation. Thus 'tis in <hi>This State,</hi> and thus it may be in <hi>That</hi> which is to <hi>Come.</hi> Here we proceed, and <hi>Argue</hi> the Nature of things <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown,</hi> from thoſe that are <hi>Known;</hi> and ſo may the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> do <hi>Hereafter,</hi> for ought that I do ſee to the contrary. The <hi>Mind</hi> of Man takes a great deal of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in arguing <hi>One</hi> thing from <hi>Another,</hi> whil'ſt Below; and it may be, that it may <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue</hi> ſo to do <hi>Above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. The <hi>Other World</hi> will not <hi>Abate,</hi> much leſs <hi>Aboliſh,</hi> the <hi>Regular</hi> Inclinations of the Humane <hi>Mind;</hi> but Perfect and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large them. The Inclination to <hi>Know,</hi> yea, and to know by <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> ſeems to me <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Eſſential</hi> to the <hi>Soul;</hi> and if ſo, it can no more put it off, than it can put off its Being. The Kingdom of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> (I humbly ſuppoſe) will very much <hi>Inlarge</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> its <hi>Diſcurſive</hi> Power
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62928:59"/>and Inclinations; it will make the Uſe and Exerciſe of it, more <hi>Facile, Pleaſant,</hi> and <hi>Succeſsful;</hi> but will not <hi>Aboliſh</hi> or <hi>Deſtroy</hi> it. An <hi>Intellectual Finite</hi> Being, without the Power and Uſe of <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> ſeems to me a <hi>Paradox,</hi> or rather a <hi>Contradiction.</hi> That a Limited Underſtanding ſhould be able to know any thing, unleſs the Firſt <hi>Principles</hi> of things, and ſome <hi>Objects</hi> of Senſe; yea, or do any thing worthy of <hi>God,</hi> or it ſelf, without <hi>Ratiocination;</hi> ſeems alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Improbable, if not Impoſſible. But of <hi>This</hi> I have ſpoken already, as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p n="28">28. A Limited Underſtanding cannot <hi>Know</hi> all things at <hi>Once;</hi> it muſt receive the Knowledge of them <hi>Succeſſively.</hi> And foraſmuch as there is a <hi>Dependance</hi> and <hi>Connexion</hi> among <hi>Beings,</hi> and <hi>One</hi> follows upon, and oftentimes derives from <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 'tis very probable, that ſuch will be the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them; and that the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of underſtanding them, will be ſuch as is their <hi>Manner</hi> of <hi>Being; i. e.</hi> One <hi>Thing</hi> will be inferred and deduced from <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> which is an Exerciſe of the <hi>Diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> Faculty. Beſides, if any thing be known by its <hi>Effects,</hi> (of which, I think, there is no doubt) in the <hi>Future World,</hi> there muſt be the Uſe of <hi>Ratiocination:</hi> For from
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62928:59"/>the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Qualities</hi> of the <hi>Effects,</hi> to determine the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> is to reaſon and argue from what is <hi>Obvious</hi> and <hi>Eaſie,</hi> to that which is <hi>Dark</hi> and <hi>Difficult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">29. Again, Is it worthy, or doth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Rational</hi> Creature, to act, or do any thing for which he can give no <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count?</hi> Is it congruous and decorous, for <hi>Intellectual</hi> Eſſences to act like <hi>Natural</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, or like Brutes? Such is their <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of acting, if they act without <hi>Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and Diſcourſe. Is that Obedience and Worſhip <hi>Worthy</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that is <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational,</hi> and performed without any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Exerciſe of the <hi>Reaſonable</hi> Faculty? Or is it poſſible, that <hi>Worſhip, Love,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> can be performed without it? Is that Worſhip or Love, is that Service or <hi>Obedience,</hi> that hath no <hi>Conſideration</hi> of the Excellency, Goodneſs, or Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of it? I know not what it may <hi>Seem,</hi> or <hi>Appear</hi> to others; but I muſt acknowledge, I am of <hi>Contrary</hi> Apprehenſions; and do think, that all Obedience and Love to <hi>God,</hi> proceeds from <hi>Ratiocination;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that 'tis of Uſe for the <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> as well as for the producing of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> in the <hi>Other World.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:62928:60"/>
            <p n="30">30. I have hitherunto ſuppoſed a <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity</hi> of <hi>Worlds,</hi> for the making an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> Increaſe of <hi>Knowledge</hi> among the <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> a thing probable, and ſuch as hath ſome <hi>Appearance</hi> of Truth in it: And I do confeſs, I cannot poſſibly reconcile my Mind to an Opinion, That from all <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> nothing was made or produced by <hi>God,</hi> till the <hi>Preſent World;</hi> the <hi>Annals</hi> of whoſe <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Duration,</hi> are left us by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and other <hi>Inſpired</hi> Authors; and ſince them, by <hi>Others:</hi> and the whole Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of its <hi>Continuation,</hi> amounts not to <hi>Six Thouſand</hi> Years.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Nevertheleſs, I will here add, That I know not whether there be any <hi>Need</hi> of it. Peradventure, the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Affairs</hi> of <hi>This VVorld,</hi> together with the great <hi>Variety</hi> of Beings that are in it, and that of the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the more Illuſtrious <hi>Creatures</hi> that are There, may miniſter Matter for <hi>Eternal</hi> Contemplation, and an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> thereby: For how <hi>Many</hi> and <hi>Numerous</hi> they are, and what vaſt <hi>Syſtems</hi> of <hi>Science</hi> may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from them, who is able to inform us? If the Concluſions that we make from ſome <hi>Few</hi> Principles, in this State of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> and <hi>Imperfection,</hi> be ſo <hi>Numerous,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Infinite,</hi> what may they be in that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62928:60"/>State of <hi>Light,</hi> and very <hi>Great</hi> Perfection?</p>
            <p n="32">32. For as I think it <hi>Probable,</hi> that the Knowledge and Happineſs of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> is Progreſſive; ſo I do eaſily and willingly grant, that it <hi>Receives</hi> very great <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> and <hi>Increaſe</hi> immediately upon their Admiſſion into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Heaven:</hi> And I do farther grant, that their Powers and Capacities will be very much <hi>Enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>Perfected,</hi> yea, and made more <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and fit for <hi>Ratiocination:</hi> They will much more <hi>Eaſily</hi> make Inferences from <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Premiſes,</hi> than they would do as long as they were in this <hi>VVeak</hi> and <hi>Imperfect</hi> State; and conſequently, enlarge the <hi>Bounds</hi> and <hi>Extent</hi> of <hi>Science</hi> exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. And how far they may be able to extend them, I cannot conjecture; but I think it may be done <hi>Indefinitely,</hi> if not <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">33. Theſe things I have ſuggeſted, to make it fairly <hi>Probable,</hi> that the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in the <hi>Future State,</hi> may <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> by <hi>Ratiocination:</hi> What <hi>Force</hi> or <hi>Weight</hi> there may be in them, I muſt leave to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Reader;</hi> and here Conclude <hi>This Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:62928:61"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VIII. Objections</hi> againſt the <hi>Doctrine</hi> delivered in the Precedent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, briefly Anſwered.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I Am not ignorant, that the <hi>Opinion</hi> that I have aſſerted in the preceding <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> is liable to ſundry <hi>Objections:</hi> And 'tis no wonder; for there is almoſt nothing in any Part of <hi>Science,</hi> either <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> or <hi>Theological,</hi> which hath not been aſſaulted by them. Some Men have made <hi>Objections</hi> againſt the Being and Providence of <hi>God;</hi> others againſt the Poſſibility of <hi>Motion,</hi> and the Certainty of <hi>Senſe:</hi> And if <hi>Objections</hi> have been made againſt things ſo <hi>Plain</hi> to all the <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Senſe</hi> of the World, it may not be expected, that a thing ſo much in the Dark, as what I have diſcourſed, ſhould be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterly Free</hi> from them. This <hi>Chapter</hi> therefore ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in making ſome <hi>Anſwer</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 1. <hi>Object.</hi> The <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> ſpeak
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62928:61"/>of the <hi>Future State,</hi> as a State of <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Preſent</hi> Perfection; and all <hi>Divines,</hi> when they make mention of it, repreſent it as a <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Perfect State:</hi> To which no <hi>Addition</hi> can be made; but is at its utmoſt  <hi>Exaltation,</hi> as ſoon as ever we be admitted into it. To this <hi>Objection</hi> I have ſundry things to Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 1. I do eaſily grant, that ſome (yea, many) <hi>Divines</hi> may have ſpoken very much to the <hi>Senſe</hi> of this <hi>Objection:</hi> But among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> eſpecially thoſe that are of <hi>Free</hi> Judgments, 'tis not the <hi>Dogmatical</hi> Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Divines,</hi> but the <hi>Evidence</hi> and <hi>Proof</hi> of what they do affirm, that doth <hi>Convince,</hi> and make their Doctrine <hi>Worthy</hi> of Credit and Belief. So that, unleſs they have <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> as well as <hi>Aſſerted,</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this <hi>Objection,</hi> I am not obliged to believe, or give Aſſent unto it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 2. But I would diſtinguiſh of <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> There is an <hi>Abſolute,</hi> and there is a <hi>Relative</hi> Perfection The <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel-Diſpenſation,</hi> are <hi>Perfect</hi> in a <hi>Relative</hi> Senſe, and compared with thoſe that lived under the <hi>Law;</hi> and ſo are <hi>Grown</hi> Chriſtians compared with thoſe that are <hi>Weak,</hi> and (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> expreſſes it) <hi>Babes in Chriſt.</hi> And in one of theſe <hi>Comparative</hi> Senſes, muſt the word <hi>Perfect</hi> be meant;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62928:62"/>1 Cor. 2.6. <hi>Howbeit we ſpeak Wiſdom among them that are Perfect.</hi> In an abſolute Senſe, neither <hi>Chriſtians</hi> compared with <hi>Jews,</hi> nor Strong <hi>Chriſtians</hi> compared with <hi>Weak</hi> ones, are <hi>Perfect;</hi> but in a <hi>Relative</hi> Senſe, they are ſo. And ſo the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> as ſoon as they are admitted the Gates of the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> are Perfect in a <hi>Relative</hi> Senſe; and in compariſon of thoſe they have left <hi>Behind</hi> them in <hi>This World,</hi> and of what they themſelves were when they dwelt <hi>Here</hi> below. And in this <hi>Relative</hi> Senſe, muſt we underſtand the word <hi>Perfect;</hi> Heb. 12.23. <hi>And to the Spirits of Juſt Men made Perfect;</hi> and others of like importance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 3. <hi>Perfection</hi> may be conſidered with <hi>Reſpect</hi> to <hi>Sin,</hi> and it may be conſidered with <hi>Reſpect</hi> to all <hi>Attainable Excellencies,</hi> that <hi>Humane</hi> Nature or Mankind are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of. In the firſt <hi>Senſe,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are Perfect; as ſoon as they get to <hi>Heaven,</hi> they are perfectly <hi>Free</hi> from all <hi>Sin,</hi> both of <hi>Inclination, Habit,</hi> and <hi>Act;</hi> the Plague of the <hi>Heart</hi> is perfectly cured; there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains not any thing of the <hi>Old Nature</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>Souls;</hi> yea, they are freed of all <hi>Sinful</hi> Ignorance: they know all that is <hi>Their Duty</hi> to know, and all that is <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> for the Performance of it. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they <hi>Know</hi> all that ever they ſhall
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62928:62"/>
               <hi>Know,</hi> or are <hi>Capable</hi> of <hi>Knowing,</hi> is <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Queſtion. <hi>God made Man upright,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 7. <hi>ult.</hi> That is, He made him without Sinful Imperfection: But that they knew as much the firſt <hi>Day</hi> of their <hi>Creation,</hi> as they would have <hi>Known,</hi> had they lived a <hi>Thouſand</hi> Years in their <hi>Innocent</hi> State, I do not believe. Our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> was <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> with reſpect to Sin, at his <hi>Birth;</hi> yet He had not then <hi>Attained</hi> all attainable <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies:</hi> for He increaſed in <hi>Wiſdom and Stature, and in Favour with God and Men,</hi> Luk 2.52. And if our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and our <hi>Firſt</hi> Parents were <hi>Perfect,</hi> before they had attained all the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> they were capable of; ſo may the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in the <hi>Future State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. 4. Thoſe very Perſons, that do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the <hi>Perfection</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon their <hi>Departure</hi> hence, and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Glory;</hi> do yet acknowledge, that the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> will add ſomething to the <hi>Increaſe</hi> of their <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> yea, and of their <hi>Happineſs</hi> alſo: And 'tis a thing ſo plain, that it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed. Will the <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> know no more after the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> than they did before? Will thoſe Works of <hi>Wonder</hi> add nothing to the <hi>Enlargement</hi> of their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings?</hi> Will their <hi>Knowledge</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62928:63"/>no Advange thereby? This were a manifeſt <hi>Contradiction,</hi> in any Man that ſhould affirm it. So then, I hope, I may conclude, That if <hi>Perfection</hi> be reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> before the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> it may be reconcileable with it afterwards.</p>
            <p n="7">7. 5. To what hath been ſaid, I may add, That the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> (without doubt) were made Perfect: Yet ſurely, the <hi>Creation, Government,</hi> and <hi>Affairs,</hi> ot <hi>This World,</hi> hath <hi>Added</hi> much to their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: That they have been <hi>Imployed</hi> in them, and conſequently have had <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of them, the <hi>Scriptures</hi> do aſſure us; and I am paſt all <hi>Scruple</hi> concerning it: Yea, I am inclin'd to think, that this <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior</hi> World was made for the Uſe of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> as well as Men; and in it they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the moſt <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Perfections</hi> of their <hi>Maker:</hi> an have <hi>Learned</hi> very many <hi>Things</hi> from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of it: Yea, 'tis my Opinion, that they have aſcribed much more of the <hi>Praiſe</hi> thereof to <hi>God,</hi> than ever was done by <hi>Mortals.</hi> The Creation and Providence of <hi>God,</hi> are a very <hi>Clear</hi> Glaſs, in which are diſcovered the <hi>Attributes</hi> and <hi>Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> But ſince the <hi>Fall,</hi> Man's <hi>Eyes</hi> have been ſo <hi>Impaired,</hi> that they could not
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:62928:63"/>diſcern them, nor give him the <hi>Praiſe</hi> of them. But that which I would infer from this Paragraph, is this: If an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of Knowledge be conſiſtent with Perfection in <hi>Angels,</hi> it may be conſiſtent with it in the <hi>Bleſſed Saints:</hi> If the one were <hi>Perfect</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had obtained much of that <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> that now they are poſſeſſed with; the other may be <hi>Perfect</hi> in the ſame Senſe, though they want much of that <hi>Knowledge,</hi> that they may, and certainly will obtain.</p>
            <p n="8">8. 2. <hi>Object.</hi> The <hi>Future State</hi> is a State of <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Fruition; The Bleſſed are there ſaid to reſt from their Labours, and their Works to follow them,</hi> Rev. 14.13. which ſeems inconſiſtent with an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, foraſmuch as <hi>Knowledge</hi> is not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without <hi>Labour;</hi> eſpecially that which comes by <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our <hi>Reaſon</hi> on ſuch <hi>Beings</hi> as are preſented to us. To this <hi>Objection</hi> I reply as followeth.</p>
            <p n="9">9. 1. The Soul of Man is a very <hi>Active</hi> Being: Action is of the very <hi>Eſſence</hi> of it; and can no more (in my Apprehenſion) be <hi>Separated</hi> from it, than <hi>Heat</hi> from Fire, or <hi>Extenſion</hi> from Natural Bodies. If you ſeparate <hi>Action</hi> from Humane <hi>Minds,</hi> you <hi>Deſtroy</hi> them: If they do <hi>Nothing,</hi> they are <hi>Nothing.</hi> Not to <hi>Act,</hi> and not to <hi>Be,</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:62928:64"/>are the ſame thing with them: The Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of their <hi>Being,</hi> is equipollent to the Ceſſation of their <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Operation. God</hi> is a <hi>Pure</hi> Act; Souls are his <hi>Image;</hi> and in the <hi>Activity</hi> of their <hi>Nature,</hi> they are a <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of Him.</p>
            <p n="10">10. 2. The Reſt of the <hi>Humane</hi> Soul therefore (as I do humbly conceive) conſiſts very much in the Performance of ſuch <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and the Uſe of ſuch <hi>Imployments,</hi> as are congruous and ſuitable to its <hi>Nature,</hi> and to the End and Intent for which it was made. Man's Inferior Faculties and Senſes have their proper Ends, Actions, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations; and in the Exerciſe and Uſe of them, on their own peculiar Objects, they find and experience all the <hi>Content</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> that they are capable of. And ſurely, the <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Soul, muſt likewiſe <hi>Conſiſt</hi> in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of its <hi>Active Powers,</hi> upon <hi>Congruous</hi> and <hi>Suitable Objects.</hi> And the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſome where places <hi>Humane</hi> Felicity in <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and not in a <hi>Dull Inactive</hi> Stupor.</p>
            <p n="11">11. 3. There is nothing more <hi>Suitable,</hi> and <hi>Agreeable</hi> to the <hi>Humane</hi> Soul, than the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of its Intellectual Faculty on the <hi>Being, Nature,</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of things. This is <hi>Wonderfully</hi> Congruous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pleaſant</hi> to it: It delights to conſider
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62928:64"/>the <hi>Nature</hi> of things; and from thoſe things that are more evident, to <hi>Infer</hi> thoſe that are leſs; and alſo from the Effect, to <hi>Infer</hi> the Cauſe; and from the Intermedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate <hi>Cauſes,</hi> to <hi>Aſcend</hi> by ſeveral <hi>Steps</hi> and <hi>Progreſſions,</hi> to the Firſt <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Cauſe</hi> of all things. This <hi>Labour</hi> is its <hi>Rest,</hi> this <hi>Work</hi> is its <hi>Reward;</hi> this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of its Powers, is their <hi>Felicity,</hi> and their <hi>Glory:</hi> This is the <hi>Imployment</hi> which they do deſire; in which they are pleaſed, and in which they will find <hi>Repoſe,</hi> yea, <hi>Raviſhment</hi> and <hi>Extaſies</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p n="12">12. 4. Though the Mind of Man finds ſome <hi>Difficulty</hi> in the obtaining of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge here Below,</hi> and though it coſts <hi>It</hi> much <hi>Painful</hi> Study, to attain any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Degree</hi> or <hi>Meaſure</hi> of it; yet I ſee no Reaſon to conclude, or ſuſpect any ſuch thing in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Heaven.</hi> It will receive ſo much Inlargement, Perfection, and Advantage by its <hi>Aſcent</hi> thither, that 'twill be no more Trouble to advance in <hi>Knowledge,</hi> than 'tis for us to turn <hi>Our Eyes</hi> from one <hi>Object</hi> to another, and to obſerve the <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Proportions</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="13">13. 5. A <hi>Diſeaſed</hi> Eye cannot behold the <hi>Light,</hi> without ſome Trouble and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; though it be the <hi>Proper</hi> Object thereof, and the <hi>Medium</hi> by which all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62928:65"/>things become Viſible; yet if it be <hi>Sore,</hi> it becomes very <hi>Offenſive</hi> unto it; and if you can but cure or remove that <hi>Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Light</hi> becomes <hi>Pleaſant</hi> unto it again. Since Man became <hi>Sinful,</hi> his Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Faculty</hi> hath ſuffered great <hi>Diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> 'tis <hi>Indiſpoſed</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncapable,</hi> in great degree, of obtaining <hi>Knowledge,</hi> (though that were the End for which it was created) and what it doth obtain, is not without <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> and <hi>Difficulty</hi> of Endeavour: But as ſoon as it enters the Gate of the <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem,</hi> this <hi>Indiſpoſition</hi> and <hi>Impotence</hi> will be removed; and, with great Facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it will Contemplate the <hi>Nature</hi> of things, and increaſe in <hi>Knowledge</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
            <p n="14">14. 3. <hi>Object.</hi> If <hi>Knowledge</hi> be capable of <hi>Everlaſting Increaſe,</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> to come, then the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are never <hi>Happy;</hi> for a Capacity of <hi>Increaſe</hi> therein, ſuppoſes <hi>Want,</hi> and a deſire of <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> and where there is <hi>Want,</hi> and an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſatisfied</hi> Appetite, there is no <hi>Perfect</hi> Happineſs: all <hi>Deſire</hi> being painful; and if <hi>Preſſing,</hi> 'tis very <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſie</hi> and <hi>Tormerting.</hi> To this <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> I Anſwer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the following Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs.</p>
            <p n="15">15. 1. This <hi>Objection</hi> preſſes all that believe the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> as well as me.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:62928:65"/>Thoſe that do affirm it, and ſome <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> thereby, (as all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do, or ought to do) and that <hi>Separate Souls</hi> do deſire that <hi>Very Happy</hi> Day, are as much <hi>Obliged</hi> to Anſwer this <hi>Objection,</hi> and reconcile it to their <hi>Own</hi> Doctrine; as I am bound to do it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile it to <hi>Mine.</hi> They affirm, That <hi>Souls</hi> are Happy <hi>Immediately</hi> upon their departure hence; and yet that they do deſire the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and are capable of <hi>Increaſing</hi> Knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. And if <hi>Deſire</hi> and <hi>Want</hi> be conſiſtent with <hi>Happineſs</hi> before the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> I hope it may be <hi>Conſiſtent</hi> with it afterwards. And if they will <hi>Anſwer</hi> the <hi>Objection,</hi> as it oppoſes their <hi>Doctrine;</hi> I will take their <hi>Arguments,</hi> (if they be good) and thereby <hi>Defend</hi> my own.</p>
            <p n="16">16. 2. But I am not ſatisfied, that all <hi>Want, Appetite,</hi> and <hi>Deſire</hi> of Satisfaction, is <hi>Painful</hi> or <hi>Tormenting.</hi> No doubt, the Bleſſed <hi>Deſire</hi> the Continuation of the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and <hi>Happineſs,</hi> that they do poſſeſs and enjoy: They <hi>Deſire</hi> always to ſee the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>His Chriſt,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in the <hi>Quire,</hi> and Communion of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels:</hi> They deſire always to <hi>Love</hi> Him, and be <hi>Beloved</hi> of Him. Yet I do not think thoſe Deſires <hi>Troubleſome</hi> or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:62928:66"/>
               <hi>Tormenting:</hi> Their Happineſs receives no <hi>Abatement</hi> or <hi>Diminution</hi> by them. They do very well agree, and dwell together: Nor is there any <hi>Quarrel</hi> or <hi>Conteſts</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
            <p n="17">17. 3. The <hi>State</hi> to which they are <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> advanced, is ſo exceeding <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> in it ſelf, and alſo in compariſon of <hi>That</hi> which they <hi>Lately</hi> left, and the much <hi>Worſe</hi> that they had deſerved, that it <hi>Abundantly</hi> pleaſes and delights them. He that is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from a <hi>Priſon,</hi> or a <hi>Dungeon,</hi> and had deſerved the <hi>Gallows,</hi> or the <hi>Block,</hi> and ſet upon a <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> and made a <hi>Mighty Prince;</hi> hath ſufficient reaſon of <hi>Joy, Satisfaction,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> though he be not the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Prince upon Earth: 'Tis no juſt Occaſion of Trouble to him, if there be ſome that are <hi>Greater</hi> than he; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if there be a Poſſibility of <hi>Increaſing</hi> his Empire, and becoming <hi>Equally</hi> Great with the Greateſt of them.</p>
            <p n="18">18. 4. The <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> 'tis true, are not ſo <hi>Perfect</hi> in <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Happineſs,</hi> as ſoon as they enter the <hi>Gates</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as thoſe that have ſpent many <hi>Years</hi> and <hi>Ages</hi> There: But 'tis ſo much <hi>Better,</hi> than the Condition in which they lived upon Earth, among <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Sorrows, Vexations</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections:</hi> 'Tis ſo much <hi>Better,</hi> than the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:62928:66"/>
               <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Damned,</hi> with whom they had <hi>Deſerved</hi> to dwell, that they have <hi>Reaſon</hi> of great <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Triumph;</hi> eſpecially when they conſider, that their <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> is Progreſſive, and will <hi>Advance</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p n="19">19. 5. Beſides, we may not imagine, that the <hi>Appetites</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> are <hi>Fierce</hi> and <hi>Raging:</hi> Though they deſire an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of <hi>Knowledge, Happineſs,</hi> and <hi>Perfection;</hi> yet 'tis with great <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Calmneſs.</hi> Their Deſires are not <hi>Trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> or <hi>Tormenting,</hi> for as much as they are <hi>Immediately</hi> ſatisfied: No ſooner do they <hi>Hunger</hi> or <hi>Thirſt,</hi> than they do <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> Satisfaction. <hi>Eternal</hi> Hunger is no Infelicity, where there are <hi>Perpetual</hi> Objects to <hi>Quiet</hi> and <hi>Allay</hi> it.</p>
            <p n="20">20. 6. Nay, peradventure, <hi>Heaven</hi> were not a State of Happineſs, if there were <hi>No Deſires</hi> There: The Soul would <hi>Languiſh,</hi> if Deſire did not <hi>Actuate</hi> and <hi>Enliven</hi> it. The Happineſs of <hi>Rational Spirits</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Action,</hi> as I have before obſerved; and <hi>Appetites</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> are the Spring of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. So that <hi>Perpetual Action,</hi> produced by <hi>Perpetual Deſires,</hi> and thoſe Deſires <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually</hi> ſatisfied, perhaps may <hi>Compound</hi> much of the Happineſs of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. 4. <hi>Object.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays. 1 Cor. 13.9, 10, 11, 12.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:62928:67"/>That whil'ſt we are in this World, <hi>We Know but in part, and Prophecy but in part: But when that which is perfect is come, that which is in part ſhall be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly, but then Face to Face: Now I know but in part, but then ſhall I know as I am known.</hi> Theſe Expreſſions ſeem to aſſert a Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> and that <hi>Immediately</hi> upon their Entrance into <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> For what elſe means that Phraſe; <hi>When that which is Perfect is come;</hi> and that, <hi>But then Face to Face;</hi> and that, <hi>Then ſhall I know as I am known?</hi> To which may be added thoſe words, 1 Joh. 3 2. <hi>We ſhall ſee Him as He is.</hi> To this <hi>Objection</hi> I ſhall not need to ſay much; what I have ſaid in Anſwer to the <hi>Firſt Objection,</hi> being enough to take off the <hi>Force</hi> of it: To which, nevertheleſs, I add as followeth.</p>
            <p n="22">22. 1. The <hi>Perfection</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks of, is only <hi>Relative,</hi> (as I do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuppoſe) for that ſome <hi>Increaſe</hi> is made to the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> after their Admiſſion into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> cannot be denyed; and I think, I have ſaid <hi>Enough</hi> to prove it.</p>
            <p n="23">23. 2. That Expreſſion of ſeeing <hi>Face to Face,</hi> is <hi>Figurative</hi> and <hi>Metaphorical;</hi> and, I think, means no more, than a <hi>Much
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:62928:67"/>Clearer</hi> Knowledge of things, than was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in <hi>This World:</hi> But a Knowledge <hi>Abſolutely</hi> and <hi>Compleatly</hi> Perfect, and ſuch as receives no <hi>Increaſe,</hi> is (I conceive) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> thing, and more than is <hi>Meant,</hi> or can be <hi>Proved</hi> from this Expreſſion.</p>
            <p n="24">24. 3. Thoſe Expreſſions of <hi>Knowing as Known,</hi> and <hi>Seeing God as He is,</hi> are (I conceive) alſo <hi>Figurative,</hi> and not to be underſtood in the <hi>Proper</hi> Senſe of the Words: For no Man can know <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Great</hi> things There, ſo <hi>Fully</hi> and <hi>Perfectly</hi> as <hi>God</hi> knows them: Nor ſhall any Man ſee <hi>God</hi> as He is, if thereby be meant <hi>Fully</hi> and <hi>Perfectly;</hi> for a <hi>Limited</hi> Underſtanding cannot fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend an <hi>Infinite</hi> Eſſence. All that can be <hi>Meant</hi> by it, I think, is this: In <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> ſhall have <hi>Clearer</hi> Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of <hi>God,</hi> and all <hi>Things</hi> There, than in <hi>This World</hi> they had; and ſhall <hi>Know God,</hi> and Them, as truly (though not ſo fully) as He <hi>Knows</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="25">25. 4. Beſides, thoſe words of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Objection,</hi> may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in a <hi>Tranſient</hi> and <hi>Progreſſive Senſe.</hi> The <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are in a State, in which they <hi>Know</hi> much, and are in Progreſs towards a <hi>More Perfect</hi> Knowledge: There is no
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:62928:68"/>need of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding Them</hi> of <hi>Immediate</hi> Perfection, as ſoon as received to <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Some <hi>Corollaries</hi> deduced from the Preceding Diſcourſes.</head>
            <p>HAving made ſome <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Objections,</hi> that are, or may be made to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> propoſed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going <hi>Chapters;</hi> I ſhall add ſome few <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences,</hi> or <hi>Deductions,</hi> from the Whole of what hath been ſaid, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Happineſs of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſive and Increaſing: 'Tis not a thing <hi>Fixed, Steddy,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncapable</hi> of any <hi>Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation:</hi> It doth not change or vary indeed for the <hi>Worſe,</hi> or to their <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage;</hi> but it changes to their <hi>Benefit</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> exceedingly. 'Tis like a <hi>Riſing Sun,</hi> that ſhines <hi>More</hi> bright by its Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Alteration. 'Tis an <hi>Eternal</hi> Spring. 'Tis an <hi>Everlaſting</hi> May: The Beauty and Verdure of it, <hi>Increaſes</hi> continually. We cannot ſay of the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> in
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:62928:68"/>Glory, <hi>Hitherunto</hi> ſhall it <hi>Proceed,</hi> and <hi>Here</hi> ſhall it <hi>Determine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For Love will <hi>Increaſe</hi> with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; the <hi>One</hi> will make <hi>Equal</hi> Progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with the <hi>Other:</hi> They will go <hi>Hand</hi> in <hi>Hand,</hi> and the <hi>One</hi> advance with the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The <hi>More</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Advance in the Knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>More</hi> will they <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> in Love to Him; the more <hi>Lively, Vigorous, Paſſionate,</hi> and <hi>Raviſhing</hi> will it be towards Him. The <hi>More</hi> they Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate his Works, and <hi>Obſerve</hi> of his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable</hi> Perfections in them, the <hi>More</hi> will they be in <hi>Love</hi> with Him, and the <hi>Greater</hi> will be their <hi>Eſteem</hi> for Him, and <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Love</hi> is <hi>Always</hi> accompanied with <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Delight:</hi> Thus we find it <hi>Now,</hi> and ſo 'twill be <hi>Hereafter.</hi> The <hi>Love</hi> that Men <hi>Bear</hi> to their <hi>Friends,</hi> their <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> yea, to their <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Luſts,</hi> miniſters <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> to them; and can the Bleſſed <hi>Love God,</hi> the <hi>Supreme</hi> Good, and <hi>Chiefest</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and not find <hi>Conſolation</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> therein? Can they <hi>Love</hi> the <hi>God</hi> that <hi>Made</hi> them, and the <hi>Saviour</hi> that <hi>Redeemed</hi> them from <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Raiſed</hi> and <hi>Exalted</hi> them to <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Glory;</hi> and find no <hi>Tranſports</hi> therein? Can they <hi>Love,</hi> and that with <hi>Vigorous</hi> Affection, and have no Senſe
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:62928:69"/>of <hi>Joy</hi> therein? Surely, <hi>That</hi> is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Great <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> will expreſs it ſelf in Enlargedneſs of <hi>Thanks</hi> and <hi>Praiſe.</hi> How will the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Triumph in the <hi>Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> and how <hi>Abundant</hi> will they be in <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> to Him? They will love Him <hi>Greatly,</hi> and therefore they will praiſe Him <hi>Much;</hi> they are full of <hi>Joy,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will <hi>Expreſs</hi> their Gratitude with ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Continued Hallelujahs. Active</hi> Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are incapable of <hi>Reſtraint</hi> or <hi>Incloſure;</hi> and therefore will <hi>Break</hi> out in Songs of <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Much of the <hi>Happineſs</hi> and <hi>Felicity</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> will conſiſt in the Exerciſe of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Delight</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> and the aſcribing of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> to Him. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge will <hi>Generate</hi> Love, and Love will <hi>Excite, Awaken,</hi> and <hi>Stir</hi> up Praiſe; and theſe will conſtitute <hi>Their</hi> Happineſs in a <hi>Good</hi> degree. <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Objective</hi> Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> His Excellencies do preſent themſelves to their <hi>View</hi> and <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration;</hi> they <hi>Know</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> them, they <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Delight</hi> in them, and are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in the <hi>Praiſes</hi> of them: And in <hi>Theſe</hi> their <hi>Subjective</hi> Happineſs doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:62928:69"/>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will never <hi>Want</hi> Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Matter for <hi>Everlaſting</hi> Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will be <hi>Preſented</hi> to them, by which their Knowledge will be <hi>Increaſed;</hi> and with the <hi>Increaſe</hi> of Knowledge, an <hi>Increaſe</hi> of Affection; and <hi>Conſequently,</hi> of grateful Adoration. And thus will they be <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed</hi> for evermore: The Days of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will be <hi>Thus</hi> conſummate: <hi>Thus</hi> will the Inhabitants of the <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem</hi> paſs their time, and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> themſelves to all Durations. <hi>Heaven</hi> is no <hi>Inactive</hi> State; the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> There are <hi>Perpetually</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; and in that <hi>Imployment,</hi> they find <hi>Their</hi> Reſt. Idleneſs is no Pleaſure to <hi>Such</hi> Beings, whoſe Natures are <hi>Active</hi> by their <hi>Very</hi> Conſtitution: And ſuch is that of our <hi>Faculties,</hi> (as I have obſerved before) and in Action <hi>Suitable</hi> to it. And upon the moſt <hi>Raiſed</hi> and <hi>Glorious</hi> Objects, conſiſts <hi>Their</hi> Happineſs: <hi>There</hi> it is, and <hi>There</hi> they may <hi>Find</hi> it; but no where elſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. There will be no <hi>Satiety</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Heaven:</hi> In <hi>This World,</hi> Men are <hi>Satiated,</hi> and ſometimes even <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oathed</hi> with their <hi>Injoyments</hi> and <hi>Fruitions:</hi> Thoſe things which they <hi>Moſt</hi> earneſtly, and <hi>Paſſionately</hi> deſired, and for which they laboured with the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Endeavour, they are oftentimes <hi>ſoon</hi> glutted withal, and ſometimes grow
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:62928:70"/>
               <hi>Weary</hi> of them. But 'twill not be ſo in <hi>Heaven:</hi> No Man will ever be <hi>Over-filled</hi> with knowing <hi>God,</hi> or ſearching out <hi>His</hi> Perfections; and <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>Being</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>Fathomed,</hi> or <hi>Fully</hi> ſearched out: There will be <hi>Something New</hi> to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in <hi>Him</hi> for ever. No man will ever be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red with <hi>Loving God,</hi> or being <hi>Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> of <hi>Him:</hi> No Man will ever be ſurfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Rejoycing</hi> and <hi>Delighting</hi> in Him, or of expreſſing it in <hi>Pſalms</hi> and <hi>Hymns</hi> of <hi>Hallelujah.</hi> The Reaſon why Men are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Cloyed</hi> with their Enjoyments <hi>Here</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, is becauſe they <hi>Find</hi> not that in them they <hi>Expected:</hi> they were <hi>Deceived</hi> by them, and therefore <hi>Grow</hi> into a Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>Againſt</hi> them. But there will be <hi>No ſuch thing</hi> Above. <hi>God</hi> will abundantly <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie</hi> all Expectations: <hi>Heaven</hi> will <hi>Deceive</hi> no Man; they will <hi>There</hi> find <hi>More,</hi> not <hi>Leſs,</hi> than they did expect.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The <hi>Future State</hi> may, <hi>Perhaps,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent us with <hi>New Things</hi> continually, or at leaſt as often as there is <hi>Occaſion</hi> for them. Who knows, but that when-ever the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> have ſufficiently <hi>Conſidered</hi> and <hi>Exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the Beings that are with <hi>Them,</hi> or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to <hi>Them, More</hi> may be propoſed, and ſet <hi>Before</hi> them; or that they may be <hi>Removed</hi> to ſome other Part of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:62928:70"/>to obſerve what is <hi>Worthy</hi> of <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> There? And this <hi>Vaniety</hi> of things and <hi>Objects,</hi> will take away all Poſſibility of an <hi>Offenſive Fulneſs.</hi> In <hi>This State,</hi> few Men are full to <hi>Loathing,</hi> whil'ſt they have continual <hi>Variety</hi> of things in <hi>Enjoyment,</hi> or in <hi>Hopes</hi> and <hi>Proſecution. Variety</hi> of things, keeps up their Expectations; and they do hope to find that in <hi>One</hi> or <hi>More</hi> things, which they have in vain ſought after in <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> In <hi>Heaven</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are <hi>Never</hi> deceived in their Expectation: In all things they ſeek to <hi>Know</hi> ſomething more of <hi>God,</hi> and that they <hi>Find</hi> in them: And when they have <hi>Drained</hi> one, they go to another; and in ſuch <hi>Variety,</hi> there can be no Nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="9">9. An Inequality of <hi>Glory</hi> among the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> is aſſerted by <hi>Many Divines:</hi> And from what hath been ſaid, we may give ſome <hi>Probable</hi> Account, wherein it doth conſiſt. Peradventure, their <hi>Minds</hi> may be of very <hi>Various</hi> Capacities; ſome may be <hi>More Large</hi> and <hi>Extenſive,</hi> than others, if <hi>God</hi> do here <hi>Freely</hi> and <hi>Arbitrarily,</hi> as a Benefactor, give unto Men <hi>Minds</hi> of very different <hi>Capacities,</hi> I know not why he may not do it as a <hi>Judge,</hi> or as the Bountiful <hi>Rewarder</hi> of thoſe that ſerve Him. I am not ignorant, that many <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:62928:71"/>an <hi>Equality</hi> among Souls; and that thoſe Differences that are ſo <hi>Obſervable</hi> in them, proceed from the <hi>Various</hi> Structure, and Conformation of the <hi>Organs,</hi> and Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Elements,</hi> which conſtitute our Bodies. I do eaſily grant, that ſome of the <hi>Differences</hi> obſerved among them, may <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe</hi> from thence; but that <hi>All</hi> do ſo, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe. That there is no Difference between the Soul of the greateſt <hi>Divine, Philoſopher,</hi> or <hi>Stateſman,</hi> and that of the verieſt <hi>Dolt</hi> or <hi>Ideot,</hi> is to me an <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable</hi> Paradox; and I cannot but think, that there is a <hi>Gradual</hi> Difference, at leaſt, among <hi>Souls</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p n="10">10. This Diverſity (I humbly conceive) is found in all the Faculties and Powers of the Soul; I mean, in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will,</hi> and <hi>Active</hi> or <hi>Executive</hi> Power. In all theſe the Difference is <hi>Various,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Men's <hi>Love, Service,</hi> and <hi>Good Works</hi> may have been <hi>Various</hi> Here below. Thoſe that have been moſt <hi>Pious, Holy,</hi> and <hi>Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> in the Works of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> will have the <hi>Largeſt</hi> Underſtandings, the moſt <hi>Vigorous</hi> Affections of Love, Delight, and Joy, and the moſt <hi>Prompt</hi> and <hi>Ready</hi> Power and Method of <hi>Expreſſing</hi> them, in <hi>Such</hi> Ways, and by <hi>Such</hi> Means, as are fit and congruous thereunto. They will know
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:62928:71"/>moſt, and love and rejoyce moſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs this Love and Joy moſt readily in the <hi>Other World,</hi> that ſerved the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Good</hi> of Men moſt <hi>Induſtriouſly</hi> in <hi>This.</hi> They that have been <hi>Moſt</hi> Holy, and lived <hi>Moſt</hi> to the <hi>Acceptation</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Time,</hi> will know Him <hi>Moſt</hi> fully, and love Him <hi>Moſt</hi> paſſionately in <hi>Eternity:</hi> And yet their Knowledge and Love, as well as that of others, may be capable of <hi>Increaſe</hi> and <hi>Augmentation,</hi> as I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed before.</p>
            <p n="11">11. And there may be as great <hi>Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the Bodies, and Bodily <hi>Organs</hi> and <hi>Senſes</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> as there is in their <hi>Minds:</hi> Some may be more <hi>Pure</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> than others; and conſequently, more <hi>Agile</hi> and <hi>Fit</hi> for <hi>Motion:</hi> Some may have their <hi>Senſes,</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Organs</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> thereof, <hi>More Perfect</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat</hi> than <hi>Others;</hi> and conſequently, more <hi>Capable</hi> of apprehending their Objects, and <hi>Perceiving</hi> all the Perfections and Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in them. Some may have a <hi>More Large</hi> and <hi>Extenſive</hi> Preſence, than others; and therefore, be capable of inſpecting at <hi>One View,</hi> more of the Works of <hi>God;</hi> which renders them <hi>More</hi> affecting, and <hi>More</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing. He that ſtands upon a <hi>High</hi> Hill or Turret, beholds <hi>More</hi> things than he
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:62928:72"/>that ſtands in a Valley, and is much <hi>More</hi> pleaſed and delighted therein; yea, is much more raviſhed with Admiration of them.</p>
            <p n="12">12. How great may be the <hi>Variety,</hi> and <hi>Gradual</hi> Difference among the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in theſe things, cannot be determined. Great have been the <hi>Numbers</hi> of Men, that ſince the <hi>Creation,</hi> have dwelt on the <hi>Face</hi> of this <hi>Earth;</hi> and yet, perhaps, there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Two among them, in <hi>All</hi> things, and <hi>Totally</hi> alike. Some Difference in the <hi>Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of the <hi>Elements,</hi> of which they were Compounded, in the <hi>Shape, Figure,</hi> and <hi>Proportion</hi> of their Bodies, in the <hi>Features</hi> of their <hi>Faces,</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> of their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances,</hi> might be ſeen and obſerved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. And as <hi>Various</hi> may be the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the <hi>Glorious</hi> Bodies of the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> The <hi>Starrs</hi> are <hi>Vaſtly</hi> numerous; and yet, perchance, the Difference of their <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> may be as Great as their Number, and that <hi>None</hi> of them are in all things <hi>Alike</hi> and <hi>Equal.</hi> And ſuch may be the <hi>Inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> among the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the <hi>Celeſtial</hi> Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="13">13. And it may be <hi>Modeſtly</hi> ſuppoſed, that the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> may be as <hi>Various</hi> as their <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> are. The more <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:62928:72"/>is, the more <hi>Like</hi> he is to <hi>God;</hi> and certainly, the <hi>More Like</hi> any Creature is to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>More</hi> it is <hi>Beloved</hi> of Him. Why elſe doth <hi>God</hi> deſpiſe the <hi>Heaven, and the Earth,</hi> in compariſon of an <hi>Humble, and Contrite Spirit, and one that trembleth at his Word?</hi> Iſa. 66.1, 2. Is it not becauſe there is <hi>More</hi> of his Image on ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than on the Frame and Fabrick of the <hi>Material</hi> Earth and Heavens? Why doth <hi>God</hi> love, and take more delight in the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> than in <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and all the <hi>Holy</hi> Myriads that are <hi>About</hi> his Throne, (of which, I think, there is no doubt) Is it not for this <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that He is a far more <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Image of his Attributes and Perfections, than <hi>Any</hi> or <hi>All</hi> of them?</p>
            <p n="14">14. How <hi>God</hi> will manifeſt a <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Different</hi> Affection to the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> according to the <hi>Difference</hi> of their <hi>Perfections,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not affirm: Whether he will do it by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> Effuſions of <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Conſolation,</hi> or by <hi>External</hi> Effects and Demonſtrations, or by both, (which ſeems moſt probable) I know not; that's a Queſtion, that I will leave for the <hi>Determination</hi> of the <hi>Other World.</hi> But that <hi>God</hi> can, and doth do it, is paſt doubt with me. He manifeſts a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar</hi> Love to his <hi>Only</hi> Beloved <hi>Son;</hi> and can do ſo to <hi>All</hi> the Members of his Body,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:62928:73"/>in <hi>Several</hi> Meaſures and Proportions.</p>
            <p n="15">15. This great <hi>Variety</hi> of Love and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection will <hi>Cauſe</hi> no Envy or Emulation <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> for they are free of all <hi>Sinful</hi> Paſſions, Affections, and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and do rejoyce in the Effuſions and Manifeſtations of the Love of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Others,</hi> as well as to <hi>Themſelves. Particular</hi> Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages are Matter of <hi>Common</hi> Joy. As <hi>All</hi> the Heavenly Quires do <hi>Rejoyce</hi> in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> ſo do they in the Advantages of <hi>Each</hi> other.</p>
            <p n="16">16. But tho this <hi>Variety</hi> cauſes no Envy or Emulation in <hi>Heaven;</hi> yet methinks, the <hi>Meditation</hi> of it ſhould be a great <hi>Spur</hi> and <hi>Incentive</hi> to <hi>Piety, Virtue,</hi> and <hi>Good Works</hi> here on <hi>Earth.</hi> Certainly, it ought to make us abound in all the <hi>Fruits</hi> of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that ſo we may be capable of the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Manifeſtations of the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> ſince thoſe that are <hi>moſt</hi> Diligent in his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> ſince thoſe that are the <hi>moſt</hi> Pious and Virtuous in <hi>This World,</hi> will be the <hi>moſt</hi> Glorious and Excellent in the <hi>Other;</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>most</hi> Worthy, will be <hi>moſt</hi> Beloved of <hi>God,</hi> and receive the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Evidences and Demonſtrations of his Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: The Conſideration of it ſhould put us upon vigorous Endeavours after a <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> Holineſs and Virtue, that we may be the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:62928:73"/>Objects of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Choice,</hi> and <hi>Peculiar Love</hi> in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. 'Tis a Queſtion controverted among <hi>Divines,</hi> whether the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> have any <hi>Knowledge</hi> of each other, in the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven:</hi> And I humbly conceive, that from what I have ſaid in the <hi>Fore-going</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, 'twill not be <hi>Difficult</hi> to reſolve it. So <hi>Long</hi> a Tract of Time as <hi>Eternity,</hi> may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſundry <hi>Occaſions</hi> and <hi>Opportunities</hi> to <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations,</hi> for the <hi>Knowing</hi> of <hi>Each</hi> other: And ſince 'tis not ſpent in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</hi> and <hi>Retirements,</hi> but in <hi>Mutual</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Society, and <hi>Converſation;</hi> 'tis not poſſible <hi>Almoſt,</hi> that they ſhould eſcape the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of one <hi>Another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. The Memory and Narration of the <hi>Mighty</hi> Works and Providences of <hi>God,</hi> of which they had <hi>Knowledge</hi> in <hi>This World,</hi> will bring Men to the Cognizance of each other <hi>There.</hi> There is a <hi>Twofold</hi> Memory in Man; there is a <hi>Senſitive,</hi> and an <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual</hi> Memory: The <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe depends upon thoſe <hi>Ideas</hi> and <hi>Similitudes</hi> of things, that by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of our Senſes, have been <hi>Impreſſed</hi> upon our <hi>Minds:</hi> The <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> depends of <hi>Such</hi> things, as by <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> are fixed and engraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. The <hi>Firſt</hi> kind of Memory, I think, will be of <hi>Little</hi> or <hi>No <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> in this Caſe.:
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:62928:74"/>For though it ſhould be granted, that it ſhould retain the <hi>Ideas</hi> of things <hi>There;</hi> yet foraſmuch as there is no <hi>Counterpart</hi> of them in the <hi>Things</hi> themſelves, all being oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> and not reſtored by the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> I do not ſee, how the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> can thereby take any <hi>Cognizance</hi> or <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Each Other;</hi> but the Intellectual Memory will be of <hi>Great</hi> Uſe in this Affair. We ſhall <hi>There</hi> remember, that we were born of <hi>Such</hi> and <hi>Such</hi> Parents, and received <hi>Such</hi> and <hi>Such</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions from them; and lived under the Teaching of <hi>Such</hi> and <hi>Such</hi> Preachers, and in the Neighbourhood and Society of <hi>Such</hi> Perſons, Friends, and Acquaintance; with many other things: And the mention of any of them, in the <hi>Mutual</hi> Society and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> will bring them to the <hi>Perſonal Knowledge</hi> of each other.</p>
            <p n="19">19. But beſides this <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>Knowing</hi> each other, there may be ſeveral <hi>Other Ways</hi> of obtaining it; ſuch as the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Angels,</hi> and Bleſſed <hi>Spirits;</hi> they may poſſibly <hi>Inform</hi> ſuch as ſhall come <hi>After</hi> them to the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> who have in the times <hi>Preceding</hi> been admitted Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and where are their <hi>Proper</hi> Manſions and Places of Abode and Reſidence; and perhaps, <hi>Some</hi> Knowledge of each other
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:62928:74"/>may be impreſſed upon the <hi>Minds</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> by <hi>Inſpiration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. But foraſmuch as the <hi>Souls</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are carried hence, and by the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> removed to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and placed in <hi>Manſions</hi> There; peradventure, by the Will of <hi>God,</hi> thoſe that have been allyed either by <hi>Nature, Neighbourhood,</hi> or <hi>Converſation,</hi> may be placed near toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in <hi>That</hi> Houſe of <hi>God;</hi> and then a <hi>Little</hi> Diſcourſe may <hi>Soon</hi> bring them to the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of each other; or the <hi>Angels</hi> may openly, and in the Preſence of <hi>All,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <hi>Who</hi> they have brought Thither, and joyned to their <hi>Society</hi> and <hi>Number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. One thing more I will add to what I have already inferred from the Precedent <hi>Diſcourſe: Eternity</hi> will unfold all the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> of <hi>Divine</hi> Providence. There are <hi>Many</hi> and great <hi>Labyrinths</hi> now in it; and we cannot <hi>Search</hi> them out, nor give any <hi>Account</hi> thereof: But <hi>Eternity</hi> will unvail them, and ſet them <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>Plain</hi> before us. The Wiſdom, Holineſs, Juſtice, Goodneſs, and Truth of <hi>God,</hi> will be <hi>Conſpicuous</hi> in every thing He hath done: All <hi>Objections</hi> will be <hi>Satisfied;</hi> and 'twill <hi>Appear,</hi> that there was nothing of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs</hi> in any of them.</p>
            <p n="22">22. What <hi>Troubled</hi> us to ſee, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:62928:75"/>will be <hi>Pleaſant</hi> to remember, when we have underſtook the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of it. 'Twas <hi>Grievous</hi> to us to have the <hi>Wicked</hi> proſper, and the <hi>Righteous</hi> ſuffer by their Hands. 'Twas an <hi>Affliction</hi> to us, to behold the Church of <hi>God</hi> under <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and the Enemies thereof bringing their <hi>Wicked</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to paſs. But the <hi>Memory</hi> of theſe things will be <hi>Grateful,</hi> when we ſhall be gloriouſly inſtructed in the <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="23">23. And thus I have ſaid <hi>many</hi> things in favour of the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> that in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning I undertood to defend. But I am not <hi>Dogmatical</hi> in what I have ſaid; nor ſhall I be offended with any Man, that is of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Apprehenſions. In things of <hi>This</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I am content that Men think as they pleaſe, or according as their <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhall direct them; which, I am ſure, is <hi>Sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> various. I have taken the Liberty to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt my <hi>Own</hi> Thoughts on this Subject; and I have no deſire to retrench to <hi>Other</hi> Men the Liberty of <hi>Theirs.</hi> If any Man ſhall propoſe any thing <hi>Better,</hi> either in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of this <hi>Opinion,</hi> or in Confutation of it, it ſhall be <hi>Equally</hi> acceptable to me.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:62928:75"/>
            <head>An Appendix.</head>
            <p n="1">1. SInce what I have ſaid in the <hi>Fourth Chapter,</hi> concerning the Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs of the Preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> looks like a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox;</hi> and 'tis poſſible, that thoſe that read it, may be ſtartled: I ſhall add a few Paragraphs, to a farther <hi>Explication</hi> of my Mind about it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis certain, that <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications</hi> have been made to <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in all Ages of the <hi>Chriſtian Church. Chriſtians</hi> have addreſſed themſelves to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> both in their Private and Publick <hi>Devotions.</hi> In all their Needs and Wants, they have applied themſelves to Him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis undeniable, that the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> do give us very great Incouragement to pray before Him, and make known our <hi>Requeſts</hi> unto Him. They aſſure us, that He is a Merciful <hi>High Prieſt;</hi> and ſuch a One, <hi>As is touched with the Feeling of our Infirmities, having been in all Points tempted as we are; and that therefore we may come boldly to the Throne of Grace, to obtain Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and find Grace to help in time of need,</hi> Heb. 4.14, 15.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:62928:76"/>
            <p n="4">4. He himſelf hath promiſed to hear the Prayers that we make before Him: <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you ſhall ask in my Name, that will I do; and if you ask any thing in my Name, I will do it,</hi> Joh. 14.13, 14.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Twas the <hi>Humane</hi> Nature of our <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> that was <hi>Tempted in all things,</hi> as we are; and is therefore compaſſionate, and hath a Senſe and <hi>Feeling</hi> of our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The <hi>Divine Nature</hi> is Merciful, but not becauſe it was <hi>In all things Tempted as we are;</hi> for it is not capable of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 'Tis only the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> that was tempted, and in that Senſe can be ſaid to be Merciful.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Therefore, the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> nath Knowledge of our <hi>Prayers, Wants,</hi> and <hi>Temptations.</hi> How elſe is He touched with a <hi>Feeling</hi> of our <hi>Infirmities?</hi> How elſe doth He <hi>Miniſter Grace to help in time of need?</hi> Or can theſe things be done, without any <hi>Knowledge</hi> of our State, our Needs, or our Supplications?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Either the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> hath an <hi>Immediate Knowledge</hi> of theſe things, or elſe it partakes in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them, by a Communication from the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi> If it be ſaid, That the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> hath an <hi>Immediate Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of them; I infer from thence, the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſiveneſs
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:62928:76"/>of Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Preſence:</hi> For that He ſhould know them <hi>Immediately,</hi> without a large and diffuſive Preſence, is (I think) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and more than is aſſerted of the <hi>Deity</hi> it ſelf; the <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> being founded in the <hi>Immenſity</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nboundedneſs</hi> of His Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p n="8">8. If it be ſaid, That the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of our <hi>Infirmities,</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> by the <hi>Divine;</hi> I do not underſtand, how <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is capable of that <hi>Knowledge,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs his <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and conſequently his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> be of <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Extenſive Nature. Quicquid recipitur, recipitur ad modum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipientis.</hi> The Hills cannot be weighed in <hi>Scales,</hi> nor the Mountains in a Pair of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances;</hi> the Duſt of the Earth cannot be comprehended in a <hi>Meaſure,</hi> nor the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the <hi>Hollow</hi> of a Man's Hand: Nor can a <hi>Created</hi> Underſtanding, (and ſuch is that of the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>) comprehend all the <hi>Needs, Wants,</hi> and <hi>Infirmities</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by whatſoever Ways or Methods they may be Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto it; unleſs you will ſuppoſe it of very <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Extenſive</hi> Preſence and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</p>
            <p n="9">9. So that, if the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of <hi>Chriſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:62928:77"/>Jeſus</hi> have any <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the State and Condition of the <hi>Church,</hi> which is his <hi>Body,</hi> (as I think, can't reaſonably be doubted) whether <hi>Mediately</hi> or <hi>Immediately;</hi> in my Apprehenſion, an <hi>Extenſion</hi> of <hi>Preſence</hi> muſt be granted thereunto. And if it be granted to <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> I know nothing that will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Conceſſion to the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> tho not in the ſame Degree; for in all things he muſt have a <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. But beſides all this, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus is the Head of his Church;</hi> and, as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Cauſe</hi> under <hi>God,</hi> conveys his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> to all the Members of it. As the <hi>Sun</hi> is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Cauſe</hi> of Light, Heat, and Motion in Sublunary Bodies; ſo is <hi>Chriſt</hi> of all <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Influences</hi> and <hi>Virtues,</hi> to the Souls of Men; and there is no other means, or way of Conveyance, but by Him.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of <hi>Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> by its being <hi>Perſonally</hi> united to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> and exalted to <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Right Hand,</hi> is by the Office of <hi>Mediator</hi> Authorized; and by a <hi>Participation</hi> of the <hi>Fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> enabled for the Communication of this <hi>Spiritual Influx,</hi> and <hi>Benediction</hi> to <hi>Humane Minds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Yet it is not to be imagined, or do I affirm, That the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of <hi>Chriſt
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:62928:77"/>Jeſus</hi> is any Cauſe of any <hi>Immanent</hi> Act of the <hi>Divine Spirit;</hi> but He is the Cauſe of the <hi>Spirits Operation,</hi> as that <hi>Operation</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the <hi>Effect</hi> upon the Mind of Man. And of this He is no <hi>Superiour,</hi> but only a <hi>Miniſterial Cauſe,</hi> as a <hi>Prince</hi> rewards the Valour of his Souldiers, as the <hi>General</hi> doth determine it.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Political</hi> Cauſe of this <hi>Spiritual Influence.</hi> He, as <hi>Mediator,</hi> is authorized to determine of the Meaſure, Time, Conditions, and Perſons, that ſhall partake therein. Whether He be alſo a <hi>Phyſical</hi> Head and Cauſe of this Influence and Grace, and by proper <hi>Efficiency</hi> do Communicate of this Spirit, and by any <hi>Phyſical</hi> Operation of his <hi>Humane Soul,</hi> He operate upon <hi>Our Minds;</hi> is a Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that I am not obliged to determine, my Cauſe not requiring it: For if He be only the <hi>Political</hi> Cauſe of this Grace and Spirit, He muſt have Knowledge of the State, Caſe, and Condition of Mankind; and that, in my Opinion, will infer a <hi>Large</hi> and <hi>Extenſive</hi> Preſence; which is all that I am concerned to prove.</p>
            <p>AND now having annexed thus much to the <hi>Book,</hi> in regard to one <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Point;</hi> I ſhall ſuperadd no leſs, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:62928:78"/>to the <hi>General Subject,</hi> for the obvia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome Objections, and preventing Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtandings in what I have <hi>Aſſerted,</hi> or rather <hi>Propoſed</hi> to indifferent Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I would not be thought to <hi>Place</hi> the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Creatures.</hi> Whoever ſhould <hi>Thus</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me, would <hi>Very</hi> much miſtake and miſapprehend me. I <hi>Place</hi> the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and being <hi>Beloved</hi> by Him. The Knowledge of <hi>Creatures,</hi> is only the <hi>Medium</hi> by which we come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Creator;</hi> and by the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of Him, we become capable of <hi>Loving</hi> Him, and <hi>Rejoycing</hi> and <hi>Delighting</hi> in Him. <hi>God</hi> is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimately</hi> the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Man</hi>'s Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity and Love. Delight and Joy are the <hi>Great</hi> Felicitating <hi>Acts;</hi> and both theſe <hi>Compleat,</hi> and make it <hi>Perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. One great <hi>Reaſon</hi> that inclines me to believe, that <hi>Knowledge</hi> will be <hi>Progreſſive</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> to come, is becauſe I do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that <hi>Man</hi> will remain a <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Finite</hi> Eſſence <hi>There;</hi> yea, and <hi>Limited</hi> to that degree, that he will not be <hi>Able</hi> at one Graſp to comprehend the <hi>Nature, Qualities,</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> A great <hi>Enlargement</hi> of Capacity <hi>Immediately</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:62928:78"/>his Departure hence, I do readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede; and if any ſhall pleaſe to call it <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural,</hi> I will have no Conteſt with him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it: But this <hi>Enlargement</hi> (I conceive) will not make his Capacity of <hi>Equal</hi> Extent with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</hi> and conſequently, his <hi>Knowledge</hi> of it, cannot be <hi>Simul</hi> and <hi>Semel,</hi> but Succeſſive.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How <hi>Various</hi> the Limitations of the <hi>Eſſences</hi> and <hi>Capacities</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> will be, I will not affirm: Peradventure, they may be as <hi>Various,</hi> and <hi>Different,</hi> as their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> will be. Thoſe that have <hi>Loved</hi> and <hi>Served God</hi> in <hi>This World,</hi> with the <hi>Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> Sincerity and Vigour of Affection and Endeavour, will have the <hi>Largest</hi> Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the <hi>Other;</hi> they will be capable of knowing <hi>Moſt</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and conſequently, of loving Him <hi>Moſt,</hi> and being <hi>Moſt</hi> belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Him. It ſeems to me (I ſay) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the <hi>Remunerating</hi> Grace of <hi>God,</hi> will <hi>Diverſify</hi> Men's Capacities in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> according to their Works <hi>Here</hi> on <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If any Man ſhould think, that becauſe I affirm an <hi>Alteration</hi> for the better in the <hi>Future State,</hi> that therefore there may be an <hi>Alteration</hi> for the worſe, and to the <hi>Diſadvantage</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> I anſwer, That I ſee <hi>Nothing</hi> in what I have <hi>Said,</hi> that may
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:62928:79"/>give any Reaſon for <hi>Such</hi> an Inference or Concluſion. For why <hi>Confirming</hi> Grace may not ſecure the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> from <hi>Any</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, on Suppoſition, that <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Happineſs,</hi> be Increaſing and Progreſſive, as well as on ſuppoſition, that it be <hi>Inſtantaneouſly</hi> Compleat and Perfect; I confeſs, I do not underſtand.</p>
            <p n="5">5. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I do acknowledge, doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, That <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor hath it entred into the Heart of Man to conceive, what</hi> God <hi>hath laid up for thoſe that love Him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9. Which words he tranſcribes from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. But how they are any <hi>Prejudice</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> that I have propoſed, I do not find: For (beſides that the <hi>Words</hi> were ſpoken by the <hi>Prophet,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the great <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> that were to be made of the <hi>Divine</hi> Grace and Mercy, at <hi>That</hi> time, and in <hi>That</hi> State) I ſhall readily grant, that no <hi>Eye hath ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor hath the Heart of any Man conceived,</hi> what, and how <hi>Various,</hi> how <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Stupendious</hi> thoſe <hi>Objects</hi> will be, that the <hi>Future State</hi> will preſent unto our <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations.</hi> Who can tell, what <hi>Variety</hi> of Wonders the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the <hi>Living God</hi> may ſet before us? Who can imagine the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre</hi>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:62928:79"/>and <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem,</hi> and what are the <hi>Beings</hi> that do <hi>Embelliſh</hi> and <hi>Adorn</hi> the Palace of the <hi>Great King?</hi> Who can tell, or who can conceive, what <hi>Species</hi> or <hi>Kinds</hi> of <hi>Beings</hi> may be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the <hi>Whole</hi> Univerſe; and of what <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Amazing</hi> Natures, Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Perfections?</p>
            <p n="6">6. And as we cannot <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> what will be the <hi>Number, Kinds, Nature,</hi> nor <hi>Perfections</hi> of theſe things; ſo we cannot <hi>Tell</hi> what will be the <hi>Joy, Pleaſure, Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,</hi> yea, <hi>Extaſies</hi> and <hi>Raviſhments,</hi> that we ſhall <hi>Conceive,</hi> and have <hi>Experience</hi> of in the <hi>Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> of them. Who can imagine what <hi>Joy</hi> he ſhall feel, at the <hi>Sight,</hi> and <hi>Firſt Aſpect</hi> of the <hi>Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> Structure of the <hi>Heavenly Palace?</hi> At the <hi>Viſion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Holy Myriads,</hi> that encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> At the <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Holy Jeſus,</hi> that <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Earth?</hi> At the <hi>Sight</hi> of all the <hi>Holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> At the <hi>View</hi> of all the <hi>Holy Confeſſors</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> Men of all Generations? Who can imagine, what <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> every <hi>Object</hi> that is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to our Meditation, may <hi>Raiſe</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken</hi> in our Souls? Who can <hi>Think,</hi> what <hi>Joy</hi> we ſhall <hi>Conceive</hi> from our Exerciſe of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:62928:80"/>
               <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion</hi> of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Beloved</hi> of Him, and of the <hi>Eternal</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ation of it?</p>
            <p n="7">7. But though we cannot <hi>Conceive,</hi> nor have not <hi>Seen,</hi> nor <hi>Heard,</hi> what are the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>Objects,</hi> that the <hi>Future State</hi> will furniſh to our <hi>View</hi> and <hi>Conſideration;</hi> and though we cannot <hi>Imagine,</hi> what will be the <hi>Joys</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> that they will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce upon our <hi>Minds:</hi> Yet we may know, that there will be <hi>Objects</hi> of <hi>Various</hi> and <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Qualities; and that the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of them will make <hi>Very Great</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant</hi> Emotions and Affections upon our <hi>Souls;</hi> and that <hi>This</hi> Knowledge, and <hi>Theſe</hi> Affections may be of <hi>Progreſſive</hi> Nature and Increaſe to <hi>All</hi> Durations: Which is all that I have <hi>Aſſerted,</hi> and I think <hi>Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently</hi> conſiſtent with the Words of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> above-mentioned.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I know nothing <hi>Momentous,</hi> that may be objected againſt what I have <hi>Said</hi> on this <hi>Subject,</hi> which I have not <hi>Anſwered</hi> or <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated</hi> in <hi>Some</hi> Place or <hi>Other</hi> of <hi>This Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi> Nevertheleſs, 'tis no <hi>Article</hi> of my <hi>Faith;</hi> nor am I zealous to <hi>Proſelyte</hi> any Man to the <hi>Belief</hi> of it. I will Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with thoſe Words, where-with <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſius</hi> concludes his <hi>Principia.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:62928:80"/>
               <hi>At nihilominus memor meae tenuitatis, nihil affirmo: ſed haec omnia tum Eccleſiae Catholicae</hi> [Anglicanae] <hi>Authoritati; tum Prudentiorum Judiciis ſubmitto; nihil<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ab ullo credi velim, niſi quod ipſi evidens &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victa ratio perſuadebit.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
